[SOUND]
This
lecture is a brief
introduction to the course.
We're going to cover the objectives
of the course, the prerequisites and
course formats, reference books and
how to complete the course.
The objectives of the course
are the following.
First, we would like to
cover the basic context and
practical techniques of text data mining.
So this means we will not be able to
cover some advanced techniques in detail,
but whether we choose
the practical use for
techniques and then treat them in order.
We're going to also cover the basic
concepts that are very useful for
many applications.
The second objective is to cover
more general techniques for
text or data mining, so
we emphasize the coverage of general
techniques that can be applicable to
any text in any natural language.
We also hope that these
techniques to either
automatically work on problems
without any human effort or
only requiring minimum human effort.
So these criteria have
helped others to choose
techniques that can be
applied to many applications.
This is in contrast to some more
detailed analysis of text data,
particularly using natural
language processing techniques.
Now such techniques
are also very important.
And they are indeed, necessary for
some of the applications,
where we would like to go in-depth to
understand text, they are in more detail.
Such detail in understanding techniques,
however,
are generally not scalable and they
tend to require a lot of human effort.
So they cannot be easy
to apply to any domain.
So as you can imagine in practice,
it would be beneficial to combine
both kinds of techniques using
the general techniques that we'll be
covering in this course as a basis and
improve these techniques by using more
human effort whenever it's appropriate.
We also would like to provide a hands-on
experience to you in multiple aspects.
First, you'll do some experiments
using a text mining toolkit and
implementing text mining algorithms.
Second, you will have opportunity to
experiment with some algorithms for
text mining and
analytics to try them on some datasets and
to understand how to do experiments.
And finally, you have opportunity
to participate in a competition
of text-based prediction task.
You're expected to know the basic
concepts of computer science.
For example, the data structures and
some other really basic
concepts in computer science.
You are also expected to be
familiar with programming and
comfortable with programming,
particularly with C++.
This course,
however is not about programming.
So you are not expected to
do a lot of coding, but
we're going to give you C++ toolkit
that's fairly sophisticated.
So you have to be comfortable
with handling such a toolkit and
you may be asked to write
a small amount of code.
It's also useful if you
know some concepts and
techniques in probability and
statistics, but it's not necessary.
Knowing such knowledge would help you
understand some of the algorithm in
more depth.
The format of the course is lectures
plus quizzes that will be given to you
in the regular basis and there is
also optional programming assignment.
Now, we've made programming
assignments optional.
Not because it's not important, but
because we suspect that the not
all of you will have the need for
computing resources to do
the program assignment.
So naturally,
we would encourage all of you to try to do
the program assignments,
if possible as that will be a great way
to learn about the knowledge
that we teach in this course.
There's no required reading for
this course,
but I was list some of
the useful reference books here.
So we expect you to be able to understand
all the essential materials by just
watching the actual videos and
you should be able to answer all the quiz
questions by just watching the videos.
But it's always good to read additional
books in the larger scope of knowledge,
so here is this the four books.
The first is a textbook about
statistical language processing.
Some of the chapters [INAUDIBLE]
are especially relevant to this course.
The second one is a textbook
about information retrieval,
but it has broadly covered
a number of techniques that
are really in the category
of text mining techniques.
So it's also useful, because of that.
The third book is actually
a collection of silly articles and
it has broadly covered all
the aspects of mining text data.
The mostly relevant chapters
are also listed here.
In these chapters, you can find
some in depth discussion of cutting
edge research on the topics that
we discussed in this course.
And the last one is actually
a book that Sean Massung and
I are currently writing and
we're going to make the rough
draft chapters available at
this URL listed right here.
You can also find additional
reference books and
other readings at the URL
listed at the bottom.
So finally, some information about how
to complete the course this
information is also on the web.
So I just briefly go over it and
you can complete the course by
earning one of the following badges.
One is Course Achievement Badge.
To earn that,
you have to have at least a 70%
average score on all the quizzes combined.
It does mean every quiz has to be 70% or
better.
The second batch here,
this is a Course Mastery Badge and
this just requires a higher score,
90% average score for the quizzes.
There are also three
optional programming badges.
I said earlier that we encourage you
to do programming assignments, but
they're not necessary,
they're not required.
The first is
Programming Achievement Badge.
This is similar to the call
switching from the badge.
Here would require you to get at least 70%
average score on programming assignments.
And similarly, the mastery badge
is given to those who can score
90% average score or better.
The last badge is
a Text Mining Competition Leader Badge and
this is given to those of you who
do well in the competition task.
And specifically, we're planning to give
the badge to the top
30% in the leaderboard.
[MUSIC]