[SOUND] This lecture is
about the syntagmatic
relation discovery and
conditional entropy.
In this lecture,
we're going to continue the discussion
of word association mining and analysis.
We're going to talk about the conditional
entropy, which is useful for
discovering syntagmatic relations.
Earlier, we talked about
using entropy to capture
how easy it is to predict the presence or
absence of a word.
Now, we'll address
a different scenario where
we assume that we know something
about the text segment.
So now the question is, suppose we know
that eats occurred in the segment.
How would that help us
predict the presence or
absence of water, like in meat?
And in particular, we want to
know whether the presence of eats
has helped us predict
the presence of meat.
And if we frame this using entrophy,
that would mean we are interested
in knowing whether knowing
the presence of eats could reduce
uncertainty about the meats.
Or, reduce the entrophy
of the random variable
corresponding to the presence or
absence of meat.
We can also ask as a question,
what if we know of the absents of eats?
Would that also help us predict
the presence or absence of meat?
These questions can be
addressed by using another
concept called a conditioning entropy.
So to explain this concept, let's first
look at the scenario we had before,
when we know nothing about the segment.
So we have these probabilities indicating
whether a word like meat occurs,
or it doesn't occur in the segment.
And we have an entropy function that
looks like what you see on the slide.
Now suppose we know eats is present, so
now we know the value of another
random variable that denotes eats.
Now, that would change all
these probabilities to
conditional probabilities.
Where we look at the presence or
absence of meat,
given that we know eats
occurred in the context.
So as a result,
if we replace these probabilities
with their corresponding conditional
probabilities in the entropy function,
we'll get the conditional entropy.
So this equation now here would be
the conditional entropy.
Conditional on the presence of eats.
So, you can see this is essentially
the same entropy function as you have
seen before, except that all
the probabilities now have a condition.
And this then tells us
the entropy of meat,
after we have known eats
occurring in the segment.
And of course, we can also define
this conditional entropy for
the scenario where we don't see eats.
So if we know it did not occur in
the segment, then this entry condition of
entropy would capture the instances
of meat in that condition.
So now,
putting different scenarios together,
we have the completed definition
of conditional entropy as follows.
Basically, we're going to consider both
scenarios of the value of eats zero, one,
and this gives us a probability
that eats is equal to zero or one.
Basically, whether eats is present or
absent.
And this of course,
is the conditional entropy of
meat in that particular scenario.
So if you expanded this entropy,
then you have the following equation.
Where you see the involvement of
those conditional probabilities.
Now in general, for any discrete
random variables x and y, we have
the conditional entropy is no larger
than the entropy of the variable x.
So basically, this is upper bound for
the conditional entropy.
That means by knowing more
information about the segment,
we want to be able to
increase uncertainty.
We can only reduce uncertainty.
And that intuitively makes sense
because as we know more information,
it should always help
us make the prediction.
And cannot hurt
the prediction in any case.
Now, what's interesting here is also to
think about what's the minimum possible
value of this conditional entropy?
Now, we know that the maximum
value is the entropy of X.
But what about the minimum,
so what do you think?
I hope you can reach the conclusion that
the minimum possible value, would be zero.
And it will be interesting to think about
under what situation will achieve this.
So, let's see how we can use conditional
entropy to capture syntagmatic relation.
Now of course,
this conditional entropy gives us directly
one way to measure
the association of two words.
Because it tells us to what extent,
we can predict the one
word given that we know the presence or
absence of another word.
Now before we look at the intuition
of conditional entropy in capturing
syntagmatic relations, it's useful to
think of a very special case, listed here.
That is, the conditional entropy
of the word given itself.
So here,
we listed this conditional
entropy in the middle.
So, it's here.
So, what is the value of this?
Now, this means we know where
the meat occurs in the sentence.
And we hope to predict whether
And of course, this is 0 because
there's no incident anymore.
Once we know whether the word
occurs in the segment,
we'll already know the answer
of the prediction.
So this is zero.
And that's also when this conditional
entropy reaches the minimum.
So now, let's look at some other cases.
So this is a case of knowing the and
trying to predict the meat.
And this is a case of knowing eats and
Which one do you think is smaller?
No doubt smaller entropy means easier for
prediction.
Which one do you think is higher?
Which one is not smaller?
Well, if you at the uncertainty,
then in the first case,
the doesn't really tell
us much about the meat.
So knowing the occurrence of the doesn't
really help us reduce entropy that much.
So it stays fairly close to
the original entropy of meat.
Whereas in the case of eats,
eats is related to meat.
So knowing presence of eats or
absence of eats,
would help us predict whether meat occurs.
So it can help us reduce entropy of meat.
So we should expect the sigma term, namely
this one, to have a smaller entropy.
And that means there is a stronger
association between meat and eats.
So we now also know when
this w is the same as this
meat, then the conditional entropy
would reach its minimum, which is 0.
And for what kind of words
would either reach its maximum?
Well, that's when this stuff
is not really related to meat.
And like the for example,
it would be very close to the maximum,
which is the entropy of meat itself.
So this suggests that when you
use conditional entropy for
mining syntagmatic relations,
the hours would look as follows.
For each word W1, we're going to
enumerate the overall other words W2.
And then, we can compute
the conditional entropy of W1 given W2.
We thought all the candidate was in
ascending order of the conditional entropy
because we're out of favor,
a world that has a small entropy.
Meaning that it helps us predict
the time of the word W1.
And then, we're going to take the top ring
of the candidate words as words that have
potential syntagmatic relations with W1.
Note that we need to use
a threshold to find these words.
The stresser can be the number
of top candidates take, or
absolute value for
the conditional entropy.
Now, this would allow us to mine the most
strongly correlated words with
a particular word, W1 here.
But, this algorithm does not
help us mine the strongest
that K syntagmatical relations
from an entire collection.
Because in order to do that, we have to
ensure that these conditional entropies
are comparable across different words.
In this case of discovering
the mathematical relations for
a targeted word like W1, we only need
to compare the conditional entropies
for W1, given different words.
And in this case, they are comparable.
All right.
So, the conditional entropy of W1, given
W2, and the conditional entropy of W1,
given W3 are comparable.
They all measure how hard
it is to predict the W1.
But, if we think about the two pairs,
where we share W2 in the same condition,
and we try to predict the W1 and W3.
Then, the conditional entropies
are actually not comparable.
You can think of about this question.
Why?
So why are they not comfortable?
Well, that was because they
have a different outer bounds.
Right?
So those outer bounds are precisely
the entropy of W1 and the entropy of W3.
And they have different upper bounds.
So we cannot really
compare them in this way.
So how do we address this problem?
Well later, we'll discuss, we can use
mutual information to solve this problem.
[MUSIC]