[SOUND] This lecture is
about the word association
mining and analysis.
In this lecture,
we're going to talk about how to mine
associations of words from text.
Now this is an example of knowledge
about the natural language that
we can mine from text data.
Here's the outline.
We're going to first talk about
what is word association and
then explain why discovering such
relations is useful and finally
we're going to talk about some general
ideas about how to mine word associations.
In general there are two word
relations and these are quite basic.
One is called a paradigmatic relation.
The other is syntagmatic relation.
A and B have paradigmatic relation
if they can be substituted for each other.
That means the two words that
have paradigmatic relation
would be in the same semantic class,
or syntactic class.
And we can in general
replace one by the other
without affecting
the understanding of the sentence.
That means we would still
have a valid sentence.
For example, cat and dog, these two
words have a paradigmatic relation
because they are in
the same class of animal.
And in general,
if you replace cat with dog in a sentence,
the sentence would still be a valid
sentence that you can make sense of.
Similarly Monday and
Tuesday have paradigmatical relation.
The second kind of relation is
called syntagmatical relation.
In this case, the two words that have this
relation, can be combined with each other.
So A and B have syntagmatic relation if
they can be combined with each other in
a sentence, that means these two
words are semantically related.
So for example, cat and sit are related
because a cat can sit somewhere.
Similarly, car and
drive are related semantically and
they can be combined with
each other to convey meaning.
However, in general, we can not
replace cat with sit in a sentence or
car with drive in the sentence
to still get a valid sentence,
meaning that if we do that, the sentence
will become somewhat meaningless.
So this is different from
paradigmatic relation.
And these two relations are in fact so
fundamental that they can be
generalized to capture basic relations
between units in arbitrary sequences.
And definitely they can be
generalized to describe
relations of any items in a language.
So, A and B don't have to be words and
they can be phrases, for example.
And they can even be more complex
phrases than just a non-phrase.
If you think about the general
problem of the sequence mining
then we can think about the units
being and the sequence data.
Then we think of paradigmatic
relation as relations that
are applied to units that tend to occur
in a singular locations in a sentence,
or in a sequence of data
elements in general.
So they occur in similar locations
relative to the neighbors in the sequence.
Syntagmatical relation on
the other hand is related to
co-occurrent elements that tend
to show up in the same sequence.
So these two are complimentary and
are basic relations of words.
And we're interested in discovering
them automatically from text data.
Discovering such worded
relations has many applications.
First, such relations can be directly
useful for improving accuracy of many NLP
tasks, and this is because this is part
of our knowledge about a language.
So if you know these two words
are synonyms, for example,
and then you can help a lot of tasks.
And grammar learning can be also
done by using such techniques.
Because if we can learn
paradigmatic relations,
then we form classes of words,
syntactic classes for example.
And if we learn syntagmatic relations,
then we would be able to know
the rules for putting together a larger
expression based on component expressions.
So we learn the structure and
what can go with what else.
Word relations can be also very useful for
many applications in text retrieval and
mining.
For example, in search and
text retrieval, we can use word
associations to modify a query,
and this can be used to
introduce additional related words into
a query and make the query more effective.
It's often called a query expansion.
Or you can use related words to
suggest related queries to the user
to explore the information space.
Another application is to
use word associations to
automatically construct the top
of the map for browsing.
We can have words as nodes and
associations as edges.
A user could navigate from
one word to another to
find information in the information space.
Finally, such word associations can also
be used to compare and summarize opinions.
For example, we might be interested
in understanding positive and
negative opinions about the iPhone 6.
In order to do that, we can look at what
words are most strongly associated with
a feature word like battery in
positive versus negative reviews.
Such a syntagmatical
relations would help us
show the detailed opinions
about the product.
So, how can we discover such
associations automatically?
Now, here are some intuitions
about how to do that.
Now let's first look at
the paradigmatic relation.
Here we essentially can take
advantage of similar context.
So here you see some simple
sentences about cat and dog.
You can see they generally
occur in similar context,
and that after all is the definition
of paradigmatic relation.
On the right side you can kind
of see I extracted expressly
the context of cat and
dog from this small sample of text data.
I've taken away cat and
dog from these sentences, so
that you can see just the context.
Now, of course we can have different
perspectives to look at the context.
For example, we can look at
what words occur in the left
part of this context.
So we can call this left context.
What words occur before we see cat or dog?
So, you can see in this case, clearly
dog and cat have similar left context.
You generally say his cat or my cat and
you say also, my dog and his dog.
So that makes them similar
in the left context.
Similarly, if you look at the words
that occur after cat and dog,
which we can call right context,
they are also very similar in this case.
Of course, it's an extreme case,
where you only see eats.
And in general,
you'll see many other words, of course,
that can't follow cat and dog.
You can also even look
at the general context.
And that might include all
the words in the sentence or
in sentences around this word.
And even in the general context, you also
see similarity between the two words.
So this was just a suggestion
that we can discover paradigmatic
relation by looking at
the similarity of context of words.
So, for example,
if we think about the following questions.
How similar are context of cat and
context of dog?
In contrast how similar are context
of cat and context of computer?
Now, intuitively,
we're to imagine the context of cat and
the context of dog would
be more similar than
the context of cat and
context of the computer.
That means, in the first case
the similarity value would be high,
between the context of cat and
dog, where as in the second,
the similarity between context of cat and
computer would be low
because they all not having a paradigmatic
relationship and imagine what words
occur after computer in general.
It would be very different from
what words occur after cat.
So this is the basic idea of what
this covering, paradigmatic relation.
What about the syntagmatic relation?
Well, here we're going to explore
the correlated occurrences,
again based on the definition
of syntagmatic relation.
Here you see the same sample of text.
But here we're interested in knowing
what other words are correlated
with the verb eats and
what words can go with eats.
And if you look at the right
side of this slide and
you see,
I've taken away the two words around eats.
I've taken away the word to its left and
also the word to its
right in each sentence.
And then we ask the question, what words
tend to occur to the left of eats?
And what words tend to
occur to the right of eats?
Now thinking about this question
would help us discover syntagmatic
relations because syntagmatic relations
essentially captures such correlations.
So the important question to ask for
syntagmatical relation is,
whenever eats occurs,
what other words also tend to occur?
So the question here has
to do with whether there
are some other words that tend
to co-occur together with each.
Meaning that whenever you see eats
you tend to see the other words.
And if you don't see eats, probably,
you don't see other words often either.
So this intuition can help
discover syntagmatic relations.
Now again, consider example.
How helpful is occurrence of eats for
predicting occurrence of meat?
Right.
All right, so knowing whether eats occurs
in a sentence would generally help us
predict whether meat also occurs indeed.
And if we see eats occur in the sentence,
and
that should increase the chance
that meat would also occur.
In contrast,
if you look at the question in the bottom,
how helpful is the occurrence of eats for
predicting of occurrence of text?
Because eats and
text are not really related, so
knowing whether eats occurred
in the sentence doesn't
really help us predict the weather,
text also occurs in the sentence.
So this is in contrast to
the question about eats and meat.
This also helps explain that intuition
behind the methods of what
discovering syntagmatic relations.
Mainly we need to capture the correlation
between the occurrences of two words.
So to summarize the general ideas for
discovering word associations
are the following.
For paradigmatic relation,
we present each word by its context.
And then compute its context similarity.
We're going to assume the words
that have high context similarity
to have paradigmatic relation.
For syntagmatic relation, we will count
how many times two words occur together
in a context, which can be a sentence,
a paragraph, or a document even.
And we're going to compare
their co-occurrences with
their individual occurrences.
We're going to assume words
with high co-occurrences but
relatively low individual occurrences
to have syntagmatic relations
because they attempt to occur together and
they don't usually occur alone.
Note that the paradigmatic relation and
the syntagmatic relation
are actually closely related
in that paradigmatically
related words tend to have syntagmatic
relation with the same word.
They tend to be associated
with the same word, and
that suggests that we can also do join
the discovery of the two relations.
So these general ideas can be
implemented in many different ways.
And the course won't cover all of them,
but
we will cover at least some of
the methods that are effective for
discovering these relations.
[MUSIC]