[SOUND] In this lecture
we continue discussing
Paradigmatic Relation Discovery.
Earlier we introduced a method called
Expected Overlap of Words in Context.
In this method we represent each
context by a word of vector
that represents the probability
of a word in the context.
And we measure the similarity by using the
dot product which can be interpreted as
the probability that two randomly picked
words from the two contexts are identical.
We also discussed the two
problems of this method.
The first is that it favors
matching one frequent term
very well over matching
more distinct terms.
It put too much emphasis on
matching one term very well.
The second is that it
treats every word equally.
Even a common word like
the would contribute equally
as content word like eats.
So now we are going to talk about
how to solve this problems.
More specifically we're going to
introduce some retrieval heuristics
used in text retrieval and these
heuristics can effectively solve these
problems as these problems also occur
in text retrieval when we match a query
with a document, so
to address the first problem,
we can use a sublinear
transformation of term frequency.
That is, we don't have to use raw
frequency count of the term to represent
the context.
We can transform it into some form that
wouldn't emphasize so much on the raw
frequency to address the problem,
we can put more weight on rare terms.
And that is,
we ran reward a matching a rare word.
And this heuristic is called IDF
term weighting in text retrieval.
IDF stands for inverse document frequency.
So now we're going to talk about
the two heuristics in more detail.
First, let's talk about
the TF transformation.
That is, it'll convert the raw count of
a word in the document into some weight
that reflects our belief about
how important this wording.
The document.
And so,
that would be denoted by TF of w and d.
That's shown in the Y axis.
Now, in general,
there are many ways to map that.
And let's first look at
the the simple way of mapping.
In this case, we're going to say, well,
any non zero counts will be mapped to one.
And the zero count will be mapped to zero.
So with this mapping, all the frequencies
will be mapped to only two values,
zero or one.
And the mapping function is
shown here as a flat line here.
This is naive because in order
the frequency of words, however,
this actually has
advantage of emphasizing,
matching all the words in the context.
It does not allow a frequent
word to dominate the match now
the approach that we have taken earlier
in the overlap account approach
is a linear transformation we
basically take y as the same as x so
we use the raw count as
a representation and
that created the problem
that we just talked about.
Namely, it emphasizes too much
on matching one frequent term.
Matching one frequent term
can contribute a lot.
We can have a lot of other interesting
transformations in between
the two extremes.
And they generally form
a sub linear transformation.
So for example,
one a logarithm of the row count.
And this will give us curve that looks
like this that you are seeing here.
In this case,
you can see the high frequency counts.
The high counts are penalized
a little bit all right,
so the curve is a sub linear curve.
And it brings down the weight
of those really high counts.
And this what we want because it prevents
that kind of terms from
dominating the scoring function.
Now, there is also another interesting
transformation called a BM25
transformation, which as been shown
to be very effective for retrieval.
And in this transformation we
have a form that looks like this.
So it's k plus one multiplies by x,
divided by x plus k.
Where k is a parameter.
X is the count.
The raw count of a word.
Now the transformation is very
interesting, in that it can actually
kind of go from one extreme to
the other extreme by varying k,
and it also is interesting that it
has upper bound, k + 1 in this case.
So, this puts a very strict
constraint on high frequency terms,
because their weight
will never exceed k + 1.
As we vary k,
we can simulate the two extremes.
So, when is set to zero,
we roughly have the zero one vector.
Whereas, when we set the k
to a very large value,
it will behave more like,
immediate transformation.
So this transformation function is by far
the most effective transformation function
for tax and retrieval, and it also
makes sense for our problem set up.
So we just talked about how to solve the
problem of overemphasizing a frequently,
a frequently tongue.
Now let's look at the second problem, and
that is how we can penalize popular terms,
matching the is not surprising
because the occurs everywhere.
But matching eats would count a lot so
how can we address that problem.
In this case we can use the IDF weight.
Pop that's commonly used in retrieval.
IDF stands for inverse document frequency.
Now frequency means the count of
the total number of documents
that contain a particular word.
So here we show that the IDF measure
is defined as a logarithm function
of the number of documents that
match a term or document frequency.
So, k is the number of documents
containing a word, or document frequency.
And M here is the total number
of documents in the collection.
The IDF function is
giving a higher value for
a lower k,
meaning that it rewards a rare term, and
the maximum value is log of M+1.
That's when the word occurred just once in
the context, so that's a very rare term.
The rarest term in the whole collection.
The lowest value you can see here is when
K reaches its maximum, which would be M.
All right so,
that would be a very low value,
close to zero in fact.
So, this of course measure
is used in search.
Where we naturally have a collection.
In our case, what would be our collection?
Well, we can also use the context
that we had collected for
all the words as our collection.
And that is to say, a word that's
populating the collection in general.
Would also have a low
IDF because depending
on the dataset we can Construct
the context vectors in the different ways.
But in the end, if a term is very
frequently original data set.
Then it will still be frequenting
the collective context documents.
So how can we add these
heuristics to improve our
similarity function well here's one way.
And there are many other
ways that are possible.
But this is a reasonable way.
Where we can adapt the BM25
retrieval model for
paradigmatic relation mining.
So here, we define,
in this case we define
the document vector as
containing elements representing
normalized BM25 values.
So in this normalization function, we see,
we take a sum over, sum of all the words.
And we normalize the weight
of each word by the sum of
the weights of all the words.
And this is to, again, ensure all
the xi's will sum to 1 in this vector.
So this would be very similar
to what we had before,
in that this vector is actually something
similar to a word distribution.
Or the xis with sum to 1.
Now the weight of BM25 for
each word is defined here.
And if you compare this with our old
definition where we just have a normalized
count, of this one so
we only have this one and
the document lens of
the total counts of words.
Being that context document and
that's what we had before.
But now with the BM25 transformation,
we're introduced to something else.
First off, because this extra occurrence
of this count is just to achieve
the of normalization.
But we also see we introduced
the parameter k here.
And this parameter is generally non active
number although zero is also possible.
This controls the upper bound and
the kind of all
to what extent it simulates
the linear transformation.
And so this is one parameter, but we also
see there was another parameter here, B.
And this would be within 0 an 1.
And this is a parameter to
control length] normalization.
And in this case, the normalization
formula has average document length here.
And this is computed by
taking the average of
the lengths of all the documents
in the collection.
In this case, all the lengths
of all the context documents.
That we are considering.
So this average document will be
a constant for any given collection.
So it actually is only
affecting the factor of
the parameter b here
because this is a constant.
But I kept it here because it's
constant and that's useful
in retrieval where it would give us a
stabilized interpretation of parameter B.
But, for
our purpose it would be a constant.
So it would only be affecting the length
normalization together with parameter b.
Now with this definition then, we have a
new way to define our document of vectors.
And we can compute the vector
d2 in the same way.
The difference is that the high
frequency terms will now have a somewhat
lower weight.
And this would help us control the
influence of these high frequency terms.
Now, the idea can be added
here in the scoring function.
That means we will introduce a way for
matching each time.
You may recall, this is sum that indicates
all the possible words that can be
overlapped between the two contacts.
And the Xi and the Yi are probabilities
of picking the word from both context,
therefore,
it indicates how likely we'll
see a match on this word.
Now, IDF would give us the importance
of matching this word.
A common word will be worth
less than a rare word, and so
we emphasize more on
matching rare words now.
So, with this modification,
then the new function.
When likely to address those two problems.
Now interestingly,
we can also use this approach to
discover syntagmatical relations.
In general,
when we represent a term vector to replant
a context with a term
vector we would likely see,
some terms have higher weights, and
other terms have lower weights.
Depending on how we assign
weights to these terms,
we might be able to use
these weights to discover
the words that are strongly associated
with a candidate of word in the context.
It's interesting that we can
also use this context for
similarity function based on BM25
to discover syntagmatic relations.
So, the idea is to use the converted
implantation of the context.
To see which terms are scored high.
And if a term has high weight,
then that term might be more strongly
related to the candidate word.
So let's take a look at
the vector in more detail here.
And we have
each Xi defined as
a normalized weight of BM25.
Now this weight alone only reflects how
frequent the word occurs in the context.
But, we can't just say an infrequent
term in the context would be
correlated with the candidate word
because many common words like the will
occur frequently out of context.
But if we apply IDF
weighting as you see here,
we can then re weigh
these terms based on IDF.
That means the words that are common,
like the, will get penalized.
so now the highest weighted terms will not
be those common terms because they have
lower IDFs.
Instead, those terms would be the terms
that are frequently in the context but
not frequent in the collection.
So those are clearly the words
that tend to occur in the context
of the candidate word, for example, cat.
So, for this reason, the highly weighted
terms in this idea of weighted vector
can also be assumed to be candidates for
syntagmatic relations.
Now, of course, this is only
a byproduct of how approach is for
discovering parathmatic relations.
And in the next lecture,
we're going to talk more about how
to discover syntagmatic relations.
But it clearly shows the relation
between discovering the two relations.
And indeed they can be discussed.
Discovered in a joined
manner by leveraging
such associations, namely syntactical
relation words that are similar in,
yeah it also shows the relation between
syntagmatic relation discovery and
the paradgratical relations discovery.
We may be able to leverage the relation to
join the discovery of
two kinds of relations.
This also shows some interesting
connections between the discovery of
syntagmatic relation and
the paradigmatic relation.
Specifically those words that
are paradigmatic related tend to be
having a syntagmatic
relation with the same word.
So to summarize the main idea of what
is covering paradigmatic relations
is to collect the context of a candidate
word to form a pseudo document,
and this is typically
represented as a bag of words.
And then compute similarity of
the corresponding context documents
of two candidate words.
And then we can take the highly
similar word pairs and
treat them as having
paradigmatic relations.
These are the words that
share similar contexts.
There are many different ways
to implement this general idea,
and we just talked about
some of the approaches, and
more specifically we talked about
using text retrieval models to help
us design effective similarity function
to compute the paradigmatic relations.
More specifically we
have used the BM25 and
IDF weighting to discover
paradigmatic relation.
And these approaches also
represent the state of the art.
In text retrieval techniques.
Finally, syntagmatic relations
can also be discovered as a by
product when we discover
paradigmatic relations.
[MUSIC]