[SOUND]
This
lecture is about probabilistic and
latent Semantic Analysis or PLSA.
In this lecture we're going to introduce
probabilistic latent semantic analysis,
often called PLSA.
This is the most basic topic model,
also one of the most useful topic models.
Now this kind of models
can in general be used to
mine multiple topics from text documents.
And PRSA is one of the most basic
topic models for doing this.
So let's first examine this power
in the e-mail for more detail.
Here I show a sample article which is
a blog article about Hurricane Katrina.
And I show some simple topics.
For example government response,
flood of the city of New Orleans.
Donation and the background.
You can see in the article we use
words from all these distributions.
So we first for example see there's
a criticism of government response and
this is followed by discussion of flooding
of the city and donation et cetera.
We also see background
words mixed with them.
So the overall of topic analysis here
is to try to decode these topics behind
the text, to segment the topics,
to figure out which words are from which
distribution and to figure out first,
what are these topics?
How do we know there's a topic
about government response.
There's a topic about a flood in the city.
So these are the tasks
at the top of the model.
If we had discovered these
topics can color these words,
as you see here,
to separate the different topics.
Then you can do a lot of things,
such as summarization, or segmentation,
of the topics,
clustering of the sentences etc.
So the formal definition of problem of
mining multiple topics from text is
shown here.
And this is after a slide that you
have seen in an earlier lecture.
So the input is a collection, the number
of topics, and a vocabulary set, and
of course the text data.
And then the output is of two kinds.
One is the topic category,
characterization.
Theta i's.
Each theta i is a word distribution.
And second, it's the topic coverage for
each document.
These are pi sub i j's.
And they tell us which document it covers.
Which topic to what extent.
So we hope to generate these as output.
Because there are many useful
applications if we can do that.
So the idea of PLSA is
actually very similar to
the two component mixture model
that we have already introduced.
The only difference is that we
are going to have more than two topics.
Otherwise, it is essentially the same.
So here I illustrate how we can generate
the text that has multiple topics and
naturally in all cases
of Probabilistic modelling would want
to figure out the likelihood function.
So we would also ask the question,
what's the probability of observing
a word from such a mixture model?
Now if you look at this picture and
compare this with the picture
that we have seen earlier,
you will see the only difference is
that we have added more topics here.
So, before we have just one topic,
besides the background topic.
But now we have more topics.
Specifically, we have k topics now.
All these are topics that we assume
that exist in the text data.
So the consequence is that our switch for
choosing a topic is now a multiway switch.
Before it's just a two way switch.
We can think of it as flipping a coin.
But now we have multiple ways.
First we can flip a coin to decide
whether we're talk about the background.
So it's the background lambda
sub B versus non-background.
1 minus lambda sub B gives
us the probability of
actually choosing a non-background topic.
After we have made this decision,
we have to make another decision to
choose one of these K distributions.
So there are K way switch here.
And this is characterized by pi,
and this sum to one.
This is just the difference of designs.
Which is a little bit more complicated.
But once we decide which distribution to
use the rest is the same we are going to
just generate a word by using one of
these distributions as shown here.
So now lets look at the question
about the likelihood.
So what's the probability of observing
a word from such a distribution?
What do you think?
Now we've seen this
problem many times now and
if you can recall, it's generally a sum.
Of all the different possibilities
of generating a word.
So let's first look at how the word can
be generated from the background mode.
Well, the probability that the word is
generated from the background model
is lambda multiplied by the probability
of the word from the background mode.
Model, right.
Two things must happen.
First, we have to have
chosen the background model,
and that's the probability of lambda,
of sub b.
Then second, we must have actually
obtained the word w from the background,
and that's probability
of w given theta sub b.
Okay, so similarly,
we can figure out the probability of
observing the word from another topic.
Like the topic theta sub k.
Now notice that here's
the product of three terms.
And that's because of the choice
of topic theta sub k,
only happens if two things happen.
One is we decide not to
talk about background.
So, that's a probability
of 1 minus lambda sub B.
Second, we also have to actually choose
theta sub K among these K topics.
So that's probability of theta sub K,
or pi.
And similarly, the probability of
generating a word from the second.
The topic and the first topic
are like what you are seeing here.
And so
in the end the probability of observing
the word is just a sum of all these cases.
And I have to stress again this is a very
important formula to know because this is
really key to understanding all the topic
models and indeed a lot of mixture models.
So make sure that you really
understand the probability
of w is indeed the sum of these terms.
So, next,
once we have the likelihood function,
we would be interested in
knowing the parameters.
All right, so to estimate the parameters.
But firstly,
let's put all these together to have the
complete likelihood of function for PLSA.
The first line shows the probability of a
word as illustrated on the previous slide.
And this is an important
formula as I said.
So let's take a closer look at this.
This actually commands all
the important parameters.
So first of all we see lambda sub b here.
This represents a percentage
of background words
that we believe exist in the text data.
And this can be a known value
that we set empirically.
Second, we see the background
language model, and
typically we also assume this is known.
We can use a large collection of text, or
use all the text that we have available
to estimate the world of distribution.
Now next in the next stop this formula.
[COUGH] Excuse me.
You see two interesting
kind of parameters,
those are the most important parameters.
That we are.
So one is pi's.
And these are the coverage
of a topic in the document.
And the other is word distributions
that characterize all the topics.
So the next line,
then is simply to plug this
in to calculate
the probability of document.
This is, again, of the familiar
form where you have a sum and
you have a count of
a word in the document.
And then log of a probability.
Now it's a little bit more
complicated than the two component.
Because now we have more components,
so the sum involves more terms.
And then this line is just
the likelihood for the whole collection.
And it's very similar, just accounting for
more documents in the collection.
So what are the unknown parameters?
I already said that there are two kinds.
One is coverage,
one is word distributions.
Again, it's a useful exercise for
you to think about.
Exactly how many
parameters there are here.
How many unknown parameters are there?
Now, try and
think out that question will help you
understand the model in more detail.
And will also allow you to understand
what would be the output that we generate
when use PLSA to analyze text data?
And these are precisely
the unknown parameters.
So after we have obtained
the likelihood function shown here,
the next is to worry about
the parameter estimation.
And we can do the usual think,
maximum likelihood estimator.
So again, it's a constrained optimization
problem, like what we have seen before.
Only that we have a collection of text and
we have more parameters to estimate.
And we still have two constraints,
two kinds of constraints.
One is the word distributions.
All the words must have probabilities
that's sum to one for one distribution.
The other is the topic
coverage distribution and
a document will have to cover
precisely these k topics so
the probability of covering each
topic that would have to sum to 1.
So at this point though it's basically
a well defined applied math problem,
you just need to figure out
the solutions to optimization problem.
There's a function with many variables.
and we need to just figure
out the patterns of these
variables to make the function
reach its maximum.
>> [MUSIC]