[MUSIC]
This lecture is about topic mining and
analysis.
We're going to talk about
using a term as topic.
This is a slide that you have
seen in a earlier lecture
where we define the task of
topic mining and analysis.
We also raised the question, how do
we exactly define the topic of theta?
So in this lecture, we're going to
offer one way to define it, and
that's our initial idea.
Our idea here is defining
a topic simply as a term.
A term can be a word or a phrase.
And in general,
we can use these terms to describe topics.
So our first thought is just
to define a topic as one term.
For example, we might have terms
like sports, travel, or science,
as you see here.
Now if we define a topic in this way,
we can then analyze the coverage
of such topics in each document.
Here for example,
we might want to discover to what
extent document one covers sports.
And we found that 30% of the content
of document one is about sports.
And 12% is about the travel, etc.
We might also discover document
two does not cover sports at all.
So the coverage is zero, etc.
So now, of course,
as we discussed in the task definition for
topic mining and analysis,
we have two tasks.
One is to discover the topics.
And the second is to analyze coverage.
So let's first think
about how we can discover
topics if we represent
each topic by a term.
So that means we need to mine k
topical terms from a collection.
Now there are, of course,
many different ways of doing that.
And we're going to talk about
a natural way of doing that,
which is also likely effective.
So first of all,
we're going to parse the text data in
the collection to obtain candidate terms.
Here candidate terms can be words or
phrases.
Let's say the simplest solution is
to just take each word as a term.
These words then become candidate topics.
Then we're going to design a scoring
function to match how good each term
is as a topic.
So how can we design such a function?
Well there are many things
that we can consider.
For example, we can use pure statistics
to design such a scoring function.
Intuitively, we would like to
favor representative terms,
meaning terms that can represent
a lot of content in the collection.
So that would mean we want
to favor a frequent term.
However, if we simply use the frequency
to design the scoring function,
then the highest scored terms
would be general terms or
functional terms like the, etc.
Those terms occur very frequently English.
So we also want to avoid having
such words on the top so
we want to penalize such words.
But in general, we would like to favor
terms that are fairly frequent but
not so frequent.
So a particular approach could be based
on TF-IDF weighting from retrieval.
And TF stands for term frequency.
IDF stands for inverse document frequency.
We talked about some of these
ideas in the lectures about
the discovery of word associations.
So these are statistical methods,
meaning that the function is
defined mostly based on statistics.
So the scoring function
would be very general.
It can be applied to any language,
any text.
But when we apply such a approach
to a particular problem,
we might also be able to leverage
some domain-specific heuristics.
For example, in news we might favor
title words actually general.
We might want to favor title
words because the authors tend to
use the title to describe
the topic of an article.
If we're dealing with tweets,
we could also favor hashtags,
which are invented to denote topics.
So naturally, hashtags can be good
candidates for representing topics.
Anyway, after we have this design
scoring function, then we can discover
the k topical terms by simply picking
k terms with the highest scores.
Now, of course,
we might encounter situation where the
highest scored terms are all very similar.
They're semantically similar, or
closely related, or even synonyms.
So that's not desirable.
So we also want to have coverage over
all the content in the collection.
So we would like to remove redundancy.
And one way to do that is
to do a greedy algorithm,
which is sometimes called a maximal
marginal relevance ranking.
Basically, the idea is to go down
the list based on our scoring
function and gradually take terms
to collect the k topical terms.
The first term, of course, will be picked.
When we pick the next term, we're
going to look at what terms have already
been picked and try to avoid
picking a term that's too similar.
So while we are considering
the ranking of a term in the list,
we are also considering
the redundancy of the candidate term
with respect to the terms
that we already picked.
And with some thresholding,
then we can get a balance of
the redundancy removal and
also high score of a term.
Okay, so
after this that will get k topical terms.
And those can be regarded as the topics
that we discovered from the connection.
Next, let's think about how we're going
to compute the topic coverage pi sub ij.
So looking at this picture,
we have sports, travel and science and
these topics.
And now suppose you are give a document.
How should we pick out coverage
of each topic in the document?
Well, one approach can be to simply
count occurrences of these terms.
So for example, sports might have occurred
four times in this this document and
travel occurred twice, etc.
And then we can just normalize these
counts as our estimate of the coverage
probability for each topic.
So in general, the formula would
be to collect the counts of
all the terms that represent the topics.
And then simply normalize them so
that the coverage of each
topic in the document would add to one.
This forms a distribution of the topics
for the document to characterize coverage
of different topics in the document.
Now, as always,
when we think about idea for
solving problem, we have to ask
the question, how good is this one?
Or is this the best way
of solving problem?
So now let's examine this approach.
In general,
we have to do some empirical evaluation
by using actual data sets and
to see how well it works.
Well, in this case let's take
a look at a simple example here.
And we have a text document that's
about a NBA basketball game.
So in terms of the content,
it's about sports.
But if we simply count these
words that represent our topics,
we will find that the word sports
actually did not occur in the article,
even though the content
is about the sports.
So the count of sports is zero.
That means the coverage of sports
would be estimated as zero.
Now of course,
the term science also did not occur in
the document and
it's estimate is also zero.
And that's okay.
But sports certainly is not okay because
we know the content is about sports.
So this estimate has problem.
What's worse, the term travel
actually occurred in the document.
So when we estimate the coverage
of the topic travel,
we have got a non-zero count.
So its estimated coverage
will be non-zero.
So this obviously is also not desirable.
So this simple example illustrates
some problems of this approach.
First, when we count what
words belong to to the topic,
we also need to consider related words.
We can't simply just count
the topic word sports.
In this case, it did not occur at all.
But there are many related words
like basketball, game, etc.
So we need to count
the related words also.
The second problem is that a word
like star can be actually ambiguous.
So here it probably means
a basketball star, but
we can imagine it might also
mean a star on the sky.
So in that case, the star might actually
suggest, perhaps, a topic of science.
So we need to deal with that as well.
Finally, a main restriction of this
approach is that we have only one
term to describe the topic, so it cannot
really describe complicated topics.
For example, a very specialized
topic in sports would be harder to
describe by using just a word or
one phrase.
We need to use more words.
So this example illustrates
some general problems with
this approach of treating a term as topic.
First, it lacks expressive power.
Meaning that it can only represent
the simple general topics, but
it cannot represent the complicated topics
that might require more words to describe.
Second, it's incomplete
in vocabulary coverage,
meaning that the topic itself
is only represented as one term.
It does not suggest what other
terms are related to the topic.
Even if we're talking about sports,
there are many terms that are related.
So it does not allow us to easily
count related terms to order,
conversion to coverage of this topic.
Finally, there is this problem
of word sense disintegration.
A topical term or
related term can be ambiguous.
For example,
basketball star versus star in the sky.
So in the next lecture,
we're going to talk
about how to solve
the problem with of a topic.
[MUSIC]