[SOUND]
We can compute this maximum estimate
by using the EM algorithm.
So in the e step,
we now have to introduce more hidden
variables because we have more topics,
so our hidden variable z now,
which is a topic indicator can
take more than two values.
So specifically will
take a k plus one values,
with b in the noting the background.
And once locate,
to denote other k topics, right.
So, now the e step, as you can
recall is your augmented data, and
by predicting the values
of the hidden variable.
So we're going to predict for
a word, whether the word has come from
one of these k plus one distributions.
This equation allows us to
predict the probability
that the word w in document d is
generated from topic zero sub j.
And the bottom one is
the predicted probability that this
word has been generated
from the background.
Note that we use document
d here to index the word.
Why?
Because whether a word is
from a particular topic
actually depends on the document.
Can you see why?
Well, it's through the pi's.
The pi's are tied to each document.
Each document can have potentially
different pi's, right.
The pi's will then affect our prediction.
So, the pi's are here.
And this depends on the document.
And that might give a different guess for
a word in different documents,
and that's desirable.
In both cases we are using
the Baye's Rule, as I explained, basically
assessing the likelihood of generating
word from each of this division and
there's normalize.
What about the m step?
Well, we may recall the m step is we
take advantage of the inferred z values.
To split the counts.
And then collected the right counts
to re-estimate the parameters.
So in this case, we can re-estimate
our coverage of probability.
And this is re-estimated based on
collecting all the words in the document.
And that's why we have the count
of the word in document.
And sum over all the words.
And then we're going to look at to
what extent this word belongs to
the topic theta sub j.
And this part is our guess from each step.
This tells us how likely this word
is actually from theta sub j.
And when we multiply them together,
we get the discounted count that's
located for topic theta sub j.
And when we normalize
this over all the topics,
we get the distribution of all
the topics to indicate the coverage.
And similarly, the bottom one is the
estimated probability of word for a topic.
And in this case we are using exact
the same count, you can see this is
the same discounted account,
] it tells us to what extend we should
allocate this word [INAUDIBLE] but
then normalization is different.
Because in this case we are interested
in the word distribution, so
we simply normalize this
over all the words.
This is different, in contrast here we
normalize the amount all the topics.
It would be useful to take
a comparison between the two.
This give us different distributions.
And these tells us how to
improve the parameters.
And as I just explained,
in both the formula is we have a maximum
estimate based on allocated
word counts [INAUDIBLE].
Now this phenomena is actually general
phenomena in all the EM algorithms.
In the m-step, you general with
the computer expect an account of
the event based on the e-step result,
and then you just and
then count to four,
particular normalize it, typically.
So, in terms of computation
of this EM algorithm, we can
actually just keep accounting various
events and then normalize them.
And when we thinking this way,
we also have a more concise way
of presenting the EM Algorithm.
It actually helps us better
understand the formulas.
So I'm going to go over
this in some detail.
So as a algorithm we first initialize
all the unknown perimeters randomly,
all right.
So, in our case, we are interested in all
of those coverage perimeters, pi's and
awarded distributions [INAUDIBLE],
and we just randomly normalize them.
This is the initialization step and then
we will repeat until likelihood converges.
Now how do we know whether
likelihood converges?
We can do compute
likelihood at each step and
compare the current likelihood
with the previous likelihood.
If it doesn't change much and
we're going to say it stopped, right.
So, in each step we're
going to do e-step and m-step.
In the e-step we're going to do
augment the data by predicting
the hidden variables.
In this case,
the hidden variable, z sub d, w,
indicates whether the word w in
d is from a topic or background.
And if it's from a topic, which topic.
So if you look at the e-step formulas,
essentially we're actually
normalizing these counts, sorry,
these probabilities of observing
the word from each distribution.
So you can see,
basically the prediction of word
from topic zero sub j is
based on the probability of
selecting that theta sub j as a word
distribution to generate the word.
Multiply by the probability of observing
the word from that distribution.
And I said it's proportional to this
because in the implementation of
EM algorithm you can keep counter for
this quantity, and
in the end it just normalizes it.
So the normalization here
is over all the topics and
then you would get a probability.
Now, in the m-step, we do the same,
and we are going to collect these.
Allocated account for each topic.
And we split words among the topics.
And then we're going to normalize
them in different ways to obtain
the real estimate.
So for example, we can normalize among all
the topics to get the re-estimate of pi,
the coverage.
Or we can re-normalize
based on all the words.
And that would give us
a word distribution.
So it's useful to think algorithm in this
way because when implemented, you can just
use variables, but keep track of
these quantities in each case.
And then you just normalize these
variables to make them distribution.
Now I did not put the constraint for
this one.
And I intentionally leave
this as an exercise for you.
And you can see,
what's the normalizer for this one?
It's of a slightly different form but
it's essentially the same as
the one that you have
seen here in this one.
So in general in the envisioning of EM
algorithms you will see you accumulate
the counts, various counts and
then you normalize them.
So to summarize,
we introduced the PLSA model.
Which is a mixture model with k unigram
language models representing k topics.
And we also added a pre-determined
background language model to
help discover discriminative topics,
because this background language model
can help attract the common terms.
And we select the maximum estimate
that we cant discover topical
knowledge from text data.
In this case PLSA allows us to discover
two things, one is k worded distributions,
each one representing a topic and
the other is the proportion of
each topic in each document.
And such detailed characterization
of coverage of topics in documents
can enable a lot of photo analysis.
For example, we can aggregate
the documents in the particular
pan period to assess the coverage of
a particular topic in a time period.
That would allow us to generate
the temporal chains of topics.
We can also aggregate topics covered in
documents associated with a particular
author and then we can categorize
the topics written by this author, etc.
And in addition to this, we can also
cluster terms and cluster documents.
In fact,
each topic can be regarded as a cluster.
So we already have the term clusters.
In the higher probability,
the words can be regarded as
belonging to one cluster
represented by the topic.
Similarly, documents can be
clustered in the same way.
We can assign a document
to the topic cluster
that's covered most in the document.
So remember, pi's indicate to what extent
each topic is covered in the document,
we can assign the document to the topical
cluster that has the highest pi.
And in general there are many useful
applications of this technique.
[MUSIC]