[MUSIC]
This lecture is about the mixture
of unigram language models.
In this lecture we will continue
discussing probabilistic topic models.
In particular, what we introduce
a mixture of unigram language models.
This is a slide that
you have seen earlier.
Where we talked about how to
get rid of the background
words that we have on top of for
one document.
So if you want to solve the problem,
it would be useful to think about
why we end up having this problem.
Well, this obviously because these
words are very frequent in our data and
we are using a maximum
likelihood to estimate.
Then the estimate obviously would
have to assign high probability for
these words in order to
maximize the likelihood.
So, in order to get rid of them that
would mean we'd have to do something
differently here.
In particular we'll have
to say this distribution
doesn't have to explain all
the words in the tax data.
What were going to say is that,
these common words should not be
explained by this distribution.
So one natural way to solve the problem is
to think about using another distribution
to account for just these common words.
This way, the two distributions can be
mixed together to generate the text data.
And we'll let the other model which
we'll call background topic model
to generate the common words.
This way our target topic theta
here will be only generating
the common handle words that are
characterised the content of the document.
So, how does this work?
Well, it is just a small
modification of the previous setup
where we have just one distribution.
Since we now have two distributions,
we have to decide which distribution
to use when we generate the word.
Each word will still be a sample
from one of the two distributions.
Text data is still
generating the same way.
Namely, look at the generating
of the one word at each time and
eventually we generate a lot of words.
When we generate the word,
however, we're going to first decide
which of the two distributions to use.
And this is controlled by another
probability, the probability of
theta sub d and
the probability of theta sub B here.
So this is a probability of enacting
the topic word of distribution.
This is the probability of
enacting the background word
of distribution denoted by theta sub B.
On this case I just give example
where we can set both to 0.5.
So you're going to basically flip a coin,
a fair coin,
to decide what you want to use.
But in general these probabilities
don't have to be equal.
So you might bias toward using
one topic more than the other.
So now the process of generating a word
would be to first we flip a coin.
Based on these probabilities choosing
each model and if let's say the coin
shows up as head, which means we're going
to use the topic two word distribution.
Then we're going to use this word
distribution to generate a word.
Otherwise we might be
going slow this path.
And we're going to use the background
word distribution to generate a word.
So in such a case,
we have a model that has some uncertainty
associated with the use
of a word distribution.
But we can still think of this as
a model for generating text data.
And such a model is
called a mixture model.
So now let's see.
In this case, what's the probability
of observing a word w?
Now here I showed some words.
like "the" and "text".
So as in all cases,
once we setup a model we are interested
in computing the likelihood function.
The basic question is, so
what's the probability of
observing a specific word here?
Now we know that the word can be observed
from each of the two distributions, so
we have to consider two cases.
Therefore it's a sum over these two cases.
The first case is to use the topic for
the distribution to generate the word.
And in such a case then
the probably would be theta sub d,
which is the probability
of choosing the model
multiplied by the probability of actually
observing the word from that model.
Both events must happen
in order to observe.
We first must have choosing
the topic theta sub d and then,
we also have to actually have sampled
the word the from the distribution.
And similarly,
the second part accounts for
a different way of generally
the word from the background.
Now obviously the probability of
text the same is all similar, right?
So we also can see the two
ways of generating the text.
And in each case, it's a product of the
probability of choosing a particular word
is multiplied by the probability of
observing the word from that distribution.
Now whether you will see,
this is actually a general form.
So might want to make sure that you have
really understood this expression here.
And you should convince yourself that
this is indeed the probability of
obsolete text.
So to summarize what we observed here.
The probability of a word from
a mixture model is a general sum
of different ways of generating the word.
In each case,
it's a product of the probability
of selecting that component model.
Multiplied by the probability of
actually observing the data point
from that component of the model.
And this is something quite general and
you will see this occurring often later.
So the basic idea of a mixture
model is just to retrieve
thesetwo distributions
together as one model.
So I used a box to bring all
these components together.
So if you view this
whole box as one model,
it's just like any other generative model.
It would just give us
the probability of a word.
But the way that determines this
probability is quite the different from
when we have just one distribution.
And this is basically a more
complicated mixture model.
So the more complicated is more
than just one distribution.
And it's called a mixture model.
So as I just said we can treat
this as a generative model.
And it's often useful to think of
just as a likelihood function.
The illustration that
you have seen before,
which is dimmer now, is just
the illustration of this generated model.
So mathematically,
this model is nothing but
to just define the following
generative model.
Where the probability of a word is
assumed to be a sum over two cases
of generating the word.
And the form you are seeing now
is a more general form that
what you have seen in
the calculation earlier.
Well I just use the symbol
w to denote any water but
you can still see this is
basically first a sum.
Right?
And this sum is due to the fact that the
water can be generated in much more ways,
two ways in this case.
And inside a sum,
each term is a product of two terms.
And the two terms are first
the probability of selecting a component
like of D Second,
the probability of actually observing
the word from this component of the model.
So this is a very general description
of all the mixture models.
I just want to make sure
that you understand
this because this is really the basis for
understanding all kinds of on top models.
So now once we setup model.
We can write down that like
functioning as we see here.
The next question is,
how can we estimate the parameter,
or what to do with the parameters.
Given the data.
Well, in general,
we can use some of the text data
to estimate the model parameters.
And this estimation would allow us to
discover the interesting
knowledge about the text.
So you, in this case, what do we discover?
Well, these are presented
by our parameters and
we will have two kinds of parameters.
One is the two worded distributions,
that result in topics, and
the other is the coverage
of each topic in each.
The coverage of each topic.
And this is determined by
probability of C less of D and
probability of theta, so this is to one.
Now, what's interesting is
also to think about special
cases like when we send one of
them to want what would happen?
Well with the other, with the zero right?
And if you look at
the likelihood function,
it will then degenerate to the special
case of just one distribution.
Okay so you can easily verify that by
assuming one of these two is 1.0 and
the other is Zero.
So in this sense,
the mixture model is more general than
the previous model where we
have just one distribution.
It can cover that as a special case.
So to summarize, we talked about the
mixture of two Unigram Language Models and
the data we're considering
here is just One document.
And the model is a mixture
model with two components,
two unigram LM models,
specifically theta sub d,
which is intended to denote the topic of
document d, and theta sub B, which is
representing a background topic that
we can set to attract the common
words because common words would be
assigned a high probability in this model.
So the parameters can
be collectively called
Lambda which I show here you can again
think about the question about how many
parameters are we talking about exactly.
This is usually a good exercise to do
because it allows you to see the model in
depth and to have a complete understanding
of what's going on this model.
And we have mixing weights,
of course, also.
So what does a likelihood
function look like?
Well, it looks very similar
to what we had before.
So for the document,
first it's a product over all the words in
the document exactly the same as before.
The only difference is that inside here
now it's a sum instead of just one.
So you might have recalled before
we just had this one there.
But now we have this sum
because of the mixture model.
And because of the mixture model we
also have to introduce a probability of
choosing that particular
component of distribution.
And so
this is just another way of writing, and
by using a product over all the unique
words in our vocabulary instead of
having that product over all
the positions in the document.
And this form where we look at
the different and unique words is
a commutative that formed for computing
the maximum likelihood estimate later.
And the maximum likelihood estimator is,
as usual,
just to find the parameters that would
maximize the likelihood function.
And the constraints here
are of course two kinds.
One is what are probabilities in each
[INAUDIBLE] must sum to 1 the other is
the choice of each
[INAUDIBLE] must sum to 1.
[MUSIC]