[SOUND]
This
lecture is about mixture model estimation.
In this lecture we're going to continue
discussing probabilistic topic models.
In particular,
we're going to talk about how to estimate
the parameters of a mixture model.
So let's first look at our motivation for
using a mixture model.
And we hope to factor out
the background words.
From the top-words equation.
The idea is to assume that the text data
actually contained two kinds of words.
One kind is from the background here.
So, the is, we, etc.
And the other kind is from our pop board
distribution that we are interested in.
So in order to solve this problem
of factoring out background words,
we can set up our mixture model as false.
We're going to assume that we
already know the parameters of
all the values for
all the parameters in the mixture model,
except for the water distribution
of which is our target.
So this is a case of customizing
a probabilist model so
that we embedded a known variable
that we are interested in.
But we're going to simplify other things.
We're going to assume we
have knowledge above others.
And this is a powerful way
of customizing a model.
For a particular need.
Now you can imagine,
we could have assumed that we also
don't know the background words.
But in this case,
our goal is to factor out precisely
those high probability background words.
So we assume the background
model is already fixed.
And one problem here is how
can we adjust theta sub d
in order to maximize the probability
of the observed document here and
we assume all the other
perimeters are now.
Now although we designed
the model holistically.
To try to factor out
these background words.
It's unclear whether,
if we use maximum write or estimator.
We will actually end up having
a whole distribution where the Common
words like the would indeed have
smaller probabilities than before.
Now in this case it turns
out the answer is yes.
And when we set up
the probability in this way,
when we use maximum likelihood or
we will end up having a word distribution
where the use common words
would be factored out.
By the use of the background
rule of distribution.
So to understand why this is so,
it's useful to examine
the behavior of a mixture model.
So we're going to look at
a very very simple case.
In order to understand some interesting
behaviors of a mixture model.
The observed pattern here actually are
generalizable to mixture model in general.
But it's much easier to
understand this behavior
when we use A very simple case
like what we are seeing here.
So specifically in this case,
let's assume that
the probability choosing each of
the two models is exactly the same.
So we're going to flip a fair coin
to decide which model to use.
Furthermore, we're going
to assume there are.
Precisely two words, the and text.
Obviously this is a very naive
oversimplification of the actual text,
but again, it's useful to examine
the behavior in such a special case.
So we further assume that the background
model gives probability of
0.9 towards the end text 0.1.
Now, lets also assume that our data is
extremely simple the document has just
two words text and the so now lets right
down the likeable function in such a case.
First, what's the probability of text,
and what's the probably of the.
I hope by this point you'll
be able to write it down.
So the probability of text is
basically the sum over two cases,
where each case corresponds with
to each of the order distribution
and it accounts for
the two ways of generating text.
And inside each case, we have
the probability of choosing the model,
which is 0.5 multiplied by the probability
of observing text from that model.
Similarly, the,
would have a probability of the same form,
just what is different is
the exact probabilities.
So naturally our lateral function
is just a product of the two.
So It's very easy to see that,
once you understand what's
the probability of each word.
Which is also why it's so
important to understand what's exactly
the probability of observing each
word from such a mixture model.
Now, the interesting question now is,
how can we then optimize this likelihood?
Well, you will note that
there are only two variables.
They are precisely the two
probabilities of the two words.
Text [INAUDIBLE] given by theta sub d.
And this is because we have assumed
that all the other parameters are known.
So, now the question is a very
simple algebra question.
So, we have a simple expression
with two variables and
we hope to choose the values of these
two variables to maximize this function.
And the exercises that we have
seen some simple algebra problems.
Note that the two probabilities must
sum to one, so there's some constraint.
If there were no constraint of course,
we would set both probabilities to
their maximum value which would be one,
to maximize, But we can't do that
because text then the must sum to one.
We can't give both a probability of one.
So, now the question is how should
we allocate the probability and
the math between the two words.
What do you think?
Now, it would be useful to look
at this formula For a moment, and
to see what, intuitively,
what we do in order to
do set these probabilities to
maximize the value of this function.
Okay, if we look into this further,
then we see some interesting behavior
of The two component models in that
they will be collaborating to maximize
the probability of the observed data.
Which is dictated by the maximum
likelihood estimator.
But they are also competing in some way,
and in particular,
they would be competing on the words.
And they would tend to back high
probabilities on different words
to avoid this competition in some sense or
to gain advantages in this competition.
So again,
looking at this objective function and
we have a constraint on
the two probabilities.
Now, if you look at
the formula intuitively,
you might feel that you want to set the
probability of text to be somewhat larger.
And this inducing can be work supported
by mathematical fact, which is when
the sum of two variables is
a constant then the product of them
which is maximum when they are equal,
and this is a fact we know from algebra.
Now if we plug that [INAUDIBLE] It
would mean that we have to make the two
probabilities equal.
And when we make them equal and
then if we consider the constraint it
will be easy to solve this problem, and
the solution is the probability of tax
will be .09 and probability is .01.
The probability of text is now much
larger than probability of the, and
this is not the case when
have just one distribution.
And this is clearly because of
the use of the background model,
which assigned the very high probability
to the and low probability to text.
And if you look at the equation
you will see obviously
some interaction of the two
distributions here.
In particular,
you will see in order to make them equal.
And then the probability assigned
by theta sub d must be higher for
a word that has a smaller
probability given by the background.
This is obvious from
examining this equation.
Because the background part is weak for
text.
It's small.
So in order to compensate for that,
we must make the probability for
text given by theta sub D somewhat larger,
so that the two sides can be balanced.
So this is in fact a very
general behavior of this model.
And that is, if one distribution assigns a
high probability to one word than another,
then the other distribution
would tend to do the opposite.
Basically it would discourage other
distributions to do the same And
this is to balance them out so
we can account for all kinds of words.
And this also means that by using
a background model that is fixed into
assigned high probabilities
through background words.
We can indeed encourages the unknown
topical one of this to assign smaller
probabilities for such common words.
Instead put more probability
than this on the content words,
that cannot be explained well
by the background model.
Meaning that they have a very small
probability from the background motor like
text here.
[MUSIC]