So, I just showed you that empirically
the likelihood will converge,
but theoretically it can also
be proved that EM algorithm will
converge to a local maximum.
So here's just an illustration of what
happened and a detailed explanation.
This required more knowledge about that,
some of that inequalities,
that we haven't really covered yet.
So here what you see is on the X
dimension, we have a c0 value.
This is a parameter that we have.
On the y axis we see
the likelihood function.
So this curve is the original
likelihood function,
and this is the one that
we hope to maximize.
And we hope to find a c0 value
at this point to maximize this.
But in the case of Mitsumoto we can
not easily find an analytic solution
to the problem.
So, we have to resolve
the numerical errors, and
the EM algorithm is such an algorithm.
It's a Hill-Climb algorithm.
That would mean you start
with some random guess.
Let's say you start from here,
that's your starting point.
And then you try to improve
this by moving this to
another point where you can
have a higher likelihood.
So that's the ideal hill climbing.
And in the EM algorithm, the way we
achieve this is to do two things.
First, we'll fix a lower
bound of likelihood function.
So this is the lower bound.
See here.
And once we fit the lower bound,
we can then maximize the lower bound.
And of course, the reason why this works,
is because the lower bound
is much easier to optimize.
So we know our current guess is here.
And by maximizing the lower bound,
we'll move this point to the top.
To here.
Right?
And we can then map to the original
likelihood function, we find this point.
Because it's a lower bound, we are
guaranteed to improve this guess, right?
Because we improve our lower bound and
then the original likelihood
curve which is above this lower bound
will definitely be improved as well.
So we already know it's
improving the lower bound.
So we definitely improve this
original likelihood function,
which is above this lower bound.
So, in our example,
the current guess is parameter value
given by the current generation.
And then the next guess is
the re-estimated parameter values.
From this illustration you
can see the next guess
is always better than the current guess.
Unless it has reached the maximum,
where it will be stuck there.
So the two would be equal.
So, the E-step is basically
to compute this lower bound.
We don't directly just compute
this likelihood function but
we compute the length of
the variable values and
these are basically a part
of this lower bound.
This helps determine the lower bound.
The M-step on the other hand is
to maximize the lower bound.
It allows us to move
parameters to a new point.
And that's why EM algorithm is guaranteed
to converge to a local maximum.
Now, as you can imagine,
when we have many local maxima,
we also have to repeat the EM
algorithm multiple times.
In order to figure out which one
is the actual global maximum.
And this actually in general is a
difficult problem in numeral optimization.
So here for
example had we started from here,
then we gradually just
climb up to this top.
So, that's not optimal, and
we'd like to climb up all the way to here,
so the only way to climb up to this gear
is to start from somewhere here or here.
So, in the EM algorithm, we generally
would have to start from different points
or have some other way to determine
a good initial starting point.
To summarize in this lecture we
introduced the EM algorithm.
This is a general algorithm for computing
maximum maximum likelihood estimate of all
kinds of models, so
not just for our simple model.
And it's a hill-climbing algorithm, so it
can only converge to a local maximum and
it will depend on initial points.
The general idea is that we will have
two steps to improve the estimate of.
In the E-step we roughly [INAUDIBLE]
how many there are by predicting values
of useful hidden variables that we
would use to simplify the estimation.
In our case, this is the distribution
that has been used to generate the word.
In the M-step then we would exploit
such augmented data which would make
it easier to estimate the distribution,
to improve the estimate of parameters.
Here improve is guaranteed in
terms of the likelihood function.
Note that it's not necessary that we
will have a stable convergence of
parameter value even though the likelihood
function is ensured to increase.
There are some properties that have to
be satisfied in order for the parameters
also to convert into some stable value.
Now here data augmentation
is done probabilistically.
That means,
we're not going to just say exactly
what's the value of a hidden variable.
But we're going to have a probability
distribution over the possible values of
these hidden variables.
So this causes a split of counts
of events probabilistically.
And in our case we'll split the word
counts between the two distributions.
[MUSIC]