[SOUND]
So
this is indeed a general idea of
the Expectation-Maximization, or EM,
Algorithm.
So in all the EM algorithms we
introduce a hidden variable
to help us solve the problem more easily.
In our case the hidden variable
is a binary variable for
each occurrence of a word.
And this binary variable would
indicate whether the word has
been generated from 0 sub d or 0 sub p.
And here we show some possible
values of these variables.
For example, for the it's from background,
the z value is one.
And text on the other hand.
Is from the topic then it's zero for
z, etc.
Now, of course, we don't observe these z
values, we just imagine they're all such.
Values of z attaching to other words.
And that's why we call
these hidden variables.
Now, the idea that we
talked about before for
predicting the word distribution that
has been used when we generate the word
is it a predictor,
the value of this hidden variable?
And, so, the EM algorithm then,
would work as follows.
First, we'll initialize all
the parameters with random values.
In our case,
the parameters are mainly the probability.
of a word, given by theta sub d.
So this is an initial addition stage.
These initialized values would allow
us to use base roll to take a guess
of these z values, so
we'd guess these values.
We can't say for sure whether
textt is from background or not.
But we can have our guess.
This is given by this formula.
It's called an E-step.
And so the algorithm would then try to
use the E-step to guess these z values.
After that, it would then invoke
another that's called M-step.
In this step we simply take advantage
of the inferred z values and
then just group words that are in
the same distribution like these
from that ground including this as well.
We can then normalize the count
to estimate the probabilities or
to revise our estimate of the parameters.
So let me also illustrate
that we can group the words
that are believed to have
come from zero sub d, and
that's text, mining algorithm,
for example, and clustering.
And we group them together to help us
re-estimate the parameters
that we're interested in.
So these will help us
estimate these parameters.
Note that before we just set
these parameter values randomly.
But with this guess, we will have
somewhat improved estimate of this.
Of course, we don't know exactly
whether it's zero or one.
So we're not going to really
do the split in a hard way.
But rather we're going to
do a softer split.
And this is what happened here.
So we're going to adjust the count by
the probability that would believe
this word has been generated
by using the theta sub d.
And you can see this,
where does this come from?
Well, this has come from here, right?
From the E-step.
So the EM Algorithm would
iteratively improve uur initial
estimate of parameters by using
E-step first and then M-step.
The E-step is to augment the data
with additional information, like z.
And the M-step is to take advantage
of the additional information
to separate the data.
To split the data accounts and
then collect the right data accounts to
re-estimate our parameter.
And then once we have a new generation of
parameter, we're going to repeat this.
We are going the E-step again.
To improve our estimate
of the hidden variables.
And then that would lead to another
generation of re-estimated parameters.
For the word distribution
that we are interested in.
Okay, so, as I said,
the bridge between the two
is really the variable z, hidden variable,
which indicates how likely
this water is from the top water
distribution, theta sub p.
So, this slide has a lot of content and
you may need to.
Pause the reader to digest it.
But this basically captures
the essence of EM Algorithm.
Start with initial values that
are often random themself.
And then we invoke E-step followed
by M-step to get an improved
setting of parameters.
And then we repeated this, so
this a Hill-Climbing algorithm
that would gradually improve
the estimate of parameters.
As I will explain later
there is some guarantee for
reaching a local maximum of
the log-likelihood function.
So lets take a look at the computation for
a specific case, so
these formulas are the EM.
Formulas that you see before, and
you can also see there are superscripts,
here, like here, n,
to indicate the generation of parameters.
Like here for example we have n plus one.
That means we have improved.
From here to here we have an improvement.
So in this setting we have assumed the two
numerals have equal probabilities and
the background model is null.
So what are the relevance
of the statistics?
Well these are the word counts.
So assume we have just four words,
and their counts are like this.
And this is our background model that
assigns high probabilities to common
words like the.
And in the first iteration,
you can picture what will happen.
Well first we initialize all the values.
So here, this probability that we're
interested in is normalized into a uniform
distribution of all the words.
And then the E-step would give us a guess
of the distribution that has been used.
That will generate each word.
We can see we have different
probabilities for different words.
Why?
Well, that's because these words have
different probabilities in the background.
So even though the two
distributions are equally likely.
And then our initial audition say uniform
distribution because of the difference
in the background of the distribution,
we have different guess the probability.
So these words are believed to
be more likely from the topic.
These on the other hand are less likely.
Probably from background.
So once we have these z values,
we know in the M-step these probabilities
will be used to adjust the counts.
So four must be multiplied by this 0.33
in order to get the allocated
accounts toward the topic.
And this is done by this multiplication.
Note that if our guess says this
is 100% If this is one point zero,
then we just get the full count
of this word for this topic.
In general it's not going
to be one point zero.
So we're just going to get some percentage
of this counts toward this topic.
Then we simply normalize these counts
to have a new generation
of parameters estimate.
So you can see, compare this with
the older one, which is here.
So compare this with this one and
we'll see the probability is different.
Not only that, we also see some
words that are believed to have come from
the topic will have a higher probability.
Like this one, text.
And of course, this new generation of
parameters would allow us to further
adjust the inferred latent variable or
hidden variable values.
So we have a new generation of values,
because of the E-step based on
the new generation of parameters.
And these new inferred values
of Zs will give us then
another generation of the estimate
of probabilities of the word.
And so on and so forth so this is what
would actually happen when we compute
these probabilities
using the EM Algorithm.
As you can see in the last row
where we show the log-likelihood,
and the likelihood is increasing
as we do the iteration.
And note that these log-likelihood is
negative because the probability is
between 0 and 1 when you take a logarithm,
it becomes a negative value.
Now what's also interesting is,
you'll note the last column.
And these are the inverted word split.
And these are the probabilities
that a word is believed to
have come from one distribution, in this
case the topical distribution, all right.
And you might wonder whether
this would be also useful.
Because our main goal is to
estimate these word distributions.
So this is our primary goal.
We hope to have a more discriminative
order of distribution.
But the last column is also bi-product.
This also can actually be very useful.
You can think about that.
We want to use, is to for
example is to estimate to what extent this
document has covered background words.
And this, when we add this up or
take the average we will kind of know to
what extent it has covered background
versus content was that are not
explained well by the background.
[MUSIC]