[SOUND] So
now let's talk about the exchanging of
PLSA to of LDA and to motivate that,
we need to talk about some
deficiencies of PLSA.
First, it's not really a generative model
because we can compute the probability of
a new document.
You can see why, and that's because the
pis are needed to generate the document,
but the pis are tied to the document
that we have in the training data.
So we can't compute the pis for
future document.
And there's some heuristic workaround,
though.
Secondly, it has many parameters, and I've
asked you to compute how many parameters
exactly there are in PLSA, and
you will see there are many parameters.
That means that model is very complex.
And this also means that there
are many local maxima and
it's prone to overfitting.
And that means it's very hard to
also find a good local maximum.
And that we are representing
global maximum.
And in terms of explaining future data,
we might find that
it will overfit the training data
because of the complexity of the model.
The model is so flexible to fit precisely
what the training data looks like.
And then it doesn't allow us to generalize
the model for using other data.
This however is not a necessary problem
for text mining because here we're often
only interested in hitting
the training documents that we have.
We are not always interested in modern
future data, but in other cases,
or if we would care about the generality,
we would worry about this overfitting.
So LDA is proposing to improve that,
and basically to make
PLSA a generative model by imposing
a Dirichlet prior on the model parameters.
Dirichlet is just a special distribution
that we can use to specify product.
So in this sense, LDA is just
a Bayesian version of PLSA, and
the parameters are now
much more regularized.
You will see there are many
few parameters and
you can achieve the same goal as PLSA for
text mining.
It means it can compute the top coverage
and topic word distributions as in PLSA.
However, there's no.
Why are the parameters for
PLSA here are much fewer,
there are fewer parameters and
in order to compute a topic coverage and
word distributions,
we again face a problem
of influence of these variables because
they are not parameters of the model.
So the influence part again
face the local maximum problem.
So essentially they are doing something
very similar, but theoretically,
LDA is a more elegant way of looking
at the top and bottom problem.
So let's see how we can
generalize the PLSA to LDA or
a standard PLSA to have LDA.
Now a full treatment of LDA is
beyond the scope of this course and
we just don't have time to go in
depth on that talking about that.
But here, I just want to give you
a brief idea about what's extending and
what it enables, all right.
So this is the picture of LDA.
Now, I remove the background
of model just for simplicity.
Now, in this model, all these
parameters are free to change and
we do not impose any prior.
So these word distributions are now
represented as theta vectors.
So these are word distributions, so here.
And the other set of parameters are pis.
And we would present it as a vector also.
And this is more convenient
to introduce LDA.
And we have one vector for each document.
And in this case, in theta,
we have one vector for each topic.
Now, the difference between LDA and
PLSA is that in LDA, we're not going
to allow them to free the chain.
Instead, we're going to force them to
be drawn from another distribution.
So more specifically,
they will be drawn from two Dirichlet
distributions respectively, but
the Dirichlet distribution is
a distribution over vectors.
So it gives us a probability of
four particular choice of a vector.
Take, for example, pis, right.
So this Dirichlet distribution tells
us which vectors of pi is more likely.
And this distribution in itself is
controlled by another vector of parameters
of alphas.
Depending on the alphas, we can
characterize the distribution in different
ways but with full certain choices of
pis to be more likely than others.
For example,
you might favor the choice of a relatively
uniform distribution of all the topics.
Or you might favor generating
a skewed coverage of topics,
and this is controlled by alpha.
And similarly here, the topic or
word distributions are drawn
from another Dirichlet
distribution with beta parameters.
And note that here,
alpha has k parameters,
corresponding to our inference on
the k values of pis for our document.
Whereas here,
beta has n values corresponding to
controlling the m words in our vocabulary.
Now once we impose this price, then
the generation process will be different.
And we start with joined pis from
the Dirichlet distribution and
this pi will tell us these probabilities.
And then, we're going to use the pi
to further choose which topic
to use, and this is of course
very similar to the PLSA model.
And similar here, we're not going
to have these distributions free.
Instead, we're going to draw one
from the Dirichlet distribution.
And then from this,
then we're going to further sample a word.
And the rest is very similar to the.
The likelihood function now
is more complicated for LDA.
But there's a close connection between the
likelihood function of LDA and the PLSA.
So I'm going to illustrate
the difference here.
So in the top,
you see PLSA likelihood function
that you have already seen before.
It's copied from previous slide.
Only that I dropped the background for
simplicity.
So in the LDA formulas you
see very similar things.
You see the first equation
is essentially the same.
And this is the probability of generating
a word from multiple word distributions.
And this formula is a sum of all
the possibilities of generating a word.
Inside a sum is a product of
the probability of choosing a topic
multiplied by the probability of
observing the word from that topic.
So this is a very important formula,
as I've stressed multiple times.
And this is actually the core
assumption in all the topic models.
And you might see other topic models
that are extensions of LDA or PLSA.
And they all rely on this.
So it's very important to understand this.
And this gives us a probability of
getting a word from a mixture model.
Now, next in the probability of
a document, we see there is a PLSA
component in the LDA formula, but the LDA
formula will add a sum integral here.
And that's to account for
the fact that the pis are not fixed.
So they are drawn from the original
distribution, and that's shown here.
That's why we have to take an integral,
to consider all the possible pis that we
could possibly draw from
this Dirichlet distribution.
And similarly in the likelihood for
the whole collection,
we also see further components added,
another integral here.
Right?
So basically in the area we're just
adding this integrals to account for
the uncertainties and we added of course
the Dirichlet distributions to cover
the choice of this parameters,
pis, and theta.
So this is a likelihood function for LDA.
Now, next to this, let's talk about the
parameter as estimation and inferences.
Now the parameters can be now estimated
using exactly the same approach
maximum likelihood estimate for LDA.
Now you might think about how many
parameters are there in LDA versus PLSA.
You'll see there're a fewer parameters
in LDA because in this case the only
parameters are alphas and the betas.
So we can use the maximum likelihood
estimator to compute that.
Of course, it's more complicated because
the form of likelihood function is
more complicated.
But what's also important
is notice that now these
parameters that we are interested
in name and topics, and
the coverage are no
longer parameters in LDA.
In this case we have to
use basic inference or
posterior inference to compute them based
on the parameters of alpha and the beta.
Unfortunately, this
computation is intractable.
So we generally have to resort
to approximate inference.
And there are many methods available for
that and I'm sure you will
see them when you use different tool kits
for LDA, or when you read papers about
these different extensions of LDA.
Now here we, of course, can't give
in-depth instruction to that, but
just know that they are computed based in
inference by using
the parameters alphas and betas.
But our math [INAUDIBLE],
actually, in the end,
in some of our math list,
it's very similar to PLSA.
And, especially when we use
algorithm called class assembly,
then the algorithm looks very
similar to the Algorithm.
So in the end,
they are doing something very similar.
So to summarize our discussion
of properties of topic models,
these models provide
a general principle or
way of mining and analyzing topics
in text with many applications.
The best basic task setup is
to take test data as input and
we're going to output the k topics.
Each topic is characterized
by word distribution.
And we're going to also output proportions
of these topics covered in each document.
And PLSA is the basic topic model, and
in fact the most basic of the topic model.
And this is often adequate for
most applications.
That's why we spend a lot of
time to explain PLSA in detail.
Now LDA improves over
PLSA by imposing priors.
This has led to theoretically
more appealing models.
However, in practice, LDA and
PLSA tend to give similar performance, so
in practice PLSA and LDA would work
equally well for most of the tasks.
Now here are some suggested readings if
you want to know more about the topic.
First is a nice review of
probabilistic topic models.
The second has a discussion about how
to automatically label a topic model.
Now I've shown you some distributions and
they intuitively suggest a topic.
But what exactly is a topic?
Can we use phrases to label the topic?
To make it the more easy to understand and
this paper is about the techniques for
doing that.
The third one is empirical comparison
of LDA and the PLSA for various tasks.
The conclusion is that they
tend to perform similarly.
[MUSIC]