This lecture is about Probabilistic Topic
Models for topic mining and analysis.
In this lecture,
we're going to continue talking
about the topic mining and analysis.
We're going to introduce
probabilistic topic models.
So this is a slide that
you have seen earlier,
where we discussed the problems
with using a term as a topic.
So, to solve these problems
intuitively we need to use
more words to describe the topic.
And this will address the problem
of lack of expressive power.
When we have more words that we
can use to describe the topic,
that we can describe complicated topics.
To address the second problem we
need to introduce weights on words.
This is what allows you to distinguish
subtle differences in topics, and
to introduce semantically
related words in a fuzzy manner.
Finally, to solve the problem of
word ambiguity, we need to split
ambiguous word, so
that we can disambiguate its topic.
It turns out that all these can be done
by using a probabilistic topic model.
And that's why we're going to spend a lot
of lectures to talk about this topic.
So the basic idea here is that,
improve the replantation of
topic as one distribution.
So what you see now is
the older replantation.
Where we replanted each topic, it was just
one word, or one term, or one phrase.
But now we're going to use a word
distribution to describe the topic.
So here you see that for sports.
We're going to use
the word distribution over
theoretical speaking all
the words in our vocabulary.
So for example, the high
probability words here are sports,
game, basketball,
football, play, star, etc.
These are sports related terms.
And of course it would also give
a non-zero probability to some other word
like Trouble which might be
related to sports in general,
not so much related to topic.
In general we can imagine a non
zero probability for all the words.
And some words that are not read and
would have very, very small probabilities.
And these probabilities will sum to one.
So that it forms a distribution
of all the words.
Now intuitively, this distribution
represents a topic in that if we assemble
words from the distribution, we tended
to see words that are ready to dispose.
You can also see, as a very special case,
if the probability of the mass
is concentrated in entirely on
just one word, it's sports.
And this basically degenerates
to the symbol foundation
of a topic was just one word.
But as a distribution,
this topic of representation can,
in general,
involve many words to describe a topic and
can model several differences
in semantics of a topic.
Similarly we can model Travel and Science
with their respective distributions.
In the distribution for Travel we see top
words like attraction, trip, flight etc.
Whereas in Science we see scientist,
spaceship, telescope, or
genomics, and, you know,
science related terms.
Now that doesn't mean sports related terms
will necessarily have zero
probabilities for science.
In general we can imagine all of these
words we have now zero probabilities.
It's just that for a particular
topic in some words we have very,
very small probabilities.
Now you can also see there are some
words that are shared by these topics.
When I say shared it just means even
with some probability threshold,
you can still see one word
occurring much more topics.
In this case I mark them in black.
So you can see travel, for example,
occurred in all the three topics here, but
with different probabilities.
It has the highest probability for
the Travel topic, 0.05.
But with much smaller probabilities for
Sports and Science, which makes sense.
And similarly, you can see a Star
also occurred in Sports and
Science with reasonably
high probabilities.
Because they might be actually
related to the two topics.
So with this replantation it addresses the
three problems that I mentioned earlier.
First, it now uses multiple
words to describe a topic.
So it allows us to describe
a fairly complicated topics.
Second, it assigns weights to terms.
So now we can model several
differences of semantics.
And you can bring in related
words together to model a topic.
Third, because we have probabilities for
the same word in different topics,
we can disintegrate the sense of word.
In the text to decode
it's underlying topic,
to address all these three problems with
this new way of representing a topic.
So now of course our problem definition
has been refined just slightly.
The slight is very similar to what
you've seen before except we have
added refinement for what our topic is.
Now each topic is word distribution,
and for each word distribution we know
that all the probabilities should sum to
one with all the words in the vocabulary.
So you see a constraint here.
And we still have another constraint
on the topic coverage, namely pis.
So all the Pi sub ij's must sum to one for
the same document.
So how do we solve this problem?
Well, let's look at this problem
as a computation problem.
So we clearly specify it's input and
output and
illustrate it here on this side.
Input of course is our text data.
C is our collection but we also generally
assume we know the number of topics, k.
Or we hypothesize a number and
then try to bind k topics,
even though we don't know the exact
topics that exist in the collection.
And V is the vocabulary that has
a set of words that determines what
units would be treated as
the basic units for analysis.
In most cases we'll use words
as the basis for analysis.
And that means each word is a unique.
Now the output would consist of as first
a set of topics represented by theta I's.
Each theta I is a word distribution.
And we also want to know the coverage
of topics in each document.
So that's.
That the same pi ijs
that we have seen before.
So given a set of text data we would
like compute all these distributions and
all these coverages as you
have seen on this slide.
Now of course there may be many
different ways of solving this problem.
In theory, you can write the [INAUDIBLE]
program to solve this problem,
but here we're going to introduce
a general way of solving this
problem called a generative model.
And this is, in fact,
a very general idea and
it's a principle way of using statistical
modeling to solve text mining problems.
And here I dimmed the picture
that you have seen before
in order to show the generation process.
So the idea of this approach is actually
to first design a model for our data.
So we design a probabilistic model
to model how the data are generated.
Of course,
this is based on our assumption.
The actual data aren't
necessarily generating this way.
So that gave us a probability
distribution of the data
that you are seeing on this slide.
Given a particular model and
parameters that are denoted by lambda.
So this template of actually consists of
all the parameters that
we're interested in.
And these parameters in general
will control the behavior of
the probability risk model.
Meaning that if you set these
parameters with different values and
it will give some data points
higher probabilities than others.
Now in this case of course,
for our text mining problem or
more precisely topic mining problem
we have the following plans.
First of all we have theta i's which
is a word distribution snd then we have
a set of pis for each document.
And since we have n documents, so we have
n sets of pis, and each set the pi up.
The pi values will sum to one.
So this is to say that we
first would pretend we already
have these word distributions and
the coverage numbers.
And then we can see how we can generate
data by using such distributions.
So how do we model the data in this way?
And we assume that the data
are actual symbols
drawn from such a model that
depends on these parameters.
Now one interesting question here is to
think about how many
parameters are there in total?
Now obviously we can already see
n multiplied by K parameters.
For pi's.
We also see k theta i's.
But each theta i is actually a set
of probability values, right?
It's a distribution of words.
So I leave this as an exercise for
you to figure out exactly how
many parameters there are here.
Now once we set up the model then
we can fit the model to our data.
Meaning that we can
estimate the parameters or
infer the parameters based on the data.
In other words we would like to
adjust these parameter values.
Until we give our data set
the maximum probability.
I just said,
depending on the parameter values,
some data points will have higher
probabilities than others.
What we're interested in, here,
is what parameter values will give
our data set the highest probability?
So I also illustrate the problem
with a picture that you see here.
On the X axis I just illustrate lambda,
the parameters,
as a one dimensional variable.
It's oversimplification, obviously,
but it suffices to show the idea.
And the Y axis shows the probability
of the data, observe.
This probability obviously depends
on this setting of lambda.
So that's why it varies as you
change the value of lambda.
What we're interested here
is to find the lambda star.
That would maximize the probability
of the observed data.
So this would be, then,
our estimate of the parameters.
And these parameters,
note that are precisely what we
hoped to discover from text data.
So we'd treat these parameters
as actually the outcome or
the output of the data mining algorithm.
So this is the general idea of using
a generative model for text mining.
First, we design a model with
some parameter values to fit
the data as well as we can.
After we have fit the data,
we will recover some parameter value.
We will use the specific
parameter value And
those would be the output
of the algorithm.
And we'll treat those as actually
the discovered knowledge from text data.
By varying the model of course we
can discover different knowledge.
So to summarize, we introduced
a new way of representing topic,
namely representing as word distribution
and this has the advantage of using
multiple words to describe a complicated
topic.It also allow us to assign
weights on words so we have more than
several variations of semantics.
We talked about the task of topic mining,
and answers.
When we define a topic as distribution.
So the importer is a clashing of text
articles and a number of topics and
a vocabulary set and
the output is a set of topics.
Each is a word distribution and
also the coverage of all
the topics in each document.
And these are formally represented
by theta i's and pi i's.
And we have two constraints here for
these parameters.
The first is the constraints
on the worded distributions.
In each worded distribution
the probability of all the words
must sum to 1,
all the words in the vocabulary.
The second constraint is on
the topic coverage in each document.
A document is not allowed to recover
a topic outside of the set of topics that
we are discovering.
So, the coverage of each of these k
topics would sum to one for a document.
We also introduce a general idea of using
a generative model for text mining.
And the idea here is, first we're design
a model to model the generation of data.
We simply assume that they
are generative in this way.
And inside the model we embed some
parameters that we're interested in
denoted by lambda.
And then we can infer the most
likely parameter values lambda star,
given a particular data set.
And we can then take the lambda star as
knowledge discovered from the text for
our problem.
And we can adjust
the design of the model and
the parameters to discover various
kinds of knowledge from text.
As you will see later
in the other lectures.
[MUSIC]