[SOUND] This lecture is
a continued discussion
of evaluation of text categorization.
Earlier we have introduced measures that
can be used with computer provision and
recall.
For each category and each document
now in this lecture we're going to
further examine how to combine the
performance of the different categories of
different documents how to aggregate them,
how do we take average?
You see on the title here I indicated
it's called a macro average and
this is in contrast to micro average
that we'll talk more about later.
So, again, for each category we're going
to compute the precision require an f1 so
for example category c1 we have
precision p1, recall r1 and F value f1.
And similarly we can do that for category
2 and and all the other categories.
Now once we compute that and
we can aggregate them, so for
example we can aggregate
all the precision values.
For all the categories, for
computing overall precision.
And this is often very useful to summarize
what we have seen in the whole data set.
And aggregation can be
done many different ways.
Again as I said, in a case when you
need to aggregate different values,
it's always good to think about what's
the best way of doing the aggregation.
For example, we can consider arithmetic
mean, which is very commonly used, or
you can use geometric mean,
which would have different behavior.
Depending on the way you aggregate,
you might have got different conclusions.
in terms of which method works better,
so it's important to consider these
differences and choosing the right one or
a more suitable one for your task.
So the difference fore example
between arithmetically and
geometrically is that the arithmetically
would be dominated by high
values whereas geometrically would
be more affected by low values.
Base and so whether you are want
to emphasis low values or
high values would be a question
relate with all you And
similar we can do that for
recal and F score.
So that's how we can generate the overall
precision, recall and F score.
Now we can do the same for aggregation
of other all the document All right.
So it's exactly the same situation for
each document on our computer.
Precision, recall, and F.
And then after we have completed
the computation for all these documents,
we're going to aggregate them to generate
the overall precision, overall recall, and
overall F score.
These are, again, examining
the results from different angles.
Which one's more useful will
depend on your application.
In general, it's beneficial to look at
the results from all these perspectives.
And especially if you compare different
methods in different dimensions,
it might reveal which method
Is better in which measure or
in what situations and
this provides insightful.
Understanding the strands of a method or
a weakness and
this provides further insight for
improving them.
So as I mentioned,
there is also micro-average
in contrast to the macro average
that we talked about earlier.
In this case, what we do is you
pool together all the decisions,
and then compute the precision and recall.
So we can compute the overall
precision and recall by just counting
how many cases are in true positive,
how many cases in false positive,
etc, it's computing the values
in the contingency table,
and then we can compute the precision and
recall just once.
In contrast, in macro-averaging, we're
going to do that for each category first.
And then aggregate over these categories
or we do that for each document and
then aggregate all the documents but
here we pooled them together.
Now this would be very similar to
the classification accuracy that we
used earlier, and
one problem here of course to treat all
the instances, all the decisions equally.
And this may not be desirable.
But it may be a property for
some applications,
especially if we associate the, for
example, the cost for each combination.
Then we can actually compute for example,
weighted classification accuracy.
Where you associate the different cost or
utility for each specific decision,
so there could be variations of these
methods that would be more useful.
But in general macro average tends to
be more information than micro average,
just because it might reflect the need for
understanding performance
on each category or performance on each
document which are needed in applications.
But macro averaging and micro averaging,
they are both very common,
and you might see both reported in
research papers on Categorization.
Also sometimes categorization
results might actually
be evaluated from ranking prospective.
And this is because categorization
results are sometimes or
often indeed passed it to a human for
various purposes.
For example, it might be passed
to humans for further editing.
For example, news articles can be tempted
to be categorized by using a system and
then human editors would
then correct them.
And all the email messages might be
throughout to the right person for
handling in the help desk.
And in such a case the categorizations
will help prioritizing
the task for
particular customer service person.
So, in this case the results
have to be prioritized
and if the system can't give a score
to the categorization decision for
confidence then we can use the scores
to rank these decisions and
then evaluate the results as a rank list,
just as in a search engine.
Evaluation where you rank
the documents in responsible query.
So for example a discovery of
spam emails can be evaluated
based on ranking emails for
the spam category.
And this is useful if you want people
to to verify whether this is really
spam, right?
The person would then take
the rank To check one by one and
then verify whether this is indeed a spam.
So to reflect the utility for
humans in such a task, it's
better to evaluate Ranking Chris and this
is basically similar to a search again.
And in such a case often
the problem can be
better formulated as a ranking problem
instead of a categorization problem.
So for example, ranking documents in
a search engine can also be framed
as a binary categorization problem,
distinguish the relevant documents that
are useful to users from those that
are not useful, but typically we
frame this as a ranking problem,
and we evaluate it as a rank list.
That's because people tend
to examine the results so
ranking evaluation more reflects
utility from user's perspective.
So to summarize categorization evaluation,
first evaluation is always very
important for all these tasks.
So get it right.
If you don't get it right,
you might get misleading results.
And you might be misled to believe
one method is better than the other,
which is in fact not true.
So it's very important to get it right.
Measures must also reflect
the intended use of the results for
a particular application.
For example, in spam filtering and
news categorization the results
are used in maybe different ways.
So then we would need to
consider the difference and
design measures appropriately.
We generally need to consider how will the
results be further processed by the user
and think from a user's perspective.
What quality is important?
What aspect of quality is important?
Sometimes there are trade offs between
multiple aspects like precision and
recall and so we need to know for this
application is high recall more important,
or high precision is more important.
Ideally we associate the different cost
with each different decision arrow.
And this of course has to be designed
in an application specific way.
Some commonly used measures for relative
comparison methods are the following.
Classification accuracy, it's very
commonly used for especially balance.
[INAUDIBLE] preceding [INAUDIBLE]
Scores are common and
report characterizing performances,
given angles and give us some
[INAUDIBLE] like a [INAUDIBLE] Per
document basis [INAUDIBLE] And then
take a average of all of them, different
ways micro versus macro [INAUDIBLE].
In general, you want to look at the
results from multiple perspectives and for
particular applications some perspectives
would be more important than others but
diagnoses and
analysis of categorization methods.
It's generally useful to look at
as many perspectives as possible
to see subtle differences between methods
or tow see where a method might be weak
from which you can obtain sight for
improving a method.
Finally sometimes ranking
may be more appropriate so
be careful sometimes categorization has
got may be better frame as a ranking tasks
and there're machine running methods for
optimizing ranking measures as well.
So here are two suggested readings.
One is some chapters of this book where
you can find more discussion about
evaluation measures.
The second is a paper about
comparison of different approaches to
text categorization and
it also has an excellent discussion of
how to evaluate textual categorization.
[MUSIC]