This lecture is about the methods for
text categorization.
So in this lecture we're going to discuss
how to do text for categorization.
First, there're many methods for
text categorization.
In such a method the idea is
to determine the category
based on some rules that
we design carefully
to reflect the domain knowledge about
the category prediction problem.
So for example, if you want to do topic
categorization for news articles you
can say well, if the news article mentions
word like a game and sports three times.
That we're going to say it's about sports
things like that and this would allow us
to deterministically decide which category
a document that should be put into.
Now such a strategy would work well
if the following conditions hold.
First the categories must be very well
defined and this allows the person to
clearly decide the category
based on some clear rules.
A certainly the categories as
half to be easy to distinguished at
the based on a surface features in text.
So that means some official
features like keywords or
punctuations or whatever,
you can easily identify in text to data.
For example, if there is some
special vocabulary that is known
to only occur in a particular category.
And that would be most effective because
we can easily use such a vocabulary or
padding of such a vocabulary
to recognize this category.
Now we also should have
sufficient knowledge for
designing these words, and so if that's
the case then such a can be effective.
And so it does have a in some domains and
sometimes.
However, in general, there are several
problems with this approach.
First off, because it's label intensive
it requires a lot of manual work.
Obviously, we can't do this for
all kinds of categorization problems.
We have to do it from scratch for
a different problem.
problem because given the rules,
what they need.
So it doesn't scale up well.
Secondly, it cannot handle
uncertainty in rules,
often the rules Aren't 100% reliable.
Take for example looking at
occurrences of words in texts and
trying to decide the topic.
It's actually very hard to
have 100% correct rule.
So for example you can say well,
if it has game, sports,
basketball Then for
sure it's about sports.
But one can also imagine some types of
articles that mention these cures, but
may not be exactly about sports or
only marginally touching sports.
The main topic could be another topic,
a different topic than sports.
So that's one disadvantage
of this approach.
And then finally,
the rules maybe inconsistent and
this would lead to robustness.
More specifically, and sometimes, the
results of categorization may be different
that depending on which
rule to be applied.
So as in that case that you
are facing uncertainty.
And you will also have to decide
an order of applying the rules,
or combination of results
that are contradictory.
So all these are problems
with this approach.
And it turns out that both
problems can be solved or
alleviated by using machine learning.
So these machine learning
methods are more automatic.
But, I still put automatic
in quotation marks because
they are not really completely automatic
cause it still require many work.
More specifically we have to use
a human experts to help in two ways.
First the human experts must annotate
data cells was category labels.
And would tell the computer which
documents should receive which categories.
And this is called training data.
And then secondly, the human experts also
need to provide a set of features to
represent each text object.
That can potentially provide
a clue about the category.
So, we need to provide some basic
features for the computers to look into.
In the case of tax a natural
choice would be the words.
So, using each has a feature is
a very common choice to start with,
but of course there are other
sophisticated features like phrases or
even parts of ancients tags or
even syntax to the structures.
So once human experts can provide this
then we can use machine running to learn
soft rules for
categorization from the training data.
So, soft rules just means,
we're going to get decided which category
we should be assigned for a document,
but it's not going to be use using
a rule that is deterministic.
So we might use something similar
to saying that if it matches games,
sports many times,
it's likely to be sports.
But, we're not going to say exactly for
sure but instead,
we're going to use probabilities or
weights.
So that we can combine
much more evidences.
So, the learning process,
basically is going to figure out which
features are most useful for
separating different categories.
And it's going to also figure out how to
optimally combine features to minimize
errors of the categorization
of the training data.
So the training data,
as you can see here, is very important.
It's the basis for learning.
And then, the trained classifier can be
applied to a new text object to predict
the most likely category.
And that's to simulate
the prediction of what
human Would assign to this text object.
If the human were to make a judgement.
So when we use machine learning for
text categorization we can also
talk about the problem in the general
setting of supervisement.
So the set up is to learn
a classifier to map a value of X.
Into a map of Y so
here X is all the text objects and
Y is all the categories,
a set of categories.
So the class phi will take
any value in x as input and
would generate a value in y as output.
We hope that output y with
this right category for x.
And here correct, of course,
is judged based on the training data.
So that's a general goal in machine
learning problems or supervised learning
problems where you are given some examples
of input and output for a function.
And then the computer's
going to figure out the,
how the function behaves
like based on this examples.
And then try to be able
to compute the values for
future x's that when we have not seen.
So in general all methods
would rely on discriminative
features of text objects to
distinguish different categories.
So that's why these features
are very important and
they have to be provided by humans.
And they will also combine multiple
features in a weight map with weights
to be optimized to minimize
errors on the training data.
So after the learning processes
optimization problem.
An objective function is often tied
into the errors on the training data.
Different methods tend to vary in
their ways of measuring the errors on
the training data.
They might optimize
a different objective function,
which is often also called a loss
function or cost function.
They also tend to vary in their
ways of combining the features.
So a linear combination for
example is simple, is often used.
But they are not as powerful
as nonlinear combinations.
But nonlinear models
might be more complex for
training, so there are tradeoffs as well.
But that would lead to
different variations of
many variations of these learning methods.
So in general we can distinguish two
kinds of classifiers at a high level.
One is called generative classifiers.
The other is called
discriminative classifiers.
The generative classifiers try to learn
what the data looks like in each category.
So it attempts to model the joint
distribution of the data and
the label x and y and
this can then be factored out to
a product of why
the distribution of labels.
And the joint probability
of sorry the conditional
probability of X given Y, so it's Y.
So we first model
the distribution of labels and
then we model how the data is
generate a particular label here.
And once we can estimate these models,
then we can compute this conditional
probability of label given data
based on the probability
of data given label.
And the label distribution
here by using the Bayes Rule.
Now this is the most important thing,
because this conditional probability
of the label can then be used directly
to decide which label is most likely.
So in such approaches objective
function is actually likelihood.
And so,
we model how the data are generated.
So it only indirectly
captures the training errors.
But if we can model the data
in each category accurately,
then we can also classify accurately.
One example is Naïve Bayes classifier,
in this case.
The other kind of approaches
are called discriminative classifies,
and these classifies try to learn
what features separate categories.
So they direct or attack the problem of
categorization for separation of classes.
So sorry for the problem.
So, these discriminative
classifiers attempt to model
the conditional probability of the label
given the data point directly.
So, the objective function tends
to directly measure the errors of
categorization on the training data.
Some examples include
a logistical regression,
support vector machines,
and k-nearest neighbors.
We will cover some of these classifiers
in detail in the next few lectures.
[MUSIC]