[SOUND]
This lecture is about text categorization.
In this lecture, we're going to
talk about text categorization.
This is a very important technique for
text data mining and analytics.
It is relevant to discovery
of various different kinds of
knowledge as shown here.
First, it's related to topic mining and
analysis.
And, that's because it has to do with
analyzing text to data based
on some predefined topics.
Secondly, it's also related to
opinion mining and sentiment analysis,
which has to do with discovery knowledge
about the observer, the human sensor.
Because we can categorize the authors,
for example,
based on the content of the articles
that they have written, right?
We can, in general,
categorize the observer
based on the content that they produce.
Finally, it's also related
to text-based prediction.
Because, we can often use text
categorization techniques to predict some
variables in the real world that
are only remotely related to text data.
And so, this is a very important
technique for text to data mining.
This is the overall plan for
covering the topic.
First, we're going to talk about
what is text categorization and
why we're interested in
doing that in this lecture?
And now, we're going to talk about
how to do text categorization for
how to evaluate
the categorization results.
So, the problem of text
categorization is defined as follows.
We're given a set of predefined categories
possibly forming a hierarchy or so.
And often,
also a set of training examples or
training set of labeled text
objects which means the text
objects have already been
enabled with known categories.
And then, the task is to classify
any text object into one or
more of these predefined categories.
So, the picture on this
slide shows what happens.
When we do text categorization,
we have a lot of text objects to be
processed by a categorization system and
the system will, in general,
assign categories through these documents.
As shown on the right and
the categorization results,
and we often assume the availability
of training examples and
these are the documents that
are tag with known categories.
And these examples are very important for
helping the system to learn
patterns in different categories.
And, this would further help
the system then know how to recognize
the categories of new text
objects that it has not seen.
So, here are some specific
examples of text categorization.
And in fact, there are many examples,
here are just a few.
So first, text objects can vary,
so we can categorize a document,
or a passage, or a sentence,
or collections of text.
As in the case of clustering, the units
to be analyzed can vary a lot, so
this creates a lot of possibilities.
Secondly, categories can also vary.
Allocate in general,
there's two major kinds of categories.
One is internal categories.
These are categories that
categorize content of text object.
For example, topic categories or
sentiment categories and
they generally have to do with
the content of the text objects
throughout the categorization
of the content.
The other kind is external categories
that can characterize an entity
associated with the text object.
For example,
authors are entities associated
with the content that they produce.
And so, we can use their content in
determining which author has written,
which part, for example, and
that's called author attribution.
Or, we can have any
other mininal categories
associate with text data
as long as there is minimal
connection between the entity and
text data.
For example, we might collect a lot
of reviews about a restaurant or
a lot of reviews about a product,
and then,
this text data can help us infer
properties of a product or a restaurant.
In that case, we can treat this
as a categorization problem.
We can categorize restaurants or
categorize products based on
their corresponding reviews.
So, this is an example for
external category.
Here are some specific
examples of the applications.
News categorization is very
common as being started a lot.
News agencies would like
to assign predefined
categories to categorize
news generated everyday.
And, these virtual article
categorizations are not important aspect.
For example, in the biomedical domain,
there's MeSH annotations.
MeSH stands for Medical Subject Heading,
and this is ontology of terms,
characterize content of
literature articles in detail.
Another example of application is spam
email detection or filtering, right?
So, we often have a spam filter
to help us distinguish spams
from legitimate emails and
this is clearly a binary
classification problem.
Sentiment categorization of
product reviews or tweets is yet
another kind of applications where we
can categorize, comparing to positive or
negative or positive and
negative or neutral.
So, you can have send them to categories,
assign the two text content.
Another application is automatic
email routing or sorting, so,
you might want to automatically sort your
emails into different folders and that's
one application of text categorization
where each folder is a category.
The results are another important kind
of applications of routing emails
to the right person to handle,
so, in helpdesk,
email messaging is generally routed
to a particular person to handle.
Different people tend to handle
different kinds of requests.
And in many cases, a person would manually
assign the messages to the right people.
But, if you can imagine,
you can't be able to automatically
text categorization system
to help routing request.
And, this is a class file, the incoming
request in the one of the categories
where each category actually corresponds
to a person to handle the request.
And finally, author attribution, as I just
mentioned, is yet another application, and
it's another example of using text
to actually infer properties of
some other entities.
And, there are also many variants
of the problem formulation.
And so, first, we have the simplest case,
which is a binary categorization,
where there are only two categories.
And, there are many examples like that,
information retrieval or search engine.
Applications with one distinguishing
relevant documents from non-relevant
documents for a particular query.
Spam filtering just distinguishing spams
from non-spams, so, also two categories.
Sometimes, classifications of
opinions can be in two categories,
positive and a negative.
A more general case would be K-category
categorization and there are also
many applications like that,
there could be more than two categories.
So, topic categorization is often
such an example where you can have
multiple topics.
Email routing would be another example
when you may have multiple folders or
if you route the email to
the right person to handle it,
then there are multiple
people to classify.
So, in all these cases, there are more
than two kinds of categories.
Another variation is to have
hierarchical categorization
where categories form a hierarchy.
Again, topical hierarchy is very common.
Yet another variation is
joint categorization.
That's when you have multiple
categorization tasks that are related and
then you hope to kind of
join the categorization.
Further leverage the dependency of
these tasks to improve accuracy for
each individual task.
Among all these binary categorizations
is most fundamental and
part of it also is because it's simple and
probably it's because
it can actually be used to perform
all the other categorization tasks.
For example, a K-category
categorization task can be actually
performed by using binary categorization.
Basically, we can look at
each category separately and
then the binary categorization problem
is whether object is in this category or
not, meaning in other categories.
And, the hierarchical categorization
can also be done by progressively
doing flat categorization at each level.
So, we have, first, we categorize
all the objects into, let's say,
a small number of high-level categories,
and inside each category, we have further
categorized to sub-categories, etc.
So, why is text categorization important?
Well, I already showed that you,
several applications but, in general,
there are several reasons.
One is text categorization helps enrich
text representation and that's to achieve
more understanding of text data that's
all it was useful for text analysis.
So, now with categorization text can
be represented in multiple levels.
The keyword conditions that's often
used for a lot text processing tasks.
But we can now also add categories and
they provide two levels of transition.
Semantic categories assigned can also
be directly or indirectly useful for
application.
So, for example, semantic categories
could be already very useful or
other attribution might
be directly useful.
Another example is when semantic
categories can facilitate aggregation
of text content and this is another case
of applications of text categorization.
For example, if we want to know
the overall opinions about a product, we
could first categorize the opinions
in each individual view
as positive or negative and then, that
would allow us to easy to aggregate all
the sentiment, and it would tell us about
the 70% of the views are positive and
30% are negative, etc.
So, without doing categorization,
it will be much harder to aggregate
such opinions to provide a concise
way of coding text in some sense
based on all of the vocabulary.
And, sometimes you may see in some
applications, text with categorizations
called a text coded,
encoded with some control of vocabulary.
The second kind of reasons is to use text
categorization to infer
properties of entities,
and text categories allows
us to infer the properties
of such entities that
are associate with text data.
So, this means we can
use text categorization
to discover knowledge about the world.
In general, as long as we can associate
the entity with text of data,
we can always the text of data to help
categorize the corresponding entities.
So, it's used for
single information network that will
connect the other entities with text data.
The obvious entities that can be
directly connected are authors.
But, you can also imagine the author's
affiliations or the author's age and
other things can be actually
connected to text data indirectly.
Once we have made the connection, then we
can make a prediction about those values.
So, this is a general way to allow
us to use text mining through, so
the text categorization to discover
knowledge about the world.
Very useful, especially in big text
data analytics where we are often
just using text data as extra sets
of data extracted from humans
to infer certain decision factors
often together with non-textual data.
Specifically with text, for example,
we can also think of examples of
inferring properties of entities.
For example, discovery of
non-native speakers of a language.
And, this can be done by categorizing
the content of speakers.
Another example is to predict the party
affiliation of a politician based
on the political speech.
And, this is again an example
of using text data to infer
some knowledge about the real world.
In nature,
the problems are all the same, and
that's as we defined and
it's a text categorization problem.
[MUSIC]