[MUSIC]
This lecture is about
evaluation of text clustering.
So far we have talked about multiple
ways of doing text clustering but
how do we know which
method works the best?
So this has to do with evaluation.
Now to talk about evaluation one must
go back to the clustering bias that
we introduced at the beginning.
Because two objects can be similar
depending on how you look at them,
we must clearly specify
the perspective of similarity.
Without that, the problem of
clustering is not well defined.
So this perspective is also
very important for evaluation.
If you look at this slide, and
you can see we have two different
ways to cluster these shapes, and
if you ask a question, which one is
the best, or which one is better?
You actually see, there's no way to answer
this question without knowing whether
we'd like to cluster based on shapes,
or cluster based on sizes.
And that's precisely why
the perspective on clustering bias is
crucial for evaluation.
In general,
we can evaluate text clusters in two ways,
one is direct evaluation, and
the other indirect evaluation.
So in direct evaluation,
we want to answer the following questions,
how close are the system-generated
clusters to the ideal clusters
that are generated by humans?
So the closeness here can be assessed
from multiple perspectives and
that will help us characterize the quality
of cluster result in multiple angles,
and this is sometimes desirable.
Now we also want to quantify
the closeness because this would allow
us to easily compare different measures
based on their performance figures.
And finally, you can see, in this case,
we essentially inject the clustering bias
by using humans, basically humans
would bring in the the need or
desire to clustering bias.
Now, how do we do that exactly?
Well, the general procedure
would look like this.
Given a test set which consists
of a lot of text objects,
we can have humans to create
the ideal clustering result, that is,
we're going to ask humans to partition
the objects to create the gold standard.
And they will use their judgments based
on the need of a particular application
to generate what they think are the best
clustering results, and this would be then
used to compare with the system generated
clusters from the same test set.
And ideally, we want the system results
to be the same as the human generated
results, but in general,
they are not going to be the same.
So we would like to then quantify the
similarity between the system-generated
clusters and the gold standard clusters.
And this similarity can also be measure
from multiple perspectives and this will
give us various meshes to quantitatively
evaluate a cluster, a clustering result.
And some of the commonly used measures
include the purity, which measures whether
a cluster has a similar object from
the same cluster, in the gold standard.
And normalized mutual information
is a commonly used measure
which basically measures
based on the identity of
cluster of object in the system generally.
How well can you predict the cluster
of the object in the gold standard or
vice versa?
And mutual information captures, the
correlation between these cluster labels
and normalized mutual information is often
used for quantifying the similarity for
this evaluation purpose,
F measure is another possible measure.
Now again a thorough discussion
of this evaluation and
these evaluation issues would be
beyond the scope of this course.
I've suggested some reading in
the end that you can take a look
at to know more about that.
So here I just want to
discuss some high level ideas
that would allow you to think about how
to do evaluation in your applications.
The second way to evaluate text
clusters is to do indirect evaluation.
So in this case the question to answer is,
how useful are the clustering results for
the intended applications?
Now this of course is application
specific question, so
usefulness is going to depend
on specific applications.
In this case, the clustering bias is
imposed by the independent application
as well, so
what counts as a best cluster result
would be dependent on the application.
Now procedure wise we also would create
a test set with text objects for
the intended application to quantify
the performance of the system.
In this case,
what we care about is the contribution of
clustering to some application so we often
have a baseline system to compare with.
This could be the current system for
doing something, and
then you hope to add
a clustering to improve it, or
the baseline system could be using
a different clustering method.
And then what you are trying
to experiment with, and
you hope to have better
idea of word clustering.
So in any case you have a baseline system
work with, and then you add a clustering
algorithm to the baseline system
to produce a clustering system.
And then we have to compare the
performance of your clustering system and
the baseline system in terms
of the performance measure for
that particular application.
So in this case we call it indirect
evaluation of clusters because there's no
explicit assessment of
the quality of clusters, but
rather it's to assess the contribution
of clusters to a particular application.
So, to summarize text clustering,
it's a very useful unsupervised
general text mining technique, and
it's particularly useful for obtaining
an overall picture of the text content.
And this is often needed
to explore text data, and
this is often the first step when
you deal with a lot of text data.
The second application or
second kind of applications is through
discover interesting clustering
structures in text data and
these structures can be very meaningful.
There are many approaches that can
be used to form text clustering and
we discussed model based approaches and
some narrative based approaches.
In general, strong clusters tend to
show up no matter what method is used.
Also the effectiveness of a method
highly depends on whether the desired
clustering bias is captured appropriately,
and this can be done either through using
the right generating model, the model
design appropriate for the clustering, or
the right similarity function
expressly define the bias.
Deciding the optimal number of customers
is a very difficult problem for
order cluster methods, and that's
because it's unsupervised algorithm,
and there's no training there how to guide
us to select the best number of clusters.
Now sometimes you may see some methods
that can automatically determine
the number of clusters, but
in general that has some implied
application of clustering bias there and
that's just not specified.
Without clearly defining a clustering
bias, it's just impossible to say
the optimal number of cluster is what,
so this important to keep in mind.
And I should also say sometimes we
can also use application to determine
the number of clusters, for example,
if you're clustering search results,
then obviously you don't want
to generate the 100 clusters, so
the number can be dictated
by the interface design.
In other situations, we might be
able to use the fitness to data
to assess whether we've got a good number
of clusters to explain our data well.
And to do that,
you can vary the number of clusters and
watch how well you can fit the data.
In general when you add a more components
to a mixed model you should fit
the data better because you, you don't,
you can always set the probability
of using the new component as zero.
So you can't in general fit the data
worse than before, but the question
is as you add more components would you be
able to significantly improve the fitness
of the data and that can be used to
determine the right number of clusters.
And finally evaluation
of clustering results,
this kind can be done both directly and
indirectly, and we often would like to
do both in order to get a good sense
about how well our method works.
So here's some suggested reading and
this is particularly useful
to better understand how the matches
are calculated and clustering in general
[MUSIC]