[SOUND] This lecture is about
the Evaluation of Text Categorization.
So we've talked about many different
methods for text categorization.
But how do you know which
method works better?
And for a particular application,
how do you know this is the best
way of solving your problem?
To understand these, we have to
how to we have to know how to
evaluate categorization results.
So first some general thoughts
about the evaluation.
In general, for evaluation of this kind of
empirical tasks such as categorization,
we use methodology that
was developed in 1960s by
information retrieval researchers.
Called a Cranfield Evaluation Methodology.
The basic idea is to have
humans create test correction,
where, we already know, every document
is tagged with the desired categories.
Or, in the case of search, for which
query, which documents that should have
been retrieved, and
this is called, a ground truth.
Now, with this ground
truth test correction,
we can then reuse the collection to
test the many different systems and
then compare different systems.
We can also turn off some components in
the system to see what's going to happen.
Basically it provides a way to do control
experiments to compare different methods.
So this methodology has
been virtually used for
all the tasks that involve
empirically defined problems.
So in our case, then, we are going to
compare our systems categorization
results with the categorization,
ground truth, created by humans.
And we're going to compare
our systems decisions,
which documents should get
which category with what
categories have been assigned
to those documents by humans.
And we want to quantify
the similarity of these decisions or
equivalently, to measure the difference
between the system output and
the desired ideal output
generated by the humans.
So obviously, the highest similarity
is the better results are.
The similarity could be
measured in different ways.
And that would lead to different measures.
And sometimes it's desirable also to match
the similarity from different perspectives
just to have a better understanding
of the results in detail.
For example, we might be also interested
in knowing which category performs
better and which which category
is easy to categorize, etc.
In general,
different categorization mistakes
however, have different costs for
specific applications.
So some areas might be
more serious than others.
So ideally, we would like to model
such differences, but if you read
many papers in categorization you will
see that they don't generally do that.
Instead, they will use a simplified
measure and that's because it's
often okay not to consider such a cost
variation when we compare methods and
when we are interested in knowing
the relative difference of these methods.
So it's okay to introduce some bias,
as long as the bias is not already with
a particular method and then we should
expect the more effective method to
perform better than a less effective one,
even though the measure is not perfect.
So the first measure that we'll introduce
is called classification accuracy and
this is a basic into measure
the percentage of correct decisions.
So here you see that there
are categories denoted by c1
through ck and there are n documents,
denoted by d1 through d N.
And for each pair of category and
the document,
we can then look at the situation.
And see if the system has
said yes to this pair,
basically has assigned this
category to this document.
Or no, so this is denoted by Y or M,
that's the systems of the decision.
And similarly, we can look at the human's
decisions also, if the human has assigned
a category to the document of that
there will be a plus sign here.
That just means that a human.
We think of this assignment is correct and
incorrect then it's a minus.
So we'll see all combinations of this Ns,
yes and nos, minus and pluses.
There are four combinations in total.
And two of them are correct, and
that's when we have y(+) or n(-),
and then there are also
two kinds of errors.
So the measure of classification
accuracy is simply to count
how many of these decisions are correct.
And normalize that by the total
number of decisions we have made.
So, we know that the total number
of decisions is n, multiplied by k.
And, the number of correct decisions
are basically of two kinds.
One is y plusses.
And the other is n minus this n.
We just put together the count.
Now, this is a very convenient
measure that will give us one number
to characterize performance of a method.
And the higher, the better, of course.
But the method also has some problems.
First it has treated all
the decisions equally.
But in reality, some decision errors
are more serious than others.
For example, it may be more important to
get the decisions right on some documents,
than others.
Or maybe, more important to get
the decisions right on some categories,
than others, and this would call for
some detailed evaluation of this
results to understand the strands and
of different methods, and to understand
the performance of these methods.
In detail in a per category or
per document basis.
One example that shows clearly
the decision errors are having different
causes is spam filtering that could be
retrieved as two category categorization
problem.
Missing a legitimate email result,
is one type of error.
But letting spam to come into your
folder is another type of error.
The two types of errors
are clearly very different,
because it's very important not
to miss a legitimate email.
It's okay to occasionally let a spam
email to come into your inbox.
So the error of the first, missing a
legitimate email is very, is of high cost.
It's a very serious mistake and
classification error, classification
accuracy does not address this issue.
There's also another problem
with imbalance to test set.
Imagine there's a skew to test set where
most instances are category one and
98% of instances are category one.
Only 2% are in category two.
In such a case, we can have a very
simple baseline that accurately performs
very well and that baseline.
Sign with similar,
I put all instances in the major category.
That will get us 98%
accuracy in this case.
It's going to be appearing to be
very effective, but in reality,
this is obviously not a good result.
And so, in general, when we use
classification accuracy as a measure,
we want to ensure that
the causes of balance.
And one above equal number of instances,
for
example in each class the minority
categories or causes tend to be
overlooked in the evaluation
of classification accuracy.
So, to address these problems,
we of course would like to also evaluate
the results in other ways and
in different ways.
As I said, it's beneficial to look
at after multiple perspectives.
So for example, we can look at
the perspective from each document
as a perspective based on each document.
So the question here is, how good
are the decisions on this document?
Now, as in the general cases of all
decisions, we can think about four
combinations of possibilities, depending
on whether the system has said yes and
depending on whether the human has said it
correct or incorrect or said yes or no.
And so the four combinations are first
when both the human systems said yes, and
that's the true positives, when the system
says, yes, and it's after the positive.
So, when the system says,
yes, it's a positive.
But, when the human confirm
that it is indeed correct,
that becomes a true positive.
When the system says, yes,
but the human says, no,
that's incorrect,
that's a false positive, have FP.
And when the system says no, but the human
says yes, then it's a false negative.
We missed one assignment.
When both the system and
human says no, then it's also correctly
to assume that's true negatives.
All right, so
then we can have some measures to just
better characterize the performance
by using these four numbers and
so two popular measures are precision and
recall.
And these were also proposed by
information retrieval researchers 1960s
for evaluating search results, but
now they have become standard measures,
use it everywhere.
So when the system says yes, we can ask
the question, how many are correct?
What's the percent of correct
decisions when the system says yes?
That's called precision.
It's true positive divided by all
the cases when the system says yes,
all the positives.
The other measure is called recall,
and this measures
whether the document has all
the categories it should have.
So in this case it's divide the true
positive by true positives and
the false negatives.
So these are all the cases where
this human Says the document
should have this category.
So this represents both categories
that it should have got, and
so recall tells us whether
the system has actually indeed
assigned all the categories that
it should have to this document.
This gives us a detailed
view of the document,
then we can aggregate them later.
And if we're interested in some documents,
and
this will tell us how well we did on
those documents, the subsets of them.
It might be more interesting than others,
for example.
And this allows us to analyze
errors in more detail as well.
We can separate the documents of certain
characteristics from others, and
then look at the errors.
You might see a pattern A for
this kind of document, this long document.
It doesn't as well for shock documents.
And this gives you some insight for
inputting the method.
Similarly, we can look at
the per-category evaluation.
In this case,
we're going to look at the how good are
the decisions on a particular category.
As in the previous case we can
define precision and recall.
And it would just basically answer the
questions from a different perspective.
So when the system says yes,
how many are correct?
That means looking at this category
to see if all the documents
that are assigned with this category
are indeed in this category, right?
And recall, would tell us,
has the category been actually assigned to
all the documents That
should have this category.
It's sometimes also useful to combine
precision and recall as one measure, and
this is often done by using f measure.
And this is just a harmonic
mean of precision.
Precision and
recall defined on this slide.
And it's also controlled
by a parameter beta to
indicate whether precision is
more important or recall is more.
When beta is set to 1,
we have measure called F1, and
in this case, we just take equal
weight upon both procedure and recall.
F1 is very often used as a measure for
categorization.
Now, as in all cases, when we combine
results, you always should think about
the best way of combining them, so in this
case I don't know if you have thought
about it and we could have combined
them just with arithmetic mean, right.
So that would still give us
the same range of values, but
obviously there's a reason why we didn't
do that and why f1 is more popular,
and it's actually useful
to think about difference.
And we think about that, you'll see
that there is indeed some difference and
some undesirable property
of this arithmatic.
Basically, it will be obvious
to you if you think about a case
when the system says yes for
all the category and document pairs.
And then try the compute the precision and
recall in that case.
And see what would happen.
And basically, this kind of measure,
the arithmetic mean, is not going to be as
reasonable as F1 minus one
[INAUDIBLE] trade off,
so that the two values are equal.
There is an extreme case where you have
0 for one letter and one for the other.
Then F1 will be low, but
the mean would still be reasonably high.
[MUSIC]