[MUSIC]
This lecture is about the similarity-based
approaches to text clustering.
In this lecture we're going to to continue
the discussion of how to do a text
clustering.
In particular, we're going to to
cover different kinds of approaches
than generative models, and
that is similarity-based approaches.
So the general idea of similarity-based
clustering is to explicitly
specify a similarity function to measure
the similarity between two text objects.
Now this is in contrast with
a generative model where we
implicitly define the clustering bias
by using a particular object to
function like a [INAUDIBLE] function.
The whole process is driven by
optimizing the [INAUDIBLE,] but
here we explicitly provide a view
of what we think are similar.
And this is often very useful
because then it allows us to inject
any particular view of similarity
into the clustering program.
So once we have a similarity function,
we can then aim at optimally partitioning,
to partitioning the data into clusters or
into different groups.
And try to maximize
the inter-group similarity and
minimize the inter-group similarity.
That is to ensure the objects that are put
into the same group to be similar, but
the objects that are put into
different groups to be not similar.
And these are the general
goals of clustering,
and there is often a trade off
between achieving both goals.
Now there are many different methods for
doing similarity based clustering,
and in general I think we can distinguish
the two strategies at high level.
One is to progressively construct
the hierarchy of clusters, and
so this often leads to
hierarchical clustering.
And we can further distinguish it
two ways, to construct a hierarchy
depending on whether we started with
the collection to divide the connection.
Or started with individual objectives and
gradually group them together, so
one is bottom-up that can
be called agglomerative.
Well we gradually group a similar
objects into larger and larger clusters.
Until we group everything together,
the other is top-down or divisive, in this
case we gradually partition the whole data
set into smaller and smaller clusters.
The other general strategy is to start
with the initial tentative clustering and
then iteratively improve it.
And this often leads for
a flat clustering, one example is k-Means,
so as I just said, there are many
different clustering methods available.
And a full coverage of all
the clustering methods would be
beyond the scope of this course.
But here we are going to talk about the
two representative methods, in some detail
one is Hierarchical Agglomerative
Clustering or HAC, the other is k-Means.
So first of it we'll get the agglomerative
hierarchical clustering, in this case,
we're given a similarity function to
measure similarity between two objects.
And then we can gradually group similar
objects together in a bottom-up fashion to
form larger and larger groups.
And they always form a hierarchy, and
then we can stop when some
stopping criterion is met.
It could be either some number
of clusters has been achieved or
the threshold for
similarity has been reached.
There are different variations here, and
they mainly differ in the ways
to compute a group similarity.
Based on the individual
objects similarity, so
let's illustrate how again induced
a structure based on just similarity.
So start with all the text objects and
we can then measure
the similarity between them.
Of course based on the provided
similarity function, and
then we can see which pair
has the highest similarity.
And then just group them together, and
then we're going to see which
pair is the next one to group.
Maybe these two now have
the highest similarity, and
then we're going to gradually
group them together.
And then every time we're going
to pick the highest similarity,
the similarity of pairs to group.
This will give us a binary tree
eventually to group everything together.
Now, depending on our applications,
we can use the whole hierarchy as
a structure for browsing, for example.
Or we can choose a cutoff,
let's say cut here to get four clusters,
or we can use a threshold to cut.
Or we can cut at this high level
to get just two clusters, so
this is a general idea, now if you think
about how to implement this algorithm.
You'll realize that we have
everything specified except for
how to compute group similarity.
We are only given the similarity
function of two objects, but as
we group groups together, we also need to
assess the similarity between two groups.
There are also different ways to do that
and there are the three popular methods.
Single-link, complete-link,
and average-link, so
given two groups and
the single-link algorithm.
Is going to define the group similarity
as the similarity of the closest pair of
the two groups.
Complete-link defines
the similarity of the two groups
as the similarity of
the farthest system pair.
Average-link defines the similarity
as average of similarity of
all the pairs of the two groups.
So it's much easier to understand
the methods by illustrating them,
so here are two groups, g1 and
g2 with some objects in each group.
And we know how to compute
the similarity between two objects, but
the question now is, how can we compute
the similarity between the two groups?
And then we can in general base this
on the similarities of the objects
in the two groups.
So, in terms of single-link and
we're just looking at the closest pair so
in this case,
these two paired objects will defined
the similarities of the two groups.
As long as they are very close,
we're going to say the two groups are very
close so
it is an optimistic view of similarity.
The complete link on the other hand
were in some sense pessimistic, and by
taking the similarity of the two farthest
pair as the similarity for the two groups.
So we are going to make sure that
if the two groups are having
a high similarity.
Then every pair of the two groups, or
the objects in the two groups will have,
will be ensured to have high similarity.
Now average link is in between, so
it takes the average of all these pairs.
Now these different ways of computing
group similarities will lead
to different clustering algorithms.
And they would in general
give different results, so
it's useful to take a look at their
differences and to make a comparison.
First, single-link can be expected to
generally the loose clusters, the reason
is because as long as two objects
are very similar in the two groups,
it will bring the two groups together.
If you think about this as similar
to having parties with people,
then it just means two groups of
people would be partying together.
As long as in each group
there is a person that
is well connected with the other group.
So the two leaders of the two
groups can have a good
relationship with each other and then
they will bring together the two groups.
In this case, the cluster is loose,
because there's no guarantee that
other members of the two groups
are actually very close to each other.
Sometimes they may be very far away,
now in this case it's also
based on individual decisions, so
it could be sensitive to outliers.
The complete-link is in
the opposite situation,
where we can expect
the clusters to be tight.
And it's also based on individual decision
so it can be sensitive to outliers.
Again to continue the analogy
to having a party of people,
then complete-link would mean
when two groups come together.
They want to ensure that even
the people that are unlikely to talk
to each other would be comfortable.
Always talking to each other, so
ensure the whole class to be coherent.
The average link of clusters in
between and as group decision, so it's
going to be insensitive to outliers,
now in practice which one is the best.
Well, this would depend on the application
and sometimes you need a lose clusters.
And aggressively cluster objects
together that maybe single-link is good.
But other times you might
need a tight clusters and
a complete-link might be better.
But in general, you have to
empirically evaluate these methods for
your application to know
which one is better.
Now, next let's look at another example of
a method for similarity-based clustering.
In this case,
which is called k-Means clustering,
we will represent each text
object as a term vector.
And then assume a similarity function
defined on two objects, now we're going to
start with some tentative clustering
results by just selecting k randomly.
selected vectors as
centroids of k clusters and
treat them as centers as if they
represent, they each represent a cluster.
So this gives us the initial
tentative cluster,
then we're going to
iteratively improve it.
And the process goes like this, and
once we have these centroids Decide.
We're going to assign
a vector to the cluster whose
centroid is closest to the current vector.
So basically we're going to measure
the distance between this vector, and
each of the centroids, and
see which one is the closest to this one.
And then just put this
object into that cluster,
this is to have tentative assignment
of objects into clusters.
And we're going to
partition all the objects
into k clusters based on our
tentative clustering and centroids.
Then we can do re-compute
the centroid based on
the locate the object in each cluster.
And this is to adjust the centroid, and
then we can repeat this process until
the similarity-based objective function.
In this case, it's within cluster
sum of squares converges, and
theoretically we can show that.
This process actually is going to minimize
the within cluster sum of squares
where define object and function.
Given k clusters, so it can be also shown,
this process will converge
to a local minimum.
I think about this process for a moment,
it might remind you the Algorithm for
mixture model.
Indeed this algorithm is very
similar to the Algorithm for
the mixture model for clustering.
More specifically we also
initialize these parameters
in the Algorithm so
the random initialization is similar.
And then in the Algorithm,
you may recall that,
we're going to repeat E-step and M-step
to improve our parameter estimation.
In this case, we're going to
improve the clustering result
iteratively by also doing two steps.
And in fact that the two steps are very
similar to Algorithm, in that when we
locate the vector into one of the clusters
based on our tentative clustering.
It's very similar to inferring
the distribution that has been used to
generate the document, the mixture model.
So it is essentially similar to E-step, so
what's the difference,
well the difference is here.
We don't make a probabilistic
allocation as in the case of E-step,
the brother will make a choice.
We're going to make a call if this,
there upon this closest to cluster two,
then we're going to say
you are in cluster two.
So there's no choice, and
we're not going to say, you assume
the set is belonging to a cluster two.
And so
we're not going to have a probability, but
we're just going to put one object
into precisely one cluster.
In the E-step however, we do a probability
location, so we split in counts.
And we're not going to say
exactly which distribution has
been used to generate a data point.
Now next,
we're going to adjust the centroid, and
this is very similar to M-step where
we re-estimate the parameters.
That's when we'll have a better
estimate of the parameter, so
here we'll have a better clustering
result by adjusting the centroid.
And note that centroid is based on
the average of the vectors in the cluster.
So this is also similar to the M-step
where we do counts,pull together counts
and then normalize them.
The difference of course is also because
of the difference in the E-step, and
we're not going to consider
probabilities when we count the points.
In this case,
k-Means we're going to all make count of
the objects as allocated to this cluster.
And this is only a subset of data points,
but in the Algorithm,
we in principle consider all the data
points based on probabilistic allocations.
But in nature they are very similar and
that's why it's also maximizing
well defined object of functions.
And it's guaranteed to
convert local minimum, so
to summarize our discussion
of clustering methods.
We first discussed model based approaches,
mainly the mixture model.
Here we use the implicit similarity
function to define the clustering bias.
There is no explicit define similarity
function, the model defines clustering
bias and the clustering structure
is built into a generative model.
That's why we can use
potentially a different model to
recover different structure.
Complex generative models can be used to
discover complex clustering structures.
We do not talk about in full,
but we can easily design,
generate a model to generate
a hierarchical clusters.
We can also use prior to further
customize the clustering algorithm to for
example control the topic of one
cluster or multiple clusters.
However one disadvantage of this
approach is that there is no easy way to
directly control the similarity measure.
Sometimes we want to that,
but it's very hard to
inject such a special definition
of similarity into such a model.
We also talked about
similarity-based approaches,
these approaches are more flexible to
actually specify similarity functions.
But one major disadvantage is that
their objective function
is not always very clear.
The k-Means algorithm has clearly
defined the objective function, but
it's also very similar to
a model based approach.
The hierarchical clustering algorithm on
the other hand is harder to
specify the objective function.
So it's not clear what
exactly is being optimized,
both approaches can
generate term clusters.
And document clusters, and
term clusters can be in general,
generated by representing each
term with some text content.
For example, take the context of each
term as a representation of each term,
as we have done in semantic
relation learning.
And then we can certainly cluster terms,
based on actual text [INAUDIBLE].
Of course, term clusters can be generated
by using generative models as well,
as we've seen.
[MUSIC]