[SOUND]
This
lecture is about generating probabilistic
models for text clustering.
In this lecture, we're going to continue
discussing text clustering, and
we're going to introduce
generating probabilistic models
as a way to do text clustering.
So this is the overall plan for
covering text clustering.
In the previous lecture, we have talked
about what is text clustering and
why text clustering is interesting.
In this lecture, we're going to talk
about how to do text clustering.
In general, as you see on this slide,
there are two kinds of approaches.
One is generating probabilistic models,
which is the topic of this lecture.
And later, we'll also discuss
similarity-based approaches.
So to talk about generating models for
text clustering,
it would be useful to revisit
the topic mining problem
using topic models,
because the two problems are very similar.
This is a slide that you have seen
earlier in the lecture on topic model.
Here we show that we have input
of a text collection C and
a number of topics k, and vocabulary V.
And we hope to generate
as output two things.
One is a set of topics
denoted by Theta i's,
each is awarded distribution and
the other is pi i j.
These are the probabilities that
each document covers each topic.
So this is a topic coverage and
it's also visualized here on this slide.
You can see that this is what we
can get by using a topic model.
Now, the main difference between this and
the text clustering problem is that here,
a document is assumed to
possibly cover multiple topics.
And indeed, in general,
a document will be covering
more than one topic with
nonzero probabilities.
In text clustering, however,
we only allow a document
to cover one topic,
if we assume one topic is a cluster.
So that means if we change the problem
definition just slightly by
assuming that each document that can only
be generated by using precisely one topic.
Then we'll have a definition of
the clustering problem as you'll hear.
So here the output is changed so
that we no longer have the detailed
coverage distributions pi i j.
But instead, we're going to have
a cluster assignment decisions, Ci.
And Ci is a decision for the document i.
And C sub i is going to take a value
from 1 through k to indicate one of
the k clusters.
And basically tells us that
d i is in which cluster.
As illustrated here, we no longer have
multiple topics covered in each document.
It is precisely one topic.
Although which topic is still uncertain.
There is also a connection with
the problem of mining one topic
that we discussed earlier.
So here again,
it's a slide that you have seen before and
here we hope to estimate a topic model or
distribution based on
precisely one document.
And that's when we assume that this
document, it covers precisely one topic.
But we can also consider some
variations of the problem.
For example,
we can consider there are N documents,
each covers a different topic, so
that's N documents, and topics.
Of course, in this case,
these documents are independent,
and these topics are also independent.
But, we can further allow these
documents with share topics, and
we can also assume that we are going
to assume there are fewer topics than
the number of documents, so
these documents must share some topics.
And if we have N documents
that share k topics,
then we'll again have precisely
the document clustering problem.
So because of these connections,
naturally we can think about how to
use a probabilistically generative model
to solve the problem of text clustering.
So the question now is what generative
model can be used to do clustering?
As in all cases of designing a generative
model, we hope the generative model would
adopt the output that we hope to generate
or the structure that we hope to model.
So in this case,
this is a clustering structure,
the topics and
each document that covers one topic.
And we hope to embed such
preferences in the generative model.
But, if you think about the main
difference between this problem and
the topic model that we
talked about earlier.
And you will see a main requirement
is how can we force every
document to be generated
from precisely one topic,
instead of k topics,
as in the topic model?
So let's revisit the topic
model again in more detail.
So this is a detailed view of
a two component mixture model.
When we have k components,
it looks similar.
So here we see that when
we generate a document,
we generate each word independent.
And when we generate each word, but first
make a choice between these distributions.
We decide to use one of
them with probability.
So p of theta 1 is the probability of
choosing the distribution on the top.
Now we first make this decision regarding
which distribution should be used to
generate the word.
And then we're going to use this
distribution to sample a word.
Now note that in such a generative model,
the decision on which distribution
to use for each word is independent.
So that means, for example,
the here could have generated from
the second distribution, theta 2
whereas text is more likely generated
from the first one on the top.
That means the words in the document that
could have been generated in general
from multiple distributions.
Now this is not what we want,
as we said, for text clustering, for
document clustering,
where we hoped this document will be
generated from precisely one topic.
So now that means we
need to modify the model.
But how?
Well, let's first think about why this
model cannot be used for clustering.
And as I just said, the reason is because
it has allowed multiple topics to
contribute a word to the document.
And that causes confusion because
we're not going to know which cluster
this document is from.
And it's, more importantly
it's violating our assumption
about the partitioning of
documents in the clusters.
If we really have one topic to correspond
it to one cluster of documents,
then we would have a document that we
generate from precisely one topic.
That means all the words in the document
must have been generated from
precisely one distribution.
And this is not true for
such a topic model that we're seeing here.
And that's why this cannot be used for
clustering because it did not ensure
that only one distribution has been used
to generate all the words in one document.
So if you realize this problem,
then we can naturally design alternative
mixture model for doing clustering.
So this is what you're seeing here.
And we again have to make a decision
regarding which distribution to use
to generate this document because
the document could potentially
be generated from any of the k
word distributions that we have.
But this time, once we have made
a decision to choose one of the topics,
we're going to stay with this regime to
generate all the words in the document.
And that means, once we have made
a choice of the distribution in
generating the first word,
we're going to go stay with this
distribution in generating all of
the other words in the document.
So, in other words,
we only make the choice once for,
basically, we make the decision once for
this document and
this state was just to
generate all the words.
Similarly if I had choosing the second
distribution, theta sub 2 here,
you can see which state was this one.
And then generate
the entire document of d.
Now, if you compare this
picture with the previous one,
you will see the decision of
using a particular distribution
is made just once for this document,
in the case of document clustering.
But in the case of topic model,
we have to make as many decisions as
the number of words in the document.
Because for each word, we can make
a potentially different decision.
And that's the key difference
between the two models.
But this is obviously
also a mixed model so
we can just group them together
as one box to show that this is
the model that will give us
a probability of the document.
Now, inside of this model,
there is also this switch of
choosing a different distribution.
And we don't observe that so
that's a mixture model.
And of course a main problem in
document clustering is to infer which
distribution has been used
to generate a document and
that would allow us to recover
the cluster identity of a document.
So it will be useful to think about
the difference from the topic model as
I have also mentioned multiple times.
And there are mainly two differences,
one is the choice of
using that particular distribution is
made just once for document clustering.
Whereas in the topic model, it's made
it multiple times for different words.
The second is that word distribution,
here,
is going to be used to regenerate
all the words for a document.
But, in the case of one
distribution doesn't have to
generate all the words in the document.
Multiple distribution could have been used
to generate the words in the document.
Let's also think about a special case,
when one of the probability of choosing
a particular distribution is equal to 1.
Now that just means we
have no uncertainty now.
We just stick with one
particular distribution.
Now in that case, clearly, we will
see this is no longer mixture model,
because there's no uncertainty here and
we can just use precisely one of the
distributions for generating a document.
And we're going back to
the case of estimating one
order distribution based on one document.
So that's a connection
that we discussed earlier.
Now you can see it more clearly.
So as in all cases of using
a generative model to solve a problem,
we first look at data and
then think about how to design the model.
But once we design the model,
the next step is to write
down the likelihood function.
And after that we're going to look at
the how to estimate the parameters.
So in this case,
what's the likelihood function?
It's going to be very similar to what
you have seen before in topic models but
it will be also different.
Now if you still recall what
the likelihood function looks like in
then you will realize that in general, the
probability of observing a data point from
mixture model is going to be a sum of all
the possibilities of generating the data.
In this case, so it's going to
be a sum over these k topics,
because every one can be
user generated document.
And then inside is the sum you can still
recall what the formula looks like, and
it's going to be the product
of two probabilities.
One is the probability of choosing the
distribution, the other is the probability
of observing a particular
datapoint from that distribution.
So if you map this kind of
formula to our problem here,
you will see the probability
of observing a document d
is basically a sum in this
case of two different
distributions because we have a very
simplified situation of just two clusters.
And so in this case,
you can see it's a sum of two cases.
In each case,
it's indeed the probability of choosing
the distribution either theta 1 or
theta 2.
And then, the probability is
multiplied by the probability of
observing this document from
this particular distribution.
And if you further expanded
this probability of observing
the whole document, we see that it's
a product of observing each word X sub i.
And here we made the assumption that
each word is generated independently, so
the probability of the whole
document is just a product
of the probability of each
word in the document.
So this form should be very
similar to the topic model.
But it's also useful to think about
the difference and for that purpose,
I am also copying the probability of
topic model of these two components here.
So here you can see the formula looks very
similar or in many ways, they are similar.
But there is also some difference.
And in particular,
the difference is on the top.
You see for the mixture model for document
clustering, we first take a product, and
then take a sum.
And that's corresponding
to our assumption of
first make a choice of
choosing one distribution and
then stay with the distribution,
it'll generate all the words.
And that's why we have
the product inside the sum.
The sum corresponds to the choice.
Now, in topic model, we see that
the sum is actually inside the product.
And that's because we generated
each word independently.
And that's why we have
the product outside, but
when we generate each word we
have to make a decision regarding
which distribution we use so
we have a sum there for each word.
But in general,
these are all mixture models and
we can estimate these models
by using the Algorithm,
as we will discuss more later.
[MUSIC]