[SOUND]
This lecture is
about how to use generative probabilistic
models for text categorization.
There are in general about two kinds
of approaches to text categorization
by using machine learning.
One is by generating probabilistic models.
The other is discriminative approaches.
In this lecture, we're going to
talk about the generative models.
In the next lecture, we're going to
talk about discriminative approaches.
So the problem of text categorization
is actually a very similar
to document clustering.
In that, we'll assume that each document
it belongs to one category or one cluster.
The main difference is that in
clustering we don't really know
what are the predefined categories are,
what are the clusters.
In fact,
that's the goal of text clustering.
We want to find such clusters in the data.
But in the case of categorization,
we are given the categories.
So we kind of have
pre-defined categories and
then based on these categories and
training data, we would like to allocate
a document to one of these categories or
sometimes multiple categories.
But because of the similarity
of the two problems,
we can actually get the document
clustering models for text categorization.
And we understand how we can
use generated models to do
text categorization from
the perspective of clustering.
And so, this is a slide that we've talked
about before, about text clustering,
where we assume there are multiple topics
represented by word distributions.
Each topic is one cluster.
So once we estimated such a model,
we faced a problem of deciding which
cluster document d should belong to.
And this question boils down to decide
which theta i has been used to generate d.
Now, suppose d has L words
represented as xi here.
Now, how can you compute
the probability that a particular
topic word distribution zeta i has
been used to generate this document?
Well, in general, we use base
wall to make this influence and
you can see this prior information here
that we need to consider if a topic or
cluster has a higher prior
then it's more likely
that the document has
been from this cluster.
And so, we should favor such a cluster.
The other is a likelihood part,
it's this part.
And this has to do with whether
the topic word of distribution
can explain the content
of this document well.
And we want to pick a topic
that's high by both values.
So more specifically,
we just multiply them together and
then choose which topic
has the highest product.
So more rigorously,
this is what we'd be doing.
So we're going to choose
the topic that would maximize.
This posterior probability at the top
of a given document gets posterior
because this one,
p of the i, is the prior.
That's our belief about
which topic is more likely,
before we observe any document.
But this conditional probability here is
the posterior probability of the topic
after we have observed the document of d.
And base wall allows us to update this
probability based on the prior and
I have shown the details,
below here you can see how
the prior here is related to
the posterior, on the left-hand side.
And this is related to how
well this word distribution
explains the document here, and
the two are related in this way.
So to find the topic that has the higher
posterior probability here it's
equivalent to maximize this product
as we have seen also,
multiple times in this course.
And we can then change the probability
of document in your product of
the probability of each word, and
that's just because we've made
an assumption about independence
in generating each word.
So this is just something that you
have seen in document clustering.
And we now can see clearly how we
can assign a document to a category
based on the information
about word distributions for
these categories and
the prior on these categories.
So this idea can be directly
adapted to do categorization.
And this is precisely what
a Naive Bayes Classifier is doing.
So here it's most really
the same information except
that we're looking at
the categorization problem now.
So we assume that if theta i
represents category i accurately,
that means the word distribution
characterizes the content of
documents in category i accurately.
Then, what we can do is precisely
like what we did for text clustering.
Namely we're going to assign
document d to the category
that has the highest probability
of generating this document.
In other words, we're going to maximize
this posterior probability as well.
And this is related to the prior and
the [INAUDIBLE] as you have
seen on the previous slide.
And so, naturally we can decompose
this [INAUDIBLE] into
a product as you see here.
Now, here, I change the notation so
that we will write down the product as
product of all the words
in the vocabulary, and
even though the document
doesn't contain all the words.
And the product is still accurately
representing the product
of all the words in the document
because of this count here.
When a word,
it doesn't occur in the document.
The count would be 0, so
this time will just disappear.
So if actively we'll just have the product
over other words in the document.
So basically, with Naive Bayes Classifier,
we're going to score each category for
the document by this function.
Now, you may notice that here it involves
a product of a lot of small probabilities.
And this can cause and the four problem.
So one way to solve the problem is
thru take logarithm of this function,
which it doesn't changes all
the often these categories.
But will helps us preserve precision.
And so, this is often the function
that we actually use to
score each category and
then we're going to choose
the category that has the highest
score by this function.
So this is called an Naive Bayes
Classifier, now the keyword base is
understandable because we are applying
a base rule here when we go from
the posterior probability of the topic to
a product of the likelihood and the prior.
Now, it's also called a naive because
we've made an assumption that every word
in the document is generated
independently, and this is indeed a naive
assumption because in reality they're
not generating independently.
Once you see some word,
then other words will more likely occur.
For example,
if you have seen a word like a text.
Than that mixed category,
they see more clustering more likely to
appear than if you have not the same text.
But this assumption allows
us to simplify the problem.
And it's actually quite effective for
many text categorization tasks.
But you should know that
this kind of model doesn't
have to make this assumption.
We could for example, assume that
words may be dependent on each other.
So that would make it a bigram analogy
model or a trigram analogy model.
And of course you can even use a mixture
model to model what the document looks
like in each category.
So in nature, they will be all using
base rule to do classification.
But the actual generating model for
documents in each category can vary.
And here, we just talk about very
simple case perhaps, the simplest case.
So now the question is,
how can we make sure theta i
actually represents category i accurately?
Now in clustering,
we learned that this category i or
what are the distributions for
category i from the data.
But in our case,
what can we do to make sure
this theta i represents indeed category i.
Well if you think about the question, and
you likely come up with the idea
of using the training data.
Indeed in the textbook,
we typically assume that there
is training data available and
those are the documents that unknown
to have generator from which category.
In other words, these are the documents
with known categories assigned and
of course human experts must do that.
In here, you see that T1
represents the set of documents
that are known to have
the generator from category 1.
And T2 represents the documents
that are known to have been
generated from category 2, etc.
Now if you look at this picture,
you'll see that the model
here is really a simplified
unigram language model.
It's no longer mixed modal, why?
Because we already know which distribution
has been used to generate which documents.
There's no uncertainty here, there's
no mixing of different categories here.
So the estimation problem of
course would be simplified.
But in general,
you can imagine what we want to do is
estimate these probabilities
that I marked here.
And what other probability is that we have
to estimate it in order to do relation.
Well there are two kinds.
So one is the prior,
the probability of theta i and
this indicates how popular
each category is or
how likely will it have observed
the document in that category.
The other kind is
the water distributions and
we want to know what words have high
probabilities for each category.
So the idea then is to just
use observe the training data
to estimate these two probabilities.
And in general, we can do this
separately for the different categories.
That's just because these documents
are known to be generated
from a specific category.
So once we know that,
it's in some sense irrelevant of what
other categories we are also dealing with.
So now this is a statistical
estimation problem.
We have observed some
data from some model and
we want to guess
the parameters of this model.
We want to take our best
guess of the parameters.
And this is a problem that we have seen
also several times in this course.
Now, if you haven't thought
about this problem,
haven't seen life based classifier.
It would be very useful for
you to pause the video for a moment and
to think about how to solve this problem.
So let me state the problem again.
So let's just think about with category 1,
we know there is one word of distribution
that has been used to generate documents.
And we generate each word in the document
independently, and we know that we have
observed a set of n sub 1
documents in the set of Q1.
These documents have been all
generated from category 1.
Namely have been all generated
using this same word distribution.
Now the question is,
what would be your guess or
estimate of the probability of
each word in this distribution?
And what would be your guess of
the entire probability of this category?
Of course,
this singular probability depends on
how likely are you to see
documents in other categories?
So think for a moment, how do you
use all this training data including
all these documents that are known
to be in these k categories,
to estimate all these parameters?
Now, if you spend some time
to think about this and
it would help you understand
the following few slides.
So do spend some time to make sure that
you can try to solve this problem, or
do you best to solve the problem yourself.
Now if you have thought about and
then you will realize the following to it.
First, what's the bases for estimating the
prior or the probability of each category.
Well this has to do with whether you
have observed a lot of documents
form that category.
Intuitively, you have seen a lot
of documents in sports and
very few in medical science.
Then you guess is that the probability
of the sports category is larger or
your prior on the category
would be larger.
And what about the basis for estimating
the probability of where each category?
Well the same, and you'll be just
assuming that words that are observed
frequently in the documents that are known
to be generated from a category will
likely have a higher probability.
And that's just a maximum
Naive Bayes made of.
Indeed, that's what we can do, so this
made the probability of which category and
to answer the question,
which category is most popular?
Then we can simply normalize,
the count of documents in each category.
So here you see N sub i denotes
the number of documents in each category.
And we simply just normalize these
counts to make this a probability.
In other words, we make this
probability proportional to the size
of training intercept in each category
that's a size of the set t sub i.
Now what about the word distribution?
Well, we do the same.
Again this time we can do this for
each category.
So let's say,
we're considering category i or theta i.
So which word has a higher probability?
Well, we simply count the word occurrences
in the documents that are known
to be generated from theta i.
And then we put together all
the counts of the same word in the set.
And then we just normalize these
counts to make this distribution
of all the words make all
the probabilities off these words to 1.
So in this case, you're going to see this
is a proportional through the count of
the word in the collection of
training documents T sub i and
that's denoted by c of w and T sub i.
Now, you may notice that we
often write down probable
estimate in the form of being
proportional for certain numbers.
And this is often sufficient,
because we have some constraints
on these distributions.
So the normalizer is
dictated by the constraint.
So in this case, it will be useful for
you to think about
what are the constraints on these
two kinds of probabilities?
So once you figure out
the answer to this question, and
you will know how to
normalize these accounts.
And so this is a good exercise to
work on if it's not obvious to you.
There is another issue in
Naive Bayes which is a smoothing.
In fact the smoothing is a general problem
in older estimate of language morals.
And this has to do with,
what would happen if you have
observed a small amount of data?
So smoothing is an important technique
to address that outsmarts this.
In our case, the training data can be
small and when the data set is small when
we use maximum likely estimator we often
face the problem of zero probability.
That means if an event is not observed
then the estimated
probability would be zero.
In this case, if we have not seen
a word in the training documents for
let's say, category i.
Then our estimator would be zero for the
probability of this one in this category,
and this is generally not accurate.
So we have to do smoothing to make
sure it's not zero probability.
The other reason for smoothing is that
this is a way to bring prior knowledge,
and this is also generally true for
a lot of situations of smoothing.
When the data set is small,
we tend to rely on some prior
knowledge to solve the problem.
So in this case our [INAUDIBLE] says that
no word should have zero probability.
So smoothing allows us to inject
these to prior initial that no
order has a real zero probability.
There is also a third reason which
us sometimes not very obvious, but
we explain that in a moment.
And that is to help achieve
discriminative weighting of terms.
And this is also called IDF weighting,
inverse document frequency weighting that
you have seen in mining word relations.
So how do we do smoothing?
Well in general we add pseudo
counts to these events,
we'll make sure that no event has 0 count.
So one possible way of smoothing
the probability of the category
is to simply add a small non active
constant delta to the count.
Let's pretend that every category
has actually some extra number of
documents represented by delta.
And in the denominator we also add
a k multiplied by delta because
we want the probability to some to 1.
So in total we've added delta k times
because we have a k categories.
Therefore in this sum,
we have to also add k multiply by
delta as a total pseudocount
that we add up to the estimate.
Now, it's interesting to think
about the influence of that data,
obvious data is a smoothing
parameter here.
Meaning that the larger data is and
the more we will do smoothing and
that means we'll more
rely on pseudocounts.
And we might indeed ignore the actual
counts if they are delta is
set to infinity.
Imagine what would happen if there
are approaches positively to infinity?
Well, we are going to say every category
has an infinite amount of documents.
And then there's no distinction to them so
it become just a uniform.
What if delta is 0?
Well, we just go back to the original
estimate based on the observed training
data to estimate to estimate
the probability of each category.
Now we can do the same for
the word distribution.
But in this case,
sometimes we find it useful
to use a nonuniform seudocount for
the word.
So here you'll see we'll add
a pseudocounts to each word and
that's mule multiplied
by the probability of
the word given by a background
language model, theta sub b.
Now that background model in
general can be estimated by using
a logic collection of tests.
Or in this case we will use the whole
set of all the training data to
estimate this background language model.
But we don't have to use this one,
we can use larger test data that
are available from somewhere else.
Now if we use such a background
language model that has pseudocounts,
we'll find that some words will
receive more pseudocounts.
So what are those words?
Well those are the common words
because they get a high probability by
the background average model.
So the pseudocounts added for
such words will be higher.
Real words on the other hand
will have smaller pseudocounts.
Now this addition of background
model would cause a nonuniform
smoothing of these word distributions.
We're going to bring the probability of
those common words to a higher level,
because of the background model.
Now this helps make the difference
of the probability of
such words smaller across categories.
Because every category has some help
from the background four words, and
I get the, a,
which have high probabilities.
Therefore, it's not always so
important that each category
has documents that contain a lot
of occurrences of such words or
the estimate is more influenced
by the background model.
And the consequence is that
when we do categorization,
such words tend not to influence
the decision that much
as words that have small probabilities
from the background language model.
Those words don't get some help
So the difference would be primary because
of the differences of the occurrences
in the training documents
in different categories.
We also see another smoothing parameter
mu here, which controls the amount of
smoothing and just like a delta does for
the other probability.
And you can easily understand why we
add mu to the denominator, because that
represents the sum of all the pseudocounts
that we add for all the words.
So view is also a non
negative constant and
it's [INAUDIBLE] set to control smoothing.
Now there are some interesting
special cases to think about as well.
First, let's think about when mu
approaches infinity what would happen?
Well in this case
the estimate would approach
to the background language model we'll
attempt to the background language model.
So we will bring every word distribution
to the same background language model and
that essentially remove the difference
between these categories.
Obviously, we don't want to do that.
The other special case is the thing
about the background model and
suppose, we actually set
the two uniform distribution.
And let's say,
1 over the size of the vocabulary.
So each one has the same probability,
then this smoothing formula is
going to be very similar to the one
on the top when we add delta.
It's because we're going to add
a constant pseudocounts to every word.
So in general,
in Naive Bayes categorization we
have to do such a small thing.
And then once we have these probabilities,
then we can compute the score for
each category.
For a document and
then choose the category where it was
the highest score as we discussed earlier.
Now, it's useful to
further understand whether
the Naive Bayes scoring
function actually makes sense.
So to understand that, and also to
understand why adding a background model
will actually achieve the effect of IDF
weighting and to penalize common words.
So suppose we have just two categories and
we're going to score based on
their ratio of probability, right?
So this is the.
Lets say this is our scoring function for
two categories, right?
So, this is a score of a document for
these two categories.
And we're going to score based
on this probability ratio.
So if the ratio is larger,
then it means it's more
likely to be in category one.
So the larger the score is the more likely
the document is in category one.
So by using Bayes' rule,
we can write down this ratio as follows,
and you have seen this before.
Now, we generally take logarithm of this
ratio, and to avoid small probabilities.
And this would then give us this
formula in the second line.
And here we see something
really interesting,
because this is our scoring function for
deciding between the two categories.
And if you look at this function,
we'll see it has several parts.
The first part here is actually
log of probability ratio.
And so this is a category bias.
It doesn't really depend on the document.
It just says which category is more
likely and then we would then favor
this category slightly, right?
So, the second part has a sum
of all the words, right?
So, these are the words that
are observed in the document but
in general we can consider all
the words in the vocabulary.
So here we're going to
collect the evidence
about which category is more likely,
right?
So inside of the sum you can see
there is product of two things.
The first, is a count of the word.
And this count of the word serves as
a feature to represent the document.
And this is what we can
collect from document.
The second part is
the weight of this feature,
here it's the weight on which word, right?
This weight tells us to
what extent observing
this word helps contribute in our decision
to put this document in category one.
Now remember,
the higher the scoring function is,
the more likely it's in category one.
Now if you look at this ratio, basically,
sorry this weight it's basically based
on the ratio of the probability of the
word from each of the two distributions.
Essentially we're comparing
the probability of the word from the two
distributions.
And if it's a higher according to theta 1,
then according to theta 2,
then this weight would be positive.
And therefore it means when
we observe such a word,
we will say that it's more
likely to be from category one.
And the more we observe such a word,
the more likely the document
will be classified as theta 1.
If, on the other hand,
the probability of the word from
theta 1 is smaller than the probability
of the word from theta 2,
then you can see that
this word is negative.
Therefore, this is negative evidence for
supporting category one.
That means the more we
observe such a word,
the more likely the document
is actually from theta 2.
So this formula now makes a little sense,
right?
So we're going to aggregate all
the evidence from the document,
we take a sum of all the words.
We can call this the features
that we collected from the document
that would help us make the decision.
And then each feature has
a weight that tells us how
does this feature support category one or
just support category two.
And this is estimated as the log of
probability ratio here in naïve Bayes.
And then finally we have
this constant of bias here.
So that formula actually
is a formula that can
be generalized to accommodate
more features and
that's why I have introduce
some other symbols here.
To introduce beta 0 to denote the Bayes
and fi to denote the each feature and
beta sub i to denote
the weight on each feature.
Now we do this generalisation,
what we see is that in
general we can represent
the document by feature vector fi,
here of course in this case
fi is the count of a word.
But in general, we can put any features
that we think are relevant for
categorization.
For example, document length or
font size or
count of other patterns in the document.
And then our scoring function can be
defined as a sum of a constant beta 0 and
the sum of the feature
weights of all the features.
So if each f sub i is a feature
value then we multiply the value
by the corresponding weight,
beta sub i, and we just take the sum.
And this is the aggregate of all evidence
that we can collect from all these
features.
And of course there are parameters here.
So what are the parameters?
Well, these are the betas.
These betas are weights.
And with a proper setting of the weights,
then we can expect such a scoring function
to work well to classify documents,
just like in the case of naive Bayes.
We can clearly see naive Bayes
classifier as a special case of
this general classifier.
Actually, this general form is very close
to a classifier called a logistical
regression, and this is actually one
of those conditional approaches or
discriminative approaches
to classification.
And we're going to talk more
about such approaches later, but
here I want you to note that
there is a strong connection,
a close connection between
the two kinds of approaches.
And this slide shows how naive Bayes
classifier can be connected to
a logistic regression.
And you can also see that in
discriminative classifiers
that tend to use more
general form on the bottom,
we can accommodate more
features to solve the problem.
[MUSIC]