[SOUND] This lecture is
a continued discussion of
Discriminative Classifiers for
Text Categorization.
So, in this lecture,
we're going to introduce, yet
another Discriminative Classifier called
the Support Vector Machine or SVM.
Which is a very popular
classification method and
it has been also shown to be effective for
text categorization.
So to introduce this classifier,
let's also think about the simple
case of two categories.
We have two topic categories,
01 and 02 here.
And we want to classify documents
into these two categories and
we're going to represent again
a document by a feature factor x here.
Now, the idea of this classifier is
to design also a linear separator
here that you'll see and
it's very similar to what you have
seen not just for regression, right?
And we're going to do also say
that if the sign of this function
value is positive then we're going to
say the objective is in category one.
Otherwise, we're going to
say it's in category 2.
So that makes 0 that is the decision
boundary between the few categories.
So, in generally hiding
marginal space such as, 0.
corresponds to a hyper plain.
Now I've shown you a simple case of two
dimensional space it was just X1 and
X2 and this case this corresponds
to a line that you can see here.
So, this is a line defined by
just three parameters here,
beta zero, beta one, and beta two.
Now, this line is heading
in this direction so
it shows that as we increase X1,
X2 will also increase.
So we know that beta one and beta two have
different assigns, one is negative and
the other is positive.
So let's just assume that beta one is
negative and beta two Is positive.
Now, it's interesting to examine, then,
the data instances on
the two sides of the slide.
So, here, the data instance are visualized
as circles for one class and
diamonds for the other class.
Now, one question is to take a point
like this one and to ask the question
what's the value of this expression, or
this classifier, for this data point?
So what do you think?
Basically, we're going to evaluate
its value by using this function.
And as we said, if this value's positive
we're going to say this is in category
one, and if it's negative,
it's going to be in category two.
Intuitively, this line separates these two
categories, so we expect the points on
one side would be positive and the points
on the other side would be negative.
Our question is under the assumption
that I just mentioned,
let's examine a particular
point like this one.
So what do you think is
the sine of this expression?
Well, to examine the sine we can
simply look at this expression here.
And we can compare this with let's say,
value on the line, let's see,
compare this with this point.
While they have identical X1, but
then one has a higher value for X2.
Now, let's look at the sin
of the coefficient for X2.
Well, we know this is a positive.
So, what that means is
that the f value for
this point should be higher
than the f value for
this point on the line that means
this will be positive, right?
So we know in general of
all points on this side,
the function's value will be positive and
you can also verify all the points
on this side will be negative.
And so this is how this kind
of linear classifier or
linear separator can then separate
the points in the two categories.
So, now the natural question is,
which linear separator is the best?
Now, I've get you one line here
that can separate the two classes.
And this line, of course, is determined
by the vector beta, the coefficients.
Different coefficients will
give us different lines.
So, we could imagine there are other
lines that can do the same job.
Gamma, for example,
could give us another line that counts
a separator to these instances.
Of course, there are also lines that won't
separate to them and those are bad lines.
But, the question is,
when we have multiple lines that can
separate both clauses,
which align the best?
In fact, you can imagine, there are many
different ways of choosing the line.
So, the logistical regression classifier
that you have seen earlier actually uses
some criteria to determine where this line
should be and so linear separate as well.
And uses a conditional likelihood
on the training that it determines
which line is the best.
But in SVM we're going to
look at another criteria for
determining which line is the best.
And this time,
the criteria is more tied to
the classification arrow as you will see.
So, the basic idea is to choose
the separator to maximize the margin.
So what is a margin?
So, I choose some dotted
lines here to indicate
the boundaries of those
data points in each class.
And the margin is simply
the distance between the line,
the separator, and
the closest point from each class.
So you can see the margin of this
side is as I've shown here and
you can also define
the margin on the other side.
In order for
the separator to maximize the margin,
it has to be kind of in the middle
of the two boundaries and
you don't want this separator to
be very close to one side, and
that in intuition makes a lot of sense.
So this is basic idea of SVM.
We're going to choose a linear
separator to maximize the margin.
Now on this slide,
I've also changed the notation so
that I'm not going to use beta
to denote the parameters.
But instead, I'm going to use w although
w was used to denote the words before so
don't be confused here.
W here is actually a width,
a certain width.
So I'm also using lowercase b to
denote the beta 0, a biased constant.
And there are instances do
represent that as x and
I also use the vector form
of multiplication here.
So we see a transpose of w vector
multiply by the future vector.
So b is a bias constant and w is a set of
weights with one way for each feature.
We have m features and
so we have m weights and
that will represent as a vector.
And similarly, the data instance here,
the text object,
is represented by also a feature
vector of the same number of elements.
Xi is a feature value.
For example, word count and
you can verify, when we.
Multiply these two vectors together,
take the dot product,
we get the same form of the linear
separator as you have seen before.
It's just a different way
of representing this.
Now I use this way so that it's
more consistent with what notations
people usually use when
they talk about SVM.
This way you can better connect the slides
with some other readings you might do.
Okay, so when we maximize
the margins of a separator,
it just means the boundary of
the separator is only determined by
a few data points, and these are the data
points that we call support vectors.
So here illustrated are two support
vectors for one class and two for
the other class.
And these quotas define
the margin basically, and
you can imagine once we know which
are supportive vectors then this
center separator line will
be determined by them.
So the other data points actually
don't really matter that much.
And you can see if you change the other
data points it won't really affect
the margin, so
the separator will stay the same.
Mainly affected by
the the support vector machines.
Sorry, it's mainly affected
by the support vectors and
that's why it's called
a support vector machine.
Okay, so now the next question is,
of course,
how can we set it up to optimize the line?
How can we actually find the line or
the separator?
Now this is equivalent to
finding values for w and
b, because they will determine
where exactly the separator is.
So in the simplest case, the linear SVM
is just a simple optimization problem.
So again, let's recall that our classifier
is such a linear separator, where we
have weights for all the features, and the
main goal is remove these weights w and b.
And the classifier will say X is in
category theta 1 if it's positive.
Otherwise, it's going to say
it's in the other category.
So this is our assumption, our setup.
So in the linear SVM,
we are going to then seek these parameter
values to optimize the margins and
then the training error.
The training data would be basically
like in other classifiers.
We have a set of training points
where we know the x vector, and
then we also know the corresponding label,
y i.
And here we define y i as two values, but
these values are not 0, 1 as you
have seen before, but rather -1 and
positive 1, and they're corresponding to
these two categories, as I've shown here.
Now you might wonder why we
don't define them as 0 and
1 instead of having -1, 1.
And this is purely for mathematical
convenience, as you will see in a moment.
So the goal of optimization first is
to make sure the labeling of
training data is all correct.
So that just means if y i,
the norm label for instance x i,
is 1, we would like this
classified value to be large.
And here we just choose
a threshold of 1 here.
But if you use another threshold,
you can easily fit that constant
into the parameter values b and
w to make the right-hand side just 1.
Now if, on the other hand, y i is -1,
that means it's in a different class,
then we want this classifier
to give us a very small value,
in fact a negative value, and we want this
value to be less than or equal to -1.
Now these are the two different instances,
different kinds of cases.
How can we combine them together?
Now this is where it's convenient
when we have chosen y i as -1 for
the other category,
because it turns out that we can either
combine the two into one constraint.
y i multiplied by the classifier value
must be larger than or equal to 1.
And obviously when y i is just 1,
you see this is the same as
the constraint on the left-hand side.
But when y i is -1, you also see that this
is equivalent to the other inequality.
So this one actually captures both
constraints in a unified way,
and that's a convenient way of
capturing these constraints.
What's our second goal?
Well, that's to maximize margin, so
we want to ensure that separator
can do well on the training data.
But then, among all the cases
where we can separate the data,
we also would like to choose the separator
that has the largest margin.
Now the margin can be assumed to be
related to the magnitude of the weight.
And so
w transform multiplied by w would give
us basically the sum of
squares of all those weights.
So to have a small value for
this expression,
it means all the w i's must be small.
So we've just assumed that
we have a constraint for
getting the data on the training
set to be classified correctly.
Now we also have the objective that's
tied into a maximization of margin,
and this is simply to minimize
w transpose multiplied by w,
and we often denote this by phi of w.
So now you can see this is
basically a optimization problem.
We have some variables to optimize,
and these are the weights and
b and we have some constraints.
These are linear constraints and
the objective function is
a quadratic function of the weights.
So this a quadratic program
with linear constraints,
and there are standard algorithm that
are variable for solving this problem.
And once we solve the problem
we obtain the weights w and b.
And then this would give us
a well-defined classifier.
So we can then use this classifier
to classify any new text objects.
Now the previous formulation did not
allow any error in the classification,
but sometimes the data may not
be linear to the separator.
That means that they may not
look as nice as you have seen on
the previous slide where a line
can separate all of them.
And what would happen if
we allowed some errors?
Well, the principle can stay.
We want to minimize the training error but
try to also maximize the margin.
But in this case we have a soft margin,
because the data points may
not be completely separable.
So it turns out that we can easily
modify SVM to accommodate this.
So what you see here is very similar
to what you have seen before,
but we have introduced
the extra variable xi i.
And we in fact will have one for
each data instance, and
this is going to model the error
that we allow for each instance.
But the optimization problem
would be very similar.
So specifically,
you will see we have added something
to the optimization problem.
First we have added some
error to the constraint so
that now we allow a Allow the classifier
to make some mistakes here.
So, this Xi i is allowed an error.
If we set Xi i to 0, then we go
back to the original constraint.
We want every instance to
be classified accurately.
But, if we allow this to be non-zero,
then we allow some errors here.
In fact, if the length of the Xi i is very
large, the error can be very, very large.
So naturally,
we don't want this to happen.
So we want to then also
minimize this Xi i.
So, because Xi i needs to be minimized
in order to control the error.
And so, as a result,
in the objective function,
we also add more to the original one,
which is only W,
by basically ensuring that we not
only minimize the weights, but
also minimize the errors, as you see here.
Here we simply take a sum
over all the instances.
Each one has a Xi i to model
the error allowed for that instance.
And when we combine them together,
we basically want to minimize
the errors on all of them.
Now you see there's a parameter C here,
and that's a constant to control
the trade-off between minimizing
the errors and maximizing the margin.
If C is set to zero, you can see,
we go back to the original object function
where we only maximize the margin.
We don't really optimize
the training errors and
then Xi i can be set to a very large value
to make the constraints easy to satisfy.
That's not very good of course, so
C should be set to a non-zero value,
a positive value.
But when C is set to a very,
very large value,
we'll see the object of the function will
be dominated mostly by the training errors
and so the optimization of margin
will then play a secondary role.
So if that happens, what would happen is
then we will try to do our best to
minimize the training errors, but
then we're not going to
take care of the margin and
that affects the generalization factors
of the classify for future data.
So it's also not good.
So in particular, this parameter C
has to be actually set carefully.
And this is just like in the case of
k-nearest neighbor where you need
to optimize a number of neighbors.
Here you need to optimize the C.
And this is, in general,
also achievable by doing cross-validation.
Basically, you look at
the empirical data and
see what value C should be set to in
order to optimize the performance.
Now with this modification,
the problem is still quadratic programming
with linear constraints so the optimizing
algorithm can be actually applied to solve
this different version of the program.
Again, once we have obtained
the weights and the bias,
then we can have classifier that's
ready for classifying new objects.
So that's the basic idea of SVM.
So to summarize the text
categorization methods,
where we introduce the many methods,
and some are generative models.
Some are discriminative methods.
And these tend to perform
similarly when optimized.
So there's still no clear winner,
although each one has its pros and cons.
And the performance might also
vary on different data sets for
different problems.
And one reason is also because the feature
representation is very critical
and these methods all require
effective feature representation.
And to design an effective feature set,
we need domain knowledge and humans
definitely play an important role here,
although there are new
machine learning methods and
algorithm representation learning
that can help with learning features.
And another common thing
is that they might
be performing similarly on the data set,
but with different mistakes.
And so,
their performance might be similar, but
then the mistakes they
make might be different.
So that means it's useful to
compare different methods for
a particular problem and
then maybe combine multiple methods
because this can improve the robustness
and they won't make the same mistakes.
So assemble approaches that
would combine different
methods tend to be more robust and
can be useful in practice.
Most techniques that we introduce
use the supervised machine learning,
which is a very general method.
So that means that these methods can
be actually applied to any text or
categorization problem.
As long as we have humans to help
annotate some training data sets and
design features, then supervising machine
learning and all these classifiers
can be easily applied to those problems
to solve the categorization problem to
allow us to characterize content
of text concisely with categories.
Or to predict the sum
properties of real world
variables that are associated
with text data.
The computers, of course, here are trying
to optimize the combinations of
the features provided by human.
And as I said, there are many
different ways of combining them and
they also optimize different object or
functions.
But in order to achieve good performance,
they all require effective features and
also plenty of training data.
So as a general rule, and if you can
improve the feature representation,
and then provide more training data,
then you can generally do better.
Performance is often much more
affected by the effectiveness of
features than by the choice
of specific classifiers.
So feature design tends to be more
important than the choice of specific
classifier.
So, how do we design effective features?
Well, unfortunately,
this is very application-specific.
So there's no really much
general thing to say here.
But we can do some analysis of
the categorization problem and
try to understand what kind of features
might help us distinguish categories.
And in general, we can use a lot of domain
knowledge to help us design features.
And another way to figure out
the effective features is
to do error analysis on
the categorization results.
You could, for example,
look at which category tends to be
confused with which other categories.
And you can use a confusion matrix
to examine the errors systematically
across categories.
And then,
you can look into specific instances to
see why the mistake has been made and
what features can prevent the mistake.
And this can allow you to obtain
insights for design new features.
So error analysis is very
important in general, and
that's where you can get the insights
about your specific problem.
And finally, we can leverage this
on machine learning techniques.
So, for example, feature selection is
a technique that we haven't really talked
about, but is very important.
And it has to do with trying to select the
most useful features before you actually
train a full classifier.
Sometimes training a classifier will also
help you identify which features have high
values.
There are also other ways
to ensure this sparsity.
Of the model,
meaning to recognize the widths.
For example, the SVM actually tries
to minimize the weights on features.
But you can further force some features,
force to use only a small
number of features.
There are also techniques for
dimension reduction.
And that's to reduce a high dimensional
feature space into a low dimensional
space typically by clustering
of features in various ways.
So metrics factorization
has been used to do
such a job, and this is some of the
techniques are actually very similar to
the talking models that we'll discuss.
So talking morals like psa or
lda can actually help us reduce
the dimension of features.
Like imagine the words
our original feature.
But the can be matched to the topic
space .Let's say we have k topics.
So a document can now be represented
as a vector of just k values
corresponding to the topics.
So we can let each topic define one
dimension, so we have a k dimensional
space instead of the original high
dimensional space corresponding to words.
And this is often another way
to learn effective features.
Especially, we could also use the
categories to supervise the learning of
such low dimensional structures.
And so, the original worth features
can be also combined with such
amazing dimension features or
lower dimensional space features
to provide a multi resolution
which is often very useful.
Deep learning is a new technique that
has been developed the machine learning.
It's particularly useful for
learning representations.
So deep learning refers to deep neural
network, it's another kind of classifier,
where you can have intermediate
features embedded in the models.
That it's highly non-linear transpire, and
some recent events that's allowed us to
train such a complex network effectively.
And the technique has been shown to be
quite effective for speech recognition,
computer reasoning, and
recently has been applied to text as well.
It has shown some promise.
And one important advantage
of this approach in
relationship with the featured design,
is that they can
learn intermediate replantations or
compound the features automatically.
And this is very valuable for
learning effective replantation,
for text recalibration.
Although in text domain, because words are
exemplary representation of text content,
because these are human's imaging for
communication.
And they are generally sufficient for
For representing content for many tasks.
If there's a need for
some new representation,
people would have invented a new word.
So because of this we think
of value of deep learning for
text processing tends to be lower than for
[INAUDIBLE].
And the speech revenue where
they are anchored corresponding
where the design that worked as features.
But people only still very promising for
learning effective features especially for
complicated tasks.
Like a analysis it has
been shown to be effective
because it can provide that
goes beyond that of words.
Now regarding the training examples.
It's generally hard to get a lot of
training examples because it involves
human labor.
But there are also some
ways to help with this.
So one is to assume in some low quality
training examples can also be used.
So, those can be called
pseudo training examples.
For example, if you take reviews from the
internet, they might have overall ratings.
So, to train a of categorizer,
meaning we want to positive or negative.
And categorize these reviews
into these two categories.
Then we could assume five star reviews
are all positive training samples.
One star are negative.
But of course,
sometimes even five star reviews will also
mention negative opinions so the training
sample is not all of that high quality,
but they can still be useful.
Another idea is to exploit
the unlabeled data and
there are techniques called
the semi-supervised machine
learning techniques that can allow you to
combine labeled data with unlabeled data.
So, in other case it's easy to see
the next model can be used For
both text plus read and
the categorization.
So you can imagine, if you have a lot of
unlabeled text data for categorization,
then you can actually do clustering
on these text data, learn categories.
And then try to somehow
align these categories.
With the categories defined
by the training data,
where we already know which
documents are in which category.
So you can in fact use the Algorithm
to actually combine both.
That would allow you essentially also
pick up useful words and label the data.
You can think of this in another way.
Basically, we can use let's say a to
classify all of the unlabeled text
documents, and then we're going to
assume the high confidence Classification
results are actually liable.
Then you suddenly have more training
data because from the enabler that we
now know some are labeled as category one,
some are labeled as category two.
All though the label is not
completely reliable But
then they can still be useful.
So let's assume they are actually training
label examples, and then we combine them
with true training examples through
improved categorization method.
And so this idea is very powerful.
When the enabled data and
the training data are very different, and
we might need to use other advanced
machine learning techniques
called domain adaptation or
transfer learning.
This is when we can
Borrow some training examples from
a related problem that may be different.
Or, from a categorization password
that follow very different distribution
from what we are working on.
But basically,
when the two domains are very different,
then we need to be careful and
not overfit the training domain.
But yet, we can still want to use some
signals from the related training data.
So for example,
training categorization on news might not
give you Effective plus y for
class vine topics and tweets.
But you can still learn something from
news to help look at writing tweets.
So there are mission learning techniques
that can help you do that effectively.
Here's a suggested reading where you
can find more details about some
more of the methods is
that we have covered.
[MUSIC]