[SOUND]
This
lecture is about the discriminative
classifiers for text categorization.
In this lecture we're going to
continue talking about how to
do text categorization and
cover discriminative approaches.
This is a slide that you have seen from
the discussion of Naive Bayes Classifier,
where we have shown that although
Naive Bayes Classifier tries to model
the generation of text data, from each
categories, we can actually use Bayes'
rule to eventually rewrite the scoring
function as you see on this slide.
And this scoring function is basically
a weighted combination of a lot
of word features, where the feature values
are word counts, and the feature weights
are the log of probability ratios of
the word given by two distributions here.
Now this kind of scoring function
can be actually a general scoring
function where we can in general
present text data as a feature vector.
Of course the features don't
have to be all the words.
Their features can be other
signals that we want to use.
And we mentioned that this is precisely
similar to logistic regression.
So, in this lecture we're going to
introduce some discriminative classifiers.
They try to model
the conditional distribution of
labels given the data directly
rather than using Bayes' rule
to compute that interactively
as we have seen in naive Bayes.
So the general idea of logistic
regression is to model
the dependency of a binary
response variable Y
on some predictors that are denoted as X.
So here we have also changed the notation
to X for future values.
You may recall in the previous
slides we have used
FI to represent the future values.
And here we use the notation of X factor,
which is more common when we introduce
such discriminative algorithms.
So, X is our input.
It's a vector with n features and
each feature has a value x sub i here.
And I will go with a model that dependency
of this binary response variable of
these features.
So in our categorization problem when
I have two categories theta 1 and
theta 2, and we can use the Y value to
denote the two categories when Y is 1,
it means the category of the document,
the first class, is theta 1.
Now, the goal here is the model, the
conditional property of Y given X directly
as opposed to model of the generation of
X and Y as in the case of Naive Bayes.
And another advantage of this
kind of approach is that
it would allow many other features
than words to be used in this vector
since we're not modeling
the generation of this vector.
And we can plug in any
signals that we want.
So this is potentially advantageous for
doing text categorization.
So more specifically,
in logistic regression,
assume the functional form of Y
depending on X is the following.
And this is very closely
related to the log
odds that I introduced in the Naive Bayes
or log of probability ratio
of the two categories that you
have seen on the previous slide.
So this is what I meant.
So in the case of Naive Bayes,
we compute this by using those words and
eventually we have reached
a formula that looks like this.
But here we actually
would assume explicitly
that we with the model our
probability of Y given X
directly as a function of these features.
So, most specifically we assume that the
ratio of the probability of Y equals 1 and
the probability of Y equals
0 is a function of X.
All right, so it's a function of x and
it's a linear combination of these feature
values controlled by theta values.
And it seems we know that
the probability of Y equals zero
is one minus probability
of Y equals one and
this can be also written in this way.
So this is a log out ratio here.
And so in logistic regression,
we're basically assuming that
the probability of Y equals 1.
Okay my X is dependent on this linear
combination of all these features.
So it's just one of the many possible
ways, assuming that the dependency.
But this particular form
has been quite useful and
it also has some nice properties.
So if we rewrite this equation to actually
express the probability of Y given X.
In terms of X by getting rid of
the logarithm we get this functional form,
and this is called a logistical function.
It's a transformation of X into Y,
as you see
on the right side here, so
that the X's will be map
into a range of values from 0 to 1.0,
you can see.
And that's precisely what we want
since we have a probability here.
And the function form looks like this.
So this is the basic idea
of logistic regression.
And it's a very useful classifier that
can be used to do a lot of classification
tasks including text categorization.
So as in all cases of model we would be
interested in estimating the parameters.
And in fact in all of the machine running
programs, once you set up with the model,
set up object and
function to model the file,
then the next step is to
compute the parameter values.
In general, we're going to adjust
to these parameter values.
Optimize the performance of
classify on the training data.
So in our case just assume we have
the training data here, xi and yi, and
each pair is basically a future vector
of x and a known label for that x.
Y is either 1 or 0.
So in our case we are interested
maximize this conditional likelihood.
The conditional likelihood here is
basically to model why
given observe the x,
so it's not like a moderate x, but
rather we're going to model this.
Note that this is a conditional
probability of Y given X and
this is also precisely what we wanted For
classification.
Now so the likelihood function would be
just a product of all the training cases.
And in each case,
this is the model of the probability of
observing this particular training case.
So given a particular Xi, how likely
we are to observe the corresponding Yi?
Of course, Yi could be 1 or
0, and in fact,
the function found here would vary
depending on whether Yi is 1 or 0.
If it's a 1, we'll be taking this form.
And that's basically the logistic
regression function.
But what about this, if it's 0?
Well, if it's 0, then we have to use
a different form, and that's this one.
Now, how do we get this one?
Well, that's just a 1 minus
the probability of Y=1, right?
And you can easily see this.
Now the key point in here is that the
function form here depends on the observer
Yi, if it's a 1,
it has a different form than when it's 0.
And if you think about when we
want to maximize this probability,
we're basically going to want this
probability to be as high as possible.
When the label is 1, that means
the document is in probability 1.
But if the document is not,
we're going to maximize this value,
and what's going to happen is
actually to make this value as
small as possible because this sum's 1.
When I maximize this one,
it's equivalent to minimize this one.
So you can see basically, if we maximize
the conditional likelihood, we're going
to basically try to make the prediction on
the training data as accurate as possible.
So as another occasion, when you
compute the maximum likelihood data,
basically you'll find a beta value,
a set of beta values that would
maximize this conditional likelihood.
And this, again, then gives us
a standard optimization problem.
In this case,
it can be also solved in many ways.
Newton's method is a popular
way to solve this problem,
there are other methods as well.
But in the end,
we will look at a set of data values.
Once we have the beta values,
then we have a way to find the scoring
function to help us classify a document.
So what's the function?
Well, it's this one.
See, if we have all the beta values,
are they known?
All we need is to compute the Xi for that
document and then plug in those values.
That will give us an estimated probability
that the document is in category one.
Okay so, so much for
logistical regression.
Let's also introduce another
discriminative classifier
called K-Nearest Neighbors.
Now in general, I should say there
are many such approaches, and
a thorough introduction to all of them is
clearly beyond the scope of this course.
And you should take
a machine learning course or
read more about machine
learning to know about them.
Here, I just want to include the basic
introduction to some of the most commonly
used classifiers, since you might
use them often for text calculation.
So the second classifier is
called K-Nearest Neighbors.
In this approach,
we're going to also estimate
the conditional probability of label
given data, but in a very different way.
So the idea is to keep all
the training examples and
then once we see a text object that we
want to classify, we're going to find
the K examples in the training set and
that are most similar to this text object.
Basically, this is to find
the neighbors of this text objector in
the training data set.
So once we found the neighborhood and
we found the object that are close to the
object we are interested in classifying,
and let's say we have found
the K-Nearest Neighbors.
That's why this method is
called K-Nearest Neighbors.
Then we're going to assign the category
that's most common in these neighbors.
Basically we're going to allow
these neighbors to vote for
the category of the objective that
we're interested in classifying.
Now that means if most of them have
a particular category and it's a category
one, they're going to say this
current object will have category one.
This approach can also be improved by
considering the distance of a neighbor and
of a current object.
Basically, we can assume a closed
neighbor would have more say
about the category of the subject.
So, we can give such a neighbor
more influence on the vote.
And we can take away some of
the votes based on the distances.
But the general idea is look
at the neighborhood, and
then try to assess the category based
on the categories of the neighbors.
Intuitively, this makes a lot of sense.
But mathematically, this can also be
regarded as a way to directly estimate
there's a conditional probability of
label given data, that is p of Y given X.
Now I'm going to explain this intuition in
a moment, but before we proceed, let me
emphasize that we do need a similarity
function here in order for this to work.
Note that in naive base class five,
we did not need a similarity function.
And in logistical regression, we did not
talk about those similarity function
either, but here we explicitly
require a similarity function.
Now this similarity function
actually is a good opportunity for
us to inject any of our
insights about the features.
Basically effective features
are those that would
make the objects that are on the same
category look more similar, but
distinguishing objects
in different categories.
So the design of this similarity function
is closely tied it to the design
of the features in logistical
regression and other classifiers.
So let's illustrate how K-NN works.
Now suppose we have a lot
of training instances here.
And I've colored them differently and
to show just different categories.
Now suppose we have a new object in
the center that we want to classify.
So according to this approach,
you work on finding the neighbors.
Now, let's first think of a special
case of finding just one neighbor,
the closest neighbor.
Now in this case, let's assume the closest
neighbor is the box filled with diamonds.
And so then we're going to say,
well, since this is in this
object that is in category of diamonds,
let's say.
Then we're going to say, well,
we're going to assign the same
category to our text object.
But let's also look at another possibility
of finding a larger neighborhood,
so let's think about the four neighbors.
In this case, we're going to include a lot
of other solid field boxes in red or
pink, right?
So in this case now, we're going to
notice that among the four neighbors,
there are three neighbors
in a different category.
So if we take a vote,
then we'll conclude the object is
actually of a different category.
So this both illustrates how
can nearest neighbor works and
also it illustrates some potential
problems of this classifier.
Basically, the results might
depend on the K and indeed,
k's an important parameter to optimize.
Now, you can intuitively imagine
if we have a lot of neighbors
around this object, and
then we'd be okay because we have
a lot of neighbors who will
help us decide the categories.
But if we have only a few,
then the decision may not be reliable.
So on the one hand,
we want to find more neighbor, right?
And then we have more votes.
But on the other hand, as we try to find
more neighbors we actually could risk
on getting neighbors that are not
really similar to this instance.
They might actually be far away
as you try to get more neighbors.
So although you get more neighbors but
those neighbors aren't necessarily so
helpful because they are not
very similar to the object.
So the parameter still has
to be set empirically.
And typically, you can optimize such
a parameter by using cross validation.
Basically, you're going to separate
your training data into two parts and
then you're going to use one
part to actually help you choose
the parameter k here or some other
parameters in other class files.
And then you're going to assume
this number that works well on your
training that will be actually be
the best for your future data.
So as I mentioned,
K-NN can be actually regarded as estimate
of conditional problem within y given x
an that's why we put this in the category
of discriminative approaches.
So the key assumption that we made in
this approach is that the distribution
of the label given the document
probability a category given for
example probability of theta i
given document d is locally smooth.
And that just means we're going to assume
that this probability is the same for
all the documents in these region R here.
And suppose we draw a neighborhood and
we're going to assume in this neighborhood
since the data instances are very
similar we're going to assume that
the conditional distribution of the label
given the data will be roughly the same.
If these are very different
then we're going to assume that
the probability of c doc given
d would be also similar.
So that's a very key assumption.
And that's actually important assumption
that would allow us to
do a lot of machinery.
But in reality,
whether this is true of course,
would depend on how we define similarity.
Because neighborhood is largely
determined by our similarity function.
If our similarity function captures
objects that do follow similar
distributions then these
assumptions are okay but
if our similarity function could
not capture that, obviously these
assumption would be a problem and
then the classifier would not be accurate.
Okay, let's proceed with these assumption.
Then what we are saying is that,
in order to estimate the probability
of category given a document.
We can try to estimate the probability of
the category given that entire region.
Now, this has a benefit, of course,
of bringing additional data points to
help us estimate this probability.
And so this is precisely the idea of K-NN.
Basically now we can use
the known categories of
all the documents in this region
to estimate this probability.
And I have even given a formula here where
you can see we just count the topics in
this region and then normalize that by the
total number of documents in the region.
So the numerator that you see here,
c of theta i and r,
is a counter of the documents in
region R was category theta i.
Since these are training document and
we know they are categories.
We can simply count how many
times it was since here.
How many times we have the same signs,
etc.
And then the denominator is just
the total number of training
documents in this region.
So this gives us a rough estimate of
which categories most popular in this
neighborhood.
And we are going to assign
the popular category
to our data object since
it falls into this region.
[MUSIC]