[SOUND]
This
lecture is the first one
about the text clustering.
In this lecture, we are going to
talk about the text clustering.
This is a very important technique for
doing topic mining and analysis.
In particular,
in this lecture we're going to start with
some basic questions about the clustering.
And that is, what is text clustering and
why we are interested in text clustering.
In the following lectures, we are going
to talk about how to do text clustering.
How to evaluate the clustering results?
So what is text clustering?
Well, clustering actually is
a very general technique for
data mining as you might have
learned in some other courses.
The idea is to discover natural
structures in the data.
In another words,
we want to group similar objects together.
In our case, these objects are of course,
text objects.
For example, they can be documents,
terms, passages,
sentences, or websites, and then I'll
go group similar text objects together.
So let's see an example, well, here
you don't really see text objects, but
I just used some shapes to denote
objects that can be grouped together.
Now if I ask you, what are some natural
structures or natural groups where you,
if you look at it and you might agree that
we can group these objects based on chips,
or their locations on this
two dimensional space.
So we got the three clusters in this case.
And they may not be so
much this agreement about
these three clusters but it really depends
on the perspective to look at the objects.
Maybe some of you have also seen
thing in a different way, so
we might get different clusters.
And you'll see another example
about this ambiguity more clearly.
But the main point of here is, the problem
is actually not so well defined.
And the problem lies in
how to define similarity.
And what do you mean by similar objects?
Now this problem has to be
clearly defined in order to have
a well defined clustering problem.
And the problem is in general
that any two objects can be similar
depending on how you look at them.
So for example, this will kept
the two words like car and horse.
So are the two words similar?
Well, it depends on how if
we look at the physical
properties of car and
horse they are very different but
if you look at them functionally,
a car and a horse,
can both be transportation tools.
So in that sense, they may be similar.
So as we can see, it really depends on
our perspective, to look at the objects.
And so it ought to make
the clustering problem well defined.
A user must define the perspective for
assessing similarity.
And we call this perspective
the clustering bias.
And when you define a clustering problem,
it's important to specify
your perspective for
similarity or for defining
the similarity that will be
used to group similar objects.
because otherwise,
the similarity is not well defined and
one can have different
ways to group objects.
So let's look at the example here.
You are seeing some objects,
or some shapes,
that are very similar to what you
have seen on the first slide, but
if I ask you to group these objects,
again, you might
feel there is more than here
than on the previous slide.
For example, you might think, well, we
can steer a group by ships, so that would
give us cluster that looks like this.
However, you might also feel that,
well, maybe the objects can be
grouped based on their sizes.
So that would give us a different way
to cluster the data if we look at
the size and
look at the similarity in size.
So as you can see clearly here,
depending on the perspective,
we'll get different clustering result.
So that also clearly tells us that in
order to evaluate the clustering without,
we must use perspective.
Without perspective, it's very hard to
define what is the best clustering result.
So there are many examples
of text clustering setup.
And so for example, we can cluster
documents in the whole text collection.
So in this case,
documents are the units to be clustered.
We may be able to cluster terms.
In this case, terms are objects.
And a cluster of terms can be used to
define concept, or theme, or a topic.
In fact, there's a topic models that you
have seen some previous lectures can
give you cluster of terms in some
sense if you take terms with
high probabilities from word distribution.
Another example is just to cluster any
text segments, for example, passages,
sentences, or any segments that you can
extract the former larger text objects.
For example, we might extract the order
text segments about the topic,
let's say, by using a topic model.
Now once we've got those
text objects then we can
cluster the segments that we've got to
discover interesting clusters that
might also ripple in the subtopics.
So this is a case of combining text
clustering with some other techniques.
And in general you will
see a lot of text mining
can be accurate combined in
a flexible way to achieve
the goal of doing more sophisticated
mining and analysis of text data.
We can also cluster fairly
large text objects and by that,
I just mean text objects may
contain a lot of documents.
So for example, we might cluster websites.
Each website is actually
compose of multiple documents.
Similarly, we can also cluster articles
written by the same author, for example.
So we can trigger all the articles
published by also as one unit for
clustering.
In this way, we might group authors
together based on whether they're
published papers or similar.
For the more text clusters will be for
the cluster to generate a hierarchy.
That's because we can in general cluster
any text object at different levels.
So more generally why is
text clustering interesting?
Well, it's because it's a very
useful technique for text mining,
particularly exploratory text analysis.
And so a typical scenario is that
you were getting a lot of text data,
let's say all the email messages
from customers in some time period,
all the literature articles, etc.
And then you hope to get a sense
about what are the overall content of
the connection, so for example,
you might be interested in getting
a sense about major topics,
or what are some typical or
representative documents
in the connection.
And clustering to help
us achieve this goal.
We sometimes also want to link
a similar text objects together.
And these objects might be
duplicated content, for example.
And in that case,
such a technique can help us remove
redundancy and remove duplicate documents.
Sometimes they are about
the same topic and
by linking them together we can have
more complete coverage of a topic.
We may also used text clustering to create
a structure on the text data and sometimes
we can create a hierarchy of structures
and this is very useful for problems.
We may also use text clustering to induce
additional features to represent text
data when we cluster documents together,
we can treat each cluster as a feature.
And then we can say when
a document is in this cluster and
then the feature value would be one.
And if a document is not in this cluster,
then the feature value is zero.
And this helps provide additional
discrimination that might be used for
text classification as
we will discuss later.
So there are, in general,
many applications of text clustering.
And I just thought of
two very specific ones.
One is to cluster search results, for
example, [INAUDIBLE] search engine
can cluster such results so
that the user can see overall structure
of the results of return the fall query.
And when the query's ambiguous this
is particularly useful because
the clusters likely represent
different senses of ambiguous word.
Another application is to understand the
major complaints from customers based on
their emails, right.
So in this case,
we can cluster email messages and
then find in the major
clusters from there,
we can understand what are the major
complaints about them.
[MUSIC]