[SOUND]
This lecture
is a continuing discussion of Generative
Probabilistic Models for text clustering.
In this lecture, we are going to continue
talking about the text clustering,
particularly, the Generative
Probabilistic Models.
So this is a slide that you have seen
earlier where we have written down
the likelihood function for
a document with two
distributions, being a two component
mixed model for document clustering.
Now in this lecture, we're going to
generalize this to include the k clusters.
Now if you look at the formula and think
about the question, how to generalize it,
you'll realize that all we need is to add
more terms, like what you have seen here.
So you can just add more thetas and
the probabilities of
thetas and the probabilities of
generating d from those thetas.
So this is precisely what we
are going to use and this is
the general presentation of the mixture
model for document clustering.
So as more cases would follow these
steps in using a generating model first,
think about our data.
And so in this case our data
is a collection of documents,
end documents denoted by d sub i,
and then we talk about the other models,
think of other modelling.
In this case, we design a mixture
of k unigram language models.
It's a little bit different from the topic
model, but we have similar parameters.
We have a set of theta i's that
denote that our distributions
corresponding to the k
unigram language models.
We have p of each theta i as
a probability of selecting
each of the k distributions
we generate the document.
Now note that although our goal
is to find the clusters and
we actually have used a more general
notion of a probability of each
cluster and this as you will see later,
will allow us to assign
a document to the cluster
that has the highest probability of
being able to generate the document.
So as a result,
we can also recover some other interesting
properties, as you will see later.
So the model basically would make
the following assumption about
the generation of a document.
We first choose a theta i according
to probability of theta i, and
then generate all the words in
the document using this distribution.
Note that it's important that we
use this distribution all
the words in the document.
This is very different from topic model.
So the likelihood function would
be like what you are seeing here.
So you can take a look
at the formula here,
we have used the different notation
here in the second line of this equation.
You are going to see now
the notation has been changed
to use unique word in the vocabulary,
in the product
instead of particular
position in the document.
So from X subject to W,
is a change of notation and
this change allows us to show
the estimation formulas more easily.
And you have seen this change also
in the topic model presentation, but
it's basically still just a product of
the probabilities of all the words.
And so
with the likelihood function, now we can
talk about how to do parameter estimation.
Here we can simply use
the maximum likelihood estimator.
So that's just a standard
way of doing things.
So all should be familiar to you now.
It's just a different model.
So after we have estimated parameters,
how can we then allocate
clusters to the documents?
Well, let's take a look at
the this situation more closely.
So we just repeated the parameters
here for this mixture model.
Now if you think about what we can
get by estimating such a model,
we can actually get more information than
what we need for doing clustering, right?
So theta i for example,
represents the content of cluster i,
this is actually a by-product, it can help
us summarize what the cluster is about.
If you look at the top
terms in this cluster or
in this word distribution and they will
tell us what the cluster is about.
p of theta i can be interpreted as
indicating the size of cluster because it
tells us how likely the cluster would
be used to generate the document.
The more likely a cluster is
used to generate a document,
we can assume the larger
the cluster size is.
Note that unlike in PLSA and
this probability of theta
i is not dependent on d.
Now you may recall that the topic
you chose at each document
actually depends on d.
That means each document can have
a potentially different choice of topics,
but here we have a generic choice
probability for all the documents.
But of course, even a particular document
that we still have to infer which
topic is more likely to
generate the document.
So in that sense,
we can still have a document
dependent probability of clusters.
So now let's look at the key problem
of assigning documents to clusters or
assigning clusters to documents.
So that's the computer c sub d here and
this will take one of the values in
the range of one through k to indicate
which cluster should be assigned to d.
Now first you might think about
a way to use likelihood on it and
that is to assign d to the cluster
corresponding to the topic of theta i,
that most likely has
been used to generate d.
So that means we're going to choose
one of those distributions that
gives d the highest probability.
In other words,
we see which distribution has the content
that matches our d at the [INAUDIBLE].
Intuitively that makes sense,
however, this approach
does not consider the size of clusters,
which is also a available to us and
so a better way is to use
the likelihood together with the prior,
in this case the prior is p of theta i.
And together, that is, we're going to
use the base formula to compute
the posterior probability of theta,
given d.
And if we choose theta .based
on this posterior probability,
we would have the following formula that
you see here on the bottom of this slide.
And in this case, we're going to choose
the theta that has a large P of theta i,
that means a large cluster and
also a high probability of generating d.
So we're going to favor
a cluster that's large and
also consistent with the document.
And that intuitively makes
sense because the chance of
a document being a large cluster is
generally higher than in a small cluster.
So this means once we can estimate
the parameters of the model,
then we can easily solve
the problem of document clustering.
So next, we'll have to discuss how to
actually compute
the estimate of the model.
[MUSIC]