[SOUND]
This lecture
is a continuing discussion of generative
probabilistic models for tax classroom.
In this lecture, we're going to
do a finishing discussion of
generative probabilistic models for
text crossing.
So this is a slide that you have seen
before and here, we show how we define
the mixture model for text crossing and
what the likelihood function looks like.
And we can also compute
the maximum likelihood estimate,
to estimate the parameters.
In this lecture, we're going to do talk
more about how exactly we're going to
compute the maximum likelihood estimate.
As in most cases the Algorithm can be used
to solve this problem for mixture models.
So here's the detail of this Algorithm for
document clustering.
Now, if you have understood
how Algorithm works for
topic models like TRSA, and
I think here it would be very similar.
And we just need to adapt a little
bit to this new mixture model.
So as you may recall Algorithm starts with
initialization of all the parameters.
So this is the same as what
happened before for topic models.
And then we're going to repeat
until the likelihood converges and
in each step we'll do E step and M step.
In M step,
we're going to infer which distribution
has been used to generate each document.
So I have to introduce
a hidden variable Zd for
each document and this variable could take
a value from the range of 1 through k,
representing k different distributions.
More specifically basically, we're going
to apply base rules to infer which
distribution is more likely to
have generated this document, or
computing the posterior probability of
the distribution given the document.
And we know it's proportional
to the probability
of selecting this
distribution p of Z the i.
And the probability of generating this
whole document from the distribution which
is the product of the probabilities of
world for this document as you see here.
Now, as you all clear this use for
kind of remember,
the normalizer or
the constraint on this probability.
So in this case, we know
the constraint on this probability in
E-Step is that all the probabilities
of Z equals i must sum to 1.
Because the documented must have been
generated from precisely one of these k
topics.
So the probability of being generated
from each of them should sum to 1.
And if you know this constraint, then
you can easily compute this distribution
as long as you know what
it is proportional to.
So once you compute this product that
you see here, then you simply normalize
these probabilities,
to make them sum to 1 over all the topics.
So that's E-Step, after E-Step we
want to know which distribution is
more likely to have generated this
document d, and which is unlikely.
And then in M-Step we're going to
re-estimate all the parameters based on
the in further z values or in further
knowledge about which distribution
has been used to generate which document.
So the re-estimation involves two kinds
of parameters 1 is p of theta and
this is the probability of selecting
a particular distribution.
Before we observe anything,
we don't have any knowledge about
which cluster is more likely.
But after we have observed
that these documents,
then we can crack the evidence to
infer which cluster is more likely.
And so this is proportional to the sum of
the probability of Z
sub d j is equal to i.
And so this gives us all
the evidence about using topic i,
theta i to generate a document.
Pull them together and again,
we normalize them into probabilities.
So this is for key of theta sub i.
Now the other kind of parameters
are the probabilities of words in each
distribution, in each cluster.
And this is very similar
to the case piz and
here we just report the kinds
of words that are in
documents that are inferred
to have been generated
from a particular topic of theta i here.
This would allows to then
estimate how many words have
actually been generated from theta i.
And then we'll normalize again these
accounts in the probabilities so
that the probabilities on all
the words would sum to up.
Note that it's very important to
understand these constraints as
they are precisely the normalizing
in all these formulas.
And it's also important to know
that the distribution is over what?
For example, the probability of
theta is over all the k topics,
that's why these k
probabilities will sum to 1.
Whereas the probability of a word given
theta is a probability distribution
over all the words.
So there are many probabilities and
they have to sum to 1.
So now, let's take a look at
a simple example of two clusters.
I've two clusters,
I've assumed some initialized values for
the two distributions.
And let's assume we randomly
initialize two probability of
selecting each cluster as 0.5,
so equally likely.
And then let's consider one
document that you have seen here.
There are two occurrences of text and
two occurrences of mining.
So there are four words together and
medical and
health did not occur in this document.
So let's think about the hidden variable.
Now for each document then we
much use a hidden variable.
And before in piz,
we used one hidden variable for
each work because that's
the output from one mixture model.
So in our case the output
from the mixture model or
the observation from mixture
model is a document, not a word.
So now we have one hidden variable
attached to the document.
Now that hidden variable must tell us
which distribution has been used to
generate the document.
So it's going to take two values,
one and two to indicate the two topics.
So now how do we infer which
distribution has been used generally d?
Well it's been used base rule,
so it looks like this.
In order for the first topic
theta 1 to generate a document,
two things must happen.
First, theta sub 1 must
have been selected.
So it's given by p of theta 1.
Second, it must have also be generating
the four words in the document.
Namely, two occurrences of text and
two occurrences of sub mining.
And that's why you see the numerator
has the product of the probability of
selecting theta 1 and the probability of
generating the document from theta 1.
So the denominator is just the sum of
two possibilities of generality in
this document.
And you can plug in the numerical
values to verify indeed in this case,
the document is more likely
to be generated from theta 1,
much more likely than from theta 2.
So once we have this probability,
we can easily compute the probability
of Z equals 2, given this document.
How?
Well, we can use the constraint.
That's going to be 1 minus 100 over 101.
So now it's important that you note
that in such a computation there
is a potential problem of underflow.
And that is because if you look at the
original numerator and the denominator,
it involves the competition of
a product of many small probabilities.
Imagine if a document has many words and
it's going to be a very small value here
that can cause the problem of underflow.
So to solve the problem,
we can use a normalize.
So here you see that we take
a average of all these two math
solutions to compute average at
the screen called a theta bar.
And this average distribution
would be comparable to
each of these distributions in terms
of the quantities or the magnitude.
So we can then divide the numerator and
the denominator both by this normalizer.
So basically this normalizes
the probability of generating
this document by using this
average word distribution.
So you can see the normalizer is here.
And since we have used exactly the same
normalizer for the numerator and
the denominator.
The whole value of this expression is not
changed but by doing this normalization
you can see we can make the numerators and
the denominators more manageable
in that the overall value is not
going to be very small for each.
And thus we can avoid
the underflow problem.
In some other times we sometimes
also use logarithm of the product
to convert this into a sum
of log of probabilities.
This can help preserve precision as well,
but
in this case we cannot use
algorithm to solve the problem.
Because there is a sum in the denominator,
but
this kind of normalizes can be
effective for solving this problem.
So it's a technique that's sometimes
useful in other situations in other
situations as well.
Now let's look at the M-Step.
So from the E-Step we can see our estimate
of which distribution is more likely to
have generated a document at d.
And you can see d1's more like
got it from the first topic,
where is d2 is more like
from second topic, etc.
Now, let's think about what we
need to compute in M-step well
basically we need to
re-estimate all the parameters.
First, look at p of theta 1 and
p of theta 2.
How do we estimate that?
Intuitively you can just pool together
these z, the probabilities from E-step.
So if all of these documents say,
well they're more likely from theta 1,
then we intuitively would give
a higher probability to theta 1.
In this case,
we can just take an average of these
probabilities that you see here and
we've obtain a 0.6 for theta 1.
So 01 is more likely and then theta 2.
So you can see probability of
02 would be natural in 0.4.
What about these word of probabilities?
Well we do the same, and
intuition is the same.
So we're going to see,
in order to estimate the probabilities
of words in theta 1,
we're going to look at which documents
have been generated from theta 1.
And we're going to pull together the words
in those documents and normalize them.
So this is basically what I just said.
More specifically, we're going to do for
example, use all the kinds of text in
these documents for estimating
the probability of text given theta 1.
But we're not going to use their
raw count or total accounts.
Instead, we can do that discount them
by the probabilities that each document
is likely been generated from theta 1.
So these gives us some
fractional accounts.
And then these accounts
would be then normalized
in order to get the probability.
Now, how do we normalize them?
Well these probability of
these words must assign to 1.
So to summarize our discussion of
generative models for clustering.
Well we show that a slight variation
of topic model can be used for
clustering documents.
And this also shows the power
of generating models in general.
By changing the generation assumption and
changing the model slightly we can achieve
different goals, and we can capture
different patterns and types of data.
So in this case, each cluster is
represented by unigram language model
word distribution and
that is similar to topic model.
So here you can see the word distribution
actually generates a term cluster
as a by-product.
A document that is generated by first
choosing a unigram language model.
And then generating all the words
in the document are using
just a single language model.
And this is very different from again
copy model where we can generate
the words in the document by using
multiple unigram language models.
And then the estimated model parameters
are given both topic characterization
of each cluster and
the probabilistic assignment of
each document into a cluster.
And this probabilistic assignment
sometimes is useful for some applications.
But if we want to achieve
harder clusters mainly to
partition documents into
disjointed clusters.
Then we can just force a document into
the cluster corresponding to the words
distribution that's most likely
to have generated the document.
We've also shown that the Algorithm can
be used to compute the maximum likelihood
estimate.
And in this case, we need to use a special
number addition technique
to avoid underflow.
[MUSIC]