[SOUND] This lecture is about
how to mine text data with
social network as context.
In this lecture we're going to continue
discussing contextual text mining.
In particular, we're going to look at
the social network of others as context.
So first, what's our motivation for using
network context for analysis of text?
The context of a text
article can form a network.
For example the authors
of research articles
might form collaboration networks.
But authors of social media content
might form social networks.
For example,
in Twitter people might follow each other.
Or in Facebook as people might
claim friends of others, etc.
So such context connects
the content of the others.
Similarly, locations associated with
text can also be connected to form
geographical network.
But in general you can can imagine
the metadata of the text data
can form some kind of network
if they have some relations.
Now there is some benefit in
jointly analyzing text and
its social network context or
network context in general.
And that's because we can use network to
impose some constraints on topics of text.
So for example it's reasonable
to assume that authors
connected in collaboration networks
tend to write about the similar topics.
So such heuristics can be used
to guide us in analyzing topics.
Text also can help characterize the
content associated with each subnetwork.
And this is to say that both
kinds of data, the network and
text, can help each other.
So for example the difference in
opinions expressed that are in
two subnetworks can be reviewed by
doing this type of joint analysis.
So here briefly you could use a model
called a network supervised topic model.
In this slide we're going to
give some general ideas.
And then in the next slide we're
going to give some more details.
But in general in this part of the course
we don't have enough time to cover
these frontier topics in detail.
But we provide references
that would allow you to
read more about the topic
to know the details.
But it should still be useful
to know the general ideas.
And to know what they can do to know
when you might be able to use them.
So the general idea of network
supervised topic model is the following.
Let's start with viewing
the regular topic models.
Like if you had an LDA as
sorting optimization problem.
Of course, in this case,
the optimization objective
function is a likelihood function.
So we often use maximum likelihood
estimator to obtain the parameters.
And these parameters will give us
useful information that we want to
obtain from text data.
For example, topics.
So we want to maximize the probability
of tests that are given the parameters
generally denoted by number.
The main idea of incorporating network is
to think about the constraints that
can be imposed based on the network.
In general,
the idea is to use the network to
impose some constraints on
the model parameters, lambda here.
For example,
the text at adjacent nodes of the network
can be similar to cover similar topics.
Indeed, in many cases,
they tend to cover similar topics.
So we may be able to smooth
the topic distributions
on the graph on the network so
that adjacent nodes will have
very similar topic distributions.
So they will share a common
distribution on the topics.
Or have just a slight variations of the
topic of distributions, of the coverage.
So, technically, what we can do
is simply to add a network and
use the regularizers to the likelihood
of objective function as shown here.
So instead of just optimize
the probability of test
data given parameters lambda, we're
going to optimize another function F.
This function combines the likelihood with
a regularizer function called R here.
And the regularizer defines
the the parameters lambda and the Network.
It tells us basically
what kind of parameters are preferred
from a network constraint perspective.
So you can easily see this is in effect
implementing the idea of imposing
some prior on the model parameters.
Only that we're not necessary
having a probabilistic model, but
the idea is the same.
We're going to combine the two in
one single objective function.
So, the advantage of this idea
is that it's quite general.
Here the top model can be any
generative model for text.
It doesn't have to be PLSA or
LEA, or the current topic models.
And similarly,
the network can be also in a network.
Any graph that connects
these text objects.
This regularizer can
also be any regularizer.
We can be flexible in capturing different
heuristics that we want to capture.
And finally,
the function F can also vary, so
there can be many different
ways to combine them.
So, this general idea is actually quite,
quite powerful.
It offers a general approach
to combining these different
types of data in single
optimization framework.
And this general idea can really
be applied for any problem.
But here in this paper reference here,
a particular instantiation
called a NetPLSA was started.
In this case, it's just for
instantiating of PLSA to incorporate this
simple constraint imposed by network.
And the prior here is the neighbors on
the network must have
similar topic distribution.
They must cover similar
topics in similar ways.
And that's basically
what it says in English.
So technically we just have
a modified objective function here.
Let's define both the texts you can
actually see in the network graph G here.
And if you look at this formula,
you can actually recognize
some part fairly familiarly.
Because they are, they should be
fairly familiar to you by now.
So can you recognize which
part is the likelihood for
the test given the topic model?
Well if you look at it, you will see this
part is precisely the PLSA log-likelihood
that we want to maximize when we
estimate parameters for PLSA alone.
But the second equation shows some
additional constraints on the parameters.
And in particular,
we'll see here it's to measure
the difference between the topic
coverage at node u and node v.
The two adjacent nodes on the network.
We want their distributions to be similar.
So here we are computing the square
of their differences and
we want to minimize this difference.
And note that there's a negative sign in
front of this sum, this whole sum here.
So this makes it possible to find
the parameters that are both to
maximize the PLSA log-likelihood.
That means the parameters
will fit the data well and,
also to respect that this
constraint from the network.
And this is the negative
sign that I just mentioned.
Because this is an negative sign,
when we maximize this
object in function we'll actually
minimize this statement term here.
So if we look further in
this picture we'll see
the results will weight of
edge between u and v here.
And that space from out network.
If you have a weight that says well,
these two nodes are strong
collaborators of researchers.
These two are strong connections
between two people in a social network.
And they would have weight.
Then that means it would be more important
that they're topic coverages are similar.
And that's basically what it says here.
And finally you see
a parameter lambda here.
This is a new parameter to control
the influence of network constraint.
We can see easily, if lambda is set to 0,
we just go back to the standard PLSA.
But when lambda is set to a larger value,
then we will let the network
influence the estimated models more.
So as you can see, the effect here is
that we're going to do basically PLSA.
But we're going to also try
to make the topic coverages
on the two nodes that are strongly
connected to be similar.
And we ensure their coverages are similar.
So here are some of the several results,
from that paper.
This is slide shows the record
results of using PLSA.
And the data here is DBLP data,
bibliographic data,
about research articles.
And the experiments have to do with
using four communities of applications.
IR information retrieval.
DM stands for data mining.
ML for machinery and web.
There are four communities of articles,
and we were hoping
to see that the topic mining can help
us uncover these four communities.
But from these assembled topics that you
have seen here that are generated by PLSA.
And PLSA is unable to generate
the four communities that
correspond to our intuition.
The reason was because they
are all mixed together and
there are many words that
are shared by these communities.
So it's not that easy to use
four topics to separate them.
If we use more topics,
perhaps we will have more coherent topics.
But what's interesting is that if we
use the NetPLSA where the network,
the collaboration network in this case of
authors is used to impose constraints.
And in this case we also use four topics.
But Ned Pierre said we gave
much more meaningful topics.
So here we'll see that these topics
correspond well to the four communities.
The first is information retrieval.
The second is data mining.
Third is machine learning.
And the fourth is web.
So that separation was mostly
because of the influence of network
where with leverage is
a collaboration network information.
Essentially the people that
form a collaborating network
would then be kind of assumed
to write about similar topics.
And that's why we're going to
have more coherent topics.
And if you just listen to text data
alone based on the occurrences,
you won't get such coherent topics.
Even though a topic model, like PLSA or
LDA also should be able to
pick up co-occurring words.
So in general the topics
that they generate represent
words that co-occur each other.
But still they cannot generate such
a coherent results as NetPLSA,
showing that the network
contest is very useful here.
Now a similar model could have been also
useful to to characterize the content
associated with each
subnetwork of collaborations.
So a more general view of text
mining in context of network is you
treat text as living in a rich
information network environment.
And that means we can connect all the
related data together as a big network.
And text data can be associated with
a lot of structures in the network.
For example, text data can be associated
with the nodes of the network, and
that's basically what we just
discussed in the NetPLSA.
But text data can be associated with age
as well, or paths or even subnetworks.
And such a way to represent texts
that are in the big environment of
all the context information
is very powerful.
Because it allows to analyze all the data,
all the information together.
And so in general, analysis of text
should be using the entire network
information that's
related to the text data.
So here's one suggested reading.
And this is the paper about NetPLSA where
you can find more details about the model
and how to make such a model.
[MUSIC]